<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Investigating Novel Mathematics Tasks for Engaging in Conceptual Talk with English Learners]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>491411.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>491411</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Margret Hjalmarson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mhjalmar@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925186</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Millions of students in the U.S. are identified as English-language learners. However, there is still limited research about the design of tasks and curriculum that best support their mathematics learning. This project will examine how learners use mathematics language and concepts in eighth-grade. The study will include interviews with individuals, pairs, and small groups to explore how students discuss their mathematical thinking and use language to describe mathematics concepts. The products of the work include mathematics tasks and design principles that can be used to create future tasks. In addition, the investigation examines a critical moment in students' education since middle school is when students are learning concepts important for algebra and geometry that are the foundation of many STEM professions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will investigate the processes associated with the learning of mathematical concepts and practices by students who are designated as "English Learners" in the eighth grade. The focus of the work is to understand how to design tasks to support the development of conceptual understanding, practices, and uses of language in mathematics. The mathematical concepts of equivalence and transformation are the center of the investigation since these are foundational mathematical ideas for algebra, geometry and statistics. Two research questions frame the inquiry: 1) How do English Learners, in interaction with others, learn mathematical concepts, practices, and uses of language? and 2) What conditions of activity design support or constrain English Learners' participation for learning concepts, practices, and language? The research design includes multiple phases from individual interviews, to paired interviews to small group tasks in order to refine the tasks and explore concepts, practices and uses of language. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported by NSF's EDU Core Research (ECR) program. The ECR program emphasizes fundamental STEM education research that generates foundational knowledge in the field. Investments are made in critical areas that are essential, broad and enduring: STEM learning and STEM learning environments, broadening participation in STEM, and STEM workforce development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400767</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jill</FirstName>
<LastName>DePiper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jill N DePiper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jdepipe@wested.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000648823</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Haiwen</FirstName>
<LastName>Chu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Haiwen Chu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[achu@wested.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000763727</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[WestEd]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN FRANCISCO</CityName>
<ZipCode>941071242</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4156153136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[730 HARRISON ST FL 5]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WNCAQMKJ7WZ9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESTED</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>WNCAQMKJ7WZ9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[WestEd]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN FRANCISCO</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941071271</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[730 HARRISON ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>798000</Code>
<Text>ECR-EDU Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~491411</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
