<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Zero Emission Vehicle Initiative to Support Future Automotive Technicians]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>270800.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>270800</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Davis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdavis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project at San Diego Miramar College aims to support the rapid transition to a Zero-Emission California by developing a Zero-Emission Vehicle Initiative (ZEVI) in collaboration with local sustainability initiatives, high schools, and regional industry partners. The initiative aligns with a recent California Executive Order (N-79-20) and Clean Cars II Regulations that requires a shift from internal combustion engines (ICE) to zero-emission vehicles (ZEVs) for cars and passenger trucks by 2035 and for medium and heavy-duty vehicles by 2045. Over the three-year project, approximately 50 students will be recruited to complete credit-bearing courses, resulting in industry validated certificates and degrees that will provide a path to high-demand and family sustaining jobs in the electric vehicle (EV) service field.  This will be accomplished through curriculum development and improvement projects with the input of regional employers, coupled with enhanced professional development for automotive faculty at the college.  To recruit additional students, Miramar College will establish a summer EV exploratory program for high school students interested in pursuing career opportunities in this field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The motivating rationale stems from the significant growth in alternative-fueled vehicles in California, particularly plug-in electric vehicles, which has been accelerated by government led support. California leads the nation in ZEV adoption, with increased consumer interest in electric vehicles over the past five years.  This rapid adoption of ZEVs has created a need for a qualified skilled technical workforce with appropriate experience in EV technology.  In this project, Miramar College will (1) develop an accessible high-voltage safety curriculum, (2) establish a pathway for high school recruitment, (3) develop a strategy to engage current and incumbent automotive workers, (4) implement a professional development strategy to support Miramar faculty, and (5) strengthen partnerships with regional employers that will validate the new curriculum and serve as a destination for Miramar College students.  Through this project, historically underserved students in the San Diego area will have increased opportunities to enter the ZEV workforce.  This project is funded by the Advanced Technological Education program that focuses on the education of technicians for the advanced-technology fields that drive the Nation's economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400853</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Kennedy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin E Kennedy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mkennedy@sdccd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000962710</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Monroy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan C Monroy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rmonroy@sdccd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000943517</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SAN DIEGO COMMUNITY COLLEGE DISTRICT]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN DIEGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>921114902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6193882600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7250 MESA COLLEGE DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>51</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA51</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>S8E4H9AYQT18</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN DIEGO COMMUNITY COLLEGE DISTRICT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>CR6NBGGLMMC6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SAN DIEGO COMMUNITY COLLEGE DISTRICT]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN DIEGO</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921114902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7250 MESA COLLEGE DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>51</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA51</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>741200</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~270800</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
