<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Synthesis of Heterometallic Single-Source Carbonaceous Precursors for Materials that Require a Carbon Modulation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>464405.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>152456</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Gilje</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwgilje@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the support of the Chemical Synthesis program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Evgeny Dikarev of the SUNY Albany will study prospective battery materials that require a carbon modulation to perform. Rechargeable batteries represent a critical component of the ever-growing energy storage field, facilitating a transition towards energetics based on the renewable and green energy sources.  This project is focused on preparing materials that are needed for the next generation of rechargeable battery. The project develops strategies to efficiently replace expensive, rare metals that are presently used with ones that are less expensive and more abundant such as sodium, magnesium, silicon, and iron. Battery safety issues also will be considered. The project lays a solid foundation for an innovative technology that can be broadly adopted by industry for the fabrication of advanced rechargeable battery materials. The project has an important outreach and community efforts component that will focus on a new Emerging Technology and Entrepreneurship program at SUNY Albany and summer program on chemical fingerprinting of “secret” household items designed for local high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop a new synthetic methodology for the preparation of prospective materials that require a carbon modulation to perform. Atomically-precise single-source carbonaceous precursors with functionalized ligands and with the proper A:M:M’:E (A = Li, Na, Mg; M/M’ = transition metals; E = F, P, Si, S) ratios for the target carbon-coated fluoride, phosphate, silicate, fluorophosphate, and fluorosulfate materials will be designed using molecular-architecture concepts based on model structures and synthesized in the course of this work. Such a wide selection of target materials is intended to demonstrate the potential of “all-in-one” heterometallic precursor technique for the preparation of not just a single mixed-metal phase, but rather a composite carbon-coated nanocrystalline architecture required for advanced energy storage applications. The major practical outcome of this research is to demonstrate that single-source precursor approach facilitates multimetallic carbon-coated cathode materials with unique characteristics such as purity, exact stoichiometry, low preparation temperature, nanosized particles morphology, and, especially, highly homogeneous element distribution. In addition, the project will train undergraduate and graduate students in areas related to modern battery technologies. There is also a component that introduces high school students to elemental crystallography.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400091</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Evgeny</FirstName>
<LastName>Dikarev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Evgeny V Dikarev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[edikarev@albany.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000493030</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Albany]]></Name>
<CityName>ALBANY</CityName>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5184374974</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 WASHINGTON AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NHH3T1Z96H29</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>NHH3T1Z96H29</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University at Albany]]></Name>
<CityName>ALBANY</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 WASHINGTON AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>687800</Code>
<Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~152456</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
