<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Enantioenriched Silanols as a Platform for Discovery for Asymmetric Catalysis]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>575000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>575000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sarah Wengryniuk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sewold@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928679</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the support of the Chemical Catalysis Program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Annaliese Franz of the University of California, Davis will study the development of new silicon-based molecules and their formation of structurally-defined complexes with metals. These complexes will be studied as catalysts for applications to the efficient synthesis of organic materials and renewable polymers that are used in technology, medicine, and daily life. The use of catalysts is important for increasing industrial efficiency and reducing waste production, and silicon is the second most abundant element in the earth's crust. As such this research will address issues of sustainability and provide opportunities to prepare new chemical structures for discovery in chemistry and catalysis. This project will also train undergraduate and graduate students to develop technical and critical thinking skills for chemical synthesis and catalysis. Professor Franz will also actively engage in STEM outreach activities including demonstrations and workshops for elementary and middle school girls to participate in hands-on activities and learn about catalysts, energy, and polymers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to develop innovative multi-functional silanol ligands, including access to Si-stereogenic compounds, with unique properties that can be exploited to design novel homogeneous chiral catalysts with the potential for high catalytic activity and stereoselectivity. The design and synthesis of new functionalized chiral silanol will be prepared and their metal-coordinating abilities, structural studies, stability, and catalytic activity will be examined in several bond activation reactions and photocatalytic applications. The structure, binding interactions, and mechanism of the new ligands and catalysts will be studied using various spectroscopy methods, kinetics, X-ray crystallography, and mass spectrometry, and also computational studies. This project will also contribute to training the next generation of scientists and broadening participation. Professor Franz will be engaged in mentoring and outreach activities to broaden participation in STEM, including demonstrations and workshops for elementary and middle school girls to participate in hands-on activities and learn about catalysts, energy, and polymers. Professor Franz will also design and implement new research-based courses for undergraduate students that will increase research opportunities for diverse first-year college students and transfer students to build critical skills that will help launch them into careers in science and technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400351</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Annaliese</FirstName>
<LastName>Franz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Annaliese K Franz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[akfranz@ucdavis.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000508733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>DAVIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1850 RESEARCH PARK DR STE 300]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TX2DAGQPENZ5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>DAVIS</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956186153</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1850 RESEARCH PARK DR, STE 300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>688400</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~575000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
