<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STEM Graduate Pathways for Marginalized Groups: A Critical Meta-Analysis of Preparation, Enrollment, and Completion Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>607573.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>607573</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jessaca Spybrook</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jspybroo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Although graduate school participation is increasing in the United States overall, students from marginalized groups in the fields of Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) do not attend graduate school as often as other groups. In particular, low participation in graduate school by women and students from certain races and ethnicities (i.e., Black, Hispanic, indigenous) continues to create disparities in the STEM workforce. Graduate preparation programs can help undergraduate students from marginalized groups enroll and succeed in STEM graduate degree programs. These programs can serve students in many ways, from providing mentorship, financial support, peer groups, or through combining multiple support structures. Understanding how students from these marginalized groups are supported in preparing for graduate programs in STEM fields is crucial to support and retain marginalized students in STEM fields, diversify the STEM workforce, and promote equity in STEM education and professions. This project will examine existing studies that focus on STEM graduate preparation programs to explore the approaches that help students apply for graduate school, enroll in a master's or doctoral program, and eventually graduate with an advanced degree. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Drawing from the theoretical foundations of intersectionality and critical capital theory, this project includes a systematic review and meta-analysis of quantitative studies that examine graduate preparation program interventions to increase preparation for, enrollment in, and completion of STEM graduate-level degree programs among marginalized groups. The project will (1) determine the overall effect of participation in graduate preparation programs on marginalized students' STEM graduate school preparation, enrollment, or degree completion; (2) identify which program components best support marginalized students' STEM graduate school preparation, enrollment, or degree completion; and (3) uncover which student identity groups do and do not have research on their participation in a graduate school preparation program. Multivariate models with robust variance estimation will be employed. Findings from this project will help the field understand to what extent graduate preparation programs work and specific systemic change levers that are most effective in improving outcomes for students from marginalized groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported by NSF's EDU Core Research (ECR) program. The ECR program emphasizes fundamental STEM education research that generates foundational knowledge in the field. Investments are made in critical areas that are essential, broad and enduring: STEM learning and STEM learning environments, broadening participation in STEM, and STEM workforce development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400502</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamaal</FirstName>
<LastName>Young</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jamaal Young</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jamaal.young@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000630089</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Renbarger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel L Renbarger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rrenbarger@fhi360.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000859732</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Wong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel M Wong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rwong2@utk.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000894739</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Family Health International]]></Name>
<CityName>DURHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>277012477</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195447040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[359 BLACKWELL STREET]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[SUITE 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VRAASTY11EA3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FAMILY HEALTH INTERNATIONAL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Family Health International]]></Name>
<CityName>DURHAM</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277012477</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[359 BLACKWELL STREET]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>798000</Code>
<Text>ECR-EDU Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8816</Code>
<Text>Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~607573</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
