<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel Grant: 8th IFAC Conference on Analysis and Design of Hybrid Systems, July 1-3, 2024]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eyad Abed</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eabed@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922303</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support students from institutions of higher learning in the United States to participate in the 8th IFAC Conference Series on Analysis and Design of Hybrid Systems (ADHS), to be held at the University of Colorado, Boulder during July 1-3, 2024. The field of hybrid systems explores the intricate interplay between discrete-event and continuous dynamics, an issue which arises frequently in modern technological systems. The award targets providing travel support for up to 20 students to attend this flagship conference. . The conference's overarching mission is to cultivate collaboration and facilitate the exchange of insights among researchers hailing from disciplines such as control engineering, computer science, and applied mathematics. Moreover, it extends its embrace to practitioners across a wide spectrum of application domains, spanning process industries, automotive, avionics, communication networks, energy systems, transportation networks, embedded systems, biology, manufacturing, and robotics. By bringing together these diverse perspectives and expertise, ADHS catalyzes innovation and fosters the cross-pollination of ideas to address complex challenges in the realm of hybrid systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will provide students with the unique opportunity to engage with field experts through attending session talks, immersing themselves in enlightening keynote presentations, and fostering valuable connections during social events. The diverse array of session talks will span numerous categories, encompassing the latest developments in areas such as specification, verification, control synthesis, machine learning, and more. These sessions serve as a conduit for students to be exposed to the forefront of cutting-edge research and advancements in hybrid systems. Moreover, the social events are conducive to interaction between students and both seasoned and emerging leaders across various domains. These interactions not only broaden students' perspectives but also nurture relationships that can prove instrumental in their academic and professional journeys. The conference will offer undergraduate and graduate students a chance to connect with senior peers, enriching conference interactions. The award places priority on funding travel expenses for students from underrepresented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400467</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Majid</FirstName>
<LastName>Zamani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Majid Zamani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[majid.zamani@colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000800508</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803090001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 MARINE ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SPVKK1RC2MZ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>BOULDER</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 MARINE ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>760700</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>791800</Code>
<Text>CPS-Cyber-Physical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>092E</Code>
<Text>Control systems &amp; applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1632</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8888</Code>
<Text>LEARNING &amp; INTELLIGENT SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~25000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
