<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Excellence in Research - Novel Cyclic Imides and Lactams from Oxidation of Pyrroles]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>405813.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>405813</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Richter-Addo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>grichter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927528</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the support of the Chemical Synthesis Program in the Chemistry Division and the Historically Black Colleges and Universities Excellence in Research (HBCU-EiR) program in the Office of Integrative Activities, Professor Sezgin Kiren of Winston Salem State University will study the synthesis of complex organic molecules from the oxidation of relatively low-cost and commercially available precursors. The molecules being targeted, namely novel cyclic imides and lactams, have been traditionally difficult to access but have potential use in pharmaceutical and material science. The research approach will allow for the generation of functionally diverse compound libraries containing these chemical motifs, and will provide additional chemical resources to other researchers interested in structure-activity relationships involving these derivatives. With this award, students from underrepresented backgrounds at Winston-Salem State University will receive high level training and mentoring in organic synthesis through hands-on research experiences, thus further facilitating their progress towards careers in STEM fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Cyclic imides and lactams and their derivatives represent significant classes of compounds of interest to both biological and materials chemistry. However, currently employed experimental methodology for their syntheses is not optimal and can be significantly improved and streamlined. The aim of the proposed research is to advance the ability of chemists to generate novel cyclic imides and lactams via oxidation of relatively low-cost pyrrole ring systems. After investigation of optimal oxidation conditions, structurally unique pyrroles will be employed to generate functionalized and privileged cyclic imide and lactam building blocks for further synthetic manipulation. More elaborate chemical entities, such as those present in the structures of valuable natural and unnatural complex molecules will be targeted. In this vein analogs of thalidomide, pomalidomide and lenalidomide will be accessible using this strategy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2401999</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sezgin</FirstName>
<LastName>Kiren</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sezgin Kiren</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kirens@wssu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000616167</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Winston-Salem State University]]></Name>
<CityName>WINSTON SALEM</CityName>
<ZipCode>271100003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3367503019</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 S MARTIN LUTHER KING JR DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>K54FKGWN2EN5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WINSTON-SALEM STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Winston-Salem State University]]></Name>
<CityName>WINSTON SALEM</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>271100003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 S MARTIN LUTHER KING JR DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>070Y00</Code>
<Text>HBCU-EiR - HBCU-Excellence in</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>112Z</Code>
<Text>Racial Equity in STEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~405813</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
