<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Excellence in Research: DISES EX: Using multipollutant mixture models to assess dynamic outcomes for humans in a socio-environmental system]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>749291.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>749291</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding how various environmental pollutants affect our health and well-being is crucial for creating healthier communities. This project focuses on how exposure to a mix of pollutants, such as chemicals found in everyday products and industrial waste, impacts stress levels in both individuals and neighborhoods. Unlike previous studies that look at one pollutant at a time, this research examines the combined effects of multiple pollutants, providing a more comprehensive picture of environmental health risks. Importantly, this study also explores how social, economic, and lifestyle factors influence who gets exposed to these pollutants and how they affect different communities. For example, people living in certain areas or with certain socioeconomic backgrounds might be more vulnerable to harmful exposures. By using publicly available health and environmental data, the project aims to develop better ways to assess and manage the risks associated with multiple pollutants. The results are being disseminated to help policymakers and public health officials create more effective strategies to protect public health, especially in communities that are most at risk. The insights gained from this study not only benefit local communities but also offer valuable knowledge applicable to regions facing similar environmental challenges worldwide. Moreover, this project enhances research capabilities at North Carolina A&amp;T State University, the nation’s largest Historically Black College and University (HBCU), by providing valuable research opportunities for students and fostering a learning environment that encourages scientific discovery and innovation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The exposome encompasses all the exposures an individual encounters throughout their life and their effects on health. Despite extensive research on single pollutants' effects, there is limited understanding of the impact of exposure to multiple pollutants simultaneously and the role of social, economic, and behavioral factors in exposure risk and stress-related outcomes. This interdisciplinary DISES-EX project aims to investigate how these factors influence exposure to and effects of multipollutant mixtures, including PFAS, metals, PAH, and PCBs, on individual and neighborhood stress. By leveraging publicly available health, environmental, and socioeconomic data, the project analyzes complex interactions between multiple pollutants and contextual factors shaping exposure patterns and health outcomes. Advanced statistical techniques are used to understand the relationships between these pollutants and stress within an integrated socio-environmental system. &lt;br/&gt;The study seeks to provide a comprehensive understanding of the collective impact of these pollutants on stress and to address current deficits in multipollutant modeling by incorporating social, economic, and behavioral frameworks. The findings offer valuable insights for researchers and policymakers, promoting a holistic approach to community health and well-being.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2401878</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Bollen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth A Bollen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bollen@unc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000189288</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emmanuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Obeng-Gyasi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emmanuel Obeng-Gyasi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eobenggyasi@ncat.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000795774</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina Agricultural & Technical State University]]></Name>
<CityName>GREENSBORO</CityName>
<ZipCode>274110002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3363347995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1601 E MARKET ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SKH5GMBR9GL3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA AGRICULTURAL AND TECHNICAL STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina Agricultural and Technical State University]]></Name>
<CityName>GREENSBORO</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>274110002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1601 E MARKET ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>070Y00</Code>
<Text>HBCU-EiR - HBCU-Excellence in</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1691</Code>
<Text>BE: DYN COUPLED NATURAL-HUMAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9278</Code>
<Text>HUMAN DIMENSIONS OF GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~749291</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
