<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EiR: Interactions between cover plant species may improve edaphic properties and strengthen microbial trophic interactions in the soil ecosystem]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Porras-Alfaro</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aporrasa@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922944</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Agricultural intensification and anthropogenic activities are altering soil ecosystems, their health, and services. To address these issues, cover crops are valuable tools for improving soil health by enhancing soil structure, fertility, organic matter, and moisture retention. They can also be used as a model to better understand biodiversity and its role on ecosystem functioning. The goal of this work is to study the role of cover crop species on soil properties. The project will use discover-based learning and integrates robust model soil system experiments with classroom activities to train students. The introduction of multi-omics approaches will benefit a broad range students and faculty at Alabama State University. The active participation of the PI, postdoctoral, graduate, and undergraduate students at local, regional, and national level forums will disseminate the findings of this project to the scientific community and society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Presently, little is known about the impact of cover crop species richness on soil ecosystem properties such as root coverage and traits, aggregate-size classes, nutrient composition, microbial diversity, and trophic interactions (protist-bacteria-fungi), which are essential for the stability and functioning of soil ecosystems. This study integrates biodiversity and ecosystem functioning (BEF) research with below ground soil-root level micro-heterogeneities and microbial trophic interactions. The project will provide new evidence on the impacts of cover crop species richness and their interactions (legume vs non-legume crop species) on edaphic properties and microbiome-metabolite co-assembly. In addition, this work will significantly advance our understanding of soil microbiomes, metabolomes, and complex trophic interactions by developing general microbial trophic- and metabolite-based frameworks that will improve predictions of the responses of soil biotic and abiotic properties to cover crop diversity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2401720</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Muhammad</FirstName>
<LastName>Saleem</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Muhammad Saleem</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[msaleem@alasu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000805569</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Alabama State University]]></Name>
<CityName>MONTGOMERY</CityName>
<ZipCode>361045714</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3342294243</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[915 S JACKSON ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLJWLMSNK627</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALABAMA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>Q2J8FSU3UDG3</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Alabama State University]]></Name>
<CityName>MONTGOMERY</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>361045732</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[915 S JACKSON ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>070Y00</Code>
<Text>HBCU-EiR - HBCU-Excellence in</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>112Z</Code>
<Text>Racial Equity in STEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~500000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
