<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Excellence in Research - Investigation of Amoebozoa Genome Complexity and the Evolution of Amoeboid Body Plan]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2028</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1069764.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1069764</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Fujita</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfujita@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927814</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Amoebozoa includes a diverse group of single cell microscopic eukaryotes primarily characterized by their movement and feeding mechanism through finger-like cytoplasmic projections called pseudopodia (false-feet). This group encompasses a wide array of microorganisms exhibiting diverse morphology and genomic complexity, inhabiting various environments such as marine, freshwater, and soil. Several Amoebozoa are also significant human parasites, contributing to health problems. Despite their importance, little is known about their genomic and cellular diversity. This project aims to investigate the genome complexity and the evolution of their unique amoeboid (cellular) body plan that underpins their remarkable diversity and ecological success. Results from this project will provide insights into the evolution of genome structure and cellular form in other similar eukaryotes. Through interdisciplinary training initiatives, particularly targeting African American women undergraduate students, the project aims to foster interest in evolutionary research and provide valuable research opportunities. Collaborations with other educational institutions will facilitate student exposure to high-quality research, paving the way for future careers in bioinformatics and data science. Moreover, efforts to enhance data science literacy through boot camps and curriculum integration will benefit both students and faculty, fostering broader engagement with genomics research. Outreach efforts include enhancing science education at K-12 levels and sparking curiosity in STEM through the use of the data and samples collected during the course of this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The supergroup Amoebozoa, characterized by its diverse morphology, behavior, ecology, and genomic complexity, holds an important evolutionary position as the closest relative of animals and fungi. This research aims to investigate two major evolutionary events within Amoebozoa using comparative genomics and cytology: genome complexity and the evolution of the amoeboid body plan. It is hypothesized that genetic innovations – including novel genes - have contributed to the extreme morphological and behavioral diversity observed within this group. Using a phylogenetic framework and genome sequences – some of which will be newly sequenced as part of this research - this project will investigate how several genomic features, such as genome size, nucleotide composition, gene expression, repetitive elements, and the evolution of new genes, have contributed to amoeboid structure and function. The genomics will be analyzed in conjunction with cytological data, which will provide morphological and cellular insights into the evolution of amoeboid structures across unicellular eukaryotes.  By integrating cytology and genomics, this project will test hypotheses regarding the evolutionary dynamics of amoeboid structures, including the presence of a shared genetic toolkit across eukaryotes and the ancestral origins of amoeboid life forms.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2401946</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yonas</FirstName>
<LastName>Tekle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yonas I Tekle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ytekle@spelman.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000596195</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Spelman College]]></Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303144399</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4042705897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[350 SPELMAN LN SW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ES69D58DJPE7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SPELMAN COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Spelman College]]></Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303144399</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[350 SPELMAN LN SW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>070Y00</Code>
<Text>HBCU-EiR - HBCU-Excellence in</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>112Z</Code>
<Text>Racial Equity in STEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~1069764</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
