<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Postdoctoral Fellowship: AAPF: Snapshots of Planet Formation Around Small Stars with Keck NIRC2 Polarimetry]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>330000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>110000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hans Krimm</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hkrimm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922761</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Briley Lewis is awarded an NSF Astronomy and Astrophysics Fellowship to carry out a program of research and education at the University of California, Santa Barbara. Lewis will contribute to cutting-edge instrumentation for the W.M. Keck Observatory in order to observe debris disks around low-mass stars in polarized light. Results from this project will advance our understanding of how planet formation occurs around smaller stars, and provide a novel observing capability for other astronomical investigations. For the educational component of this project, Lewis will create a series of planetarium shows featuring tactile resources accessible to blind and low-vision audiences for the Santa Barbara Natural History Museum. She will also develop and offer a disciplinary writing workshop series for graduate students in Physics and Astronomy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Polarimetry is a key technology for resolving dusty disks around other stars; historically, however, high-contrast polarimetric capabilities have been mostly restricted to observing bright stars due to limitations of adaptive optics systems. The investigator will create a data processing pipeline and perform calibrations and commissioning observations for the upcoming Keck NIRC2 polarimetry upgrade, making Keck II the largest telescope on which infrared (Y to L band) polarimetry capabilities will be available. This polarimetry mode will be able to work in conjunction with the existing facility-grade laser guide star adaptive optics system to uniquely target fainter and redder stars than those accessible by other facilities. The investigator will use this mode to complete a survey of debris disks around K- and M-dwarf stars and analyze trends in their composition and morphology to inform planet formation models.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/22/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/22/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2401654</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Briley</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Briley L Lewis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000884667</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lewis, Briley Lynn]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>90095</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931060001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>160900</Code>
<Text>NSF ASTRON &amp; ASTROPHY PSTDC FE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~110000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
