<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Postdoctoral Fellowship: MPS-Ascend: Laser Cooling Radioactive Molecules]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen McCloud</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmccloud@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928236</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Arian Jadbabaie is awarded an NSF Mathematical and Physical Sciences Ascending Postdoctoral Research Fellowship (NSF MPS-Ascend) to conduct a program of research and activities related to broadening participation by groups underrepresented in STEM. This fellowship to Dr. Jadbabaie  supports the research project entitled “Postdoctoral Fellowship: MPS-Ascend: Laser Cooling Radioactive Molecules” under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. The host institution for the fellowship is Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. Garcia Ruiz.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the precision spectroscopy of radioactive molecules and an attempt to demonstrate their first direct laser cooling. Successful cooling of such molecules will open the way for a new class of table-top experiments searching for physics beyond the Standard Model of particle physics.  While the Standard Model successfully describes a vast range of physical phenomena, it is known that it is not a complete theory.  Searches using high precision atomic, molecular and optical physics measurement techniques, such as the one enabled by this award, are one important avenue for constraining extensions of the Standard Model.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI plans to increase broadening participation in STEM by utilizing  science outreach at local Boston schools, to directly engage students and parents with compelling science demonstrations, create a network with local schools, and spread science opportunities. Next, the Fellow will become one of the main organizers of the event “Bridging Talents and Opportunities”, which will attract high school students, parents, teachers, and sponsors to the host institution, MIT. The event is focused on connecting students with research opportunities, mentors, and funding; sharing the lived experiences of scientists; and exposing students to captivating outreach. Finally, two students per year will be offered summer research opportunities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/25/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2402254</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arian</FirstName>
<LastName>Jadbabaie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arian Jadbabaie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000947305</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/25/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Jadbabaie, Arian]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<ZipCode>91125</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>187Y00</Code>
<Text>ASCEND - MPS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~200000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
