<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Postdoctoral Fellowship: MPS-Ascend: Towards Precision Physics: Calculating Neutron Beta Decay with Lattice Quantum Chromodynamics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen McCloud</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmccloud@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928236</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Zack Hall is awarded an NSF Mathematical and Physical Sciences Ascending Postdoctoral Research Fellowship (NSF MPS-Ascend) to conduct a program of research and activities related to broadening participation by groups underrepresented in STEM. This fellowship to Dr. Hall supports the research project entitled “Postdoctoral Fellowship: MPS-Ascend: Towards Precision Physics: Calculating Neutron Beta Decay with Lattice Quantum Chromodynamics” under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. The host institution for the fellowship is Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. Andre Walker-Loud.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the PI’s study of non-perturbative calculation of quantum electrodynamic (QED) corrections to the nucleon axial coupling, gA, which is critical in determining the nuclear neutron beta decay rate. Comparing to the lattice quantum chromodynamics (LQCD) estimations, where only strong QCD interactions are considered, results of experimental measurements contain both strong and electromagnetic contributions. The objective of the investigation is to encompass a QCD+QED approach to evaluate gA with mesons, baryons, and nucleon matrix elements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI plans to increase broadening participation in STEM by building on his previous experiences with designing and leading mentoring initiatives by actively working to provide access to quality mentors, improve science literacy, and facilitate opportunities for underrepresented minorities in STEM to gain valuable transferrable skills. The proposed work has several areas where graduate and undergraduate students can contribute to numerical calculations to hone their programming skills. Additionally, the PI will join existing out-reach programs at the host institution geared toward mentoring, establishing networks with STEM professionals, and building research skills for high school and college students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2402482</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zack</FirstName>
<LastName>Hall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>II</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zack B Hall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000951806</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hall, Zack B]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<ZipCode>947081914</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lawrence Berkeley National Labortatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947208169</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>187Y00</Code>
<Text>ASCEND - MPS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~200000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
