<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Postdoctoral Fellowship: MPS-Ascend: Probing Secondary Structure and Hydration in Nucleic Acids Using Chiral Selective Vibrational Sum Frequency Generation Spectroscopy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samy El-Shall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>selshall@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927416</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Ty Santiago is awarded an NSF Mathematical and Physical Sciences Ascending Postdoctoral Research Fellowship (NSF MPS-Ascend) to conduct a program of research and activities related to broaden participation by groups underrepresented in STEM. This fellowship to Dr. Santiago supports the research project entitled “MPS-Ascend: Probing secondary structure and hydration in Nucleic acids using chiral selective vibrational sum frequency generation spectroscopy” under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. The host institution for the fellowship is Yale University, and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. Elsa C. Y. Yan.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal intends to use chiral vibrational sum frequency generation (cSFG) spectroscopy to identify the vibrational signatures of DNA sequences that fold into model secondary structures. The cSFG responses that are unique to the macroscopic chirality of different DNA secondary structures will allow for differentiating DNA folding in situ and in real time. The cSFG spectroscopy will also be used to probe the hydration structures of DNA and the DNA-Peptide interactions, and the experimental cSFG spectra will be compared with computationally simulated spectra produced by collaborative efforts aimed at validating molecular models and developing computational tools for interpreting the cSFG spectra. Successful implementation of this work will introduce opportunities for future studies of DNA structural changes in response to temperature, pH, binding of small molecules or protein. The overall goal is to establish cSFG as a tool for studying secondary structures of DNA as well as biomolecular recognition, and the role that water plays in each.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI intends to participate in outreach activities to inspire young people to pursue careers in STEM. The PI is planning to serve as a panelist on the topic of graduate school application at Alabama State University, and to give an invited talk at Yale’s seminar series of Biological and Biomedical Sciences Diversity and Inclusion Collective. As a member of the Society for Advancement of Chicanos/Hispanics &amp; Native Americans in Science (SACNAS), the PI will volunteer as a judge for the poster contest and serve as a panelist in a Q&amp;A session organized by SACNAS. As a member of the Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion advocates in the Chemistry Department at Yale, the PI will host social togetherness events, trainings, and workshops to improve equity and inclusivity in the workplace, lab, and classroom.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2402247</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ty</FirstName>
<LastName>Santiago</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ty J Santiago</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000936381</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Santiago, Ty J]]></Name>
<CityName>North Branford</CityName>
<ZipCode>06471</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208107</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>187Y00</Code>
<Text>ASCEND - MPS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~200000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
