<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II: Video Game Tool for Navigating the College Admission Process]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>989117.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>989117</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lindsay Portnoy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lportnoy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928848</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader/commercial impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will address the critical issue of low college enrollment rates among underserved high school students. With limited access to guidance counselors, particularly in schools serving large minority populations, students often struggle to navigate the complex college preparation, admissions, and financial aid processes. By leveraging the power of gaming technology, this project aims to engage and educate youth about college-going habits and persistence strategies during their recreational gaming time. The innovative gaming system will provide a cost-effective solution to supplement the limited resources available for college counseling at under-resourced middle and high schools. The technology has the potential to become a key factor in the commercial success of the company, with school districts being the initial target market. This initiative not only enhances scientific and technological understanding but also addresses a significant societal challenge by promoting educational equity and increasing access to higher education for underserved communities. Ultimately, this project aligns with NSF's mission to advance national prosperity and welfare by empowering students with the knowledge and skills necessary to pursue post-secondary education and contribute to the nation's workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project aims to shift the college-going culture at under-resourced middle and high schools by developing an innovative video game that educates and prepares students for the college application process. The research objectives are to measure students' knowledge acquisition about college admissions criteria, deadlines, acceptance and enrollment processes, and financial aid options as they progress through the game's levels. The proposed research involves validating and refining the instruments and measures developed during the pilot phase to assess students' readiness based on their performance at each level. The anticipated technical results include a comprehensive set of reliable and valid measures that will enable schools and stakeholders to identify and address students' knowledge gaps, ultimately strengthening their pathways to college. This project is particularly crucial for underrepresented students who often face significant barriers during the college application process. By leveraging the engaging nature of video games, this project offers a unique and transformative approach to democratizing college access. The outcome of this research has the potential to set a new standard for learning solutions and progressive practices in the field of college preparation, providing a scalable and effective model for empowering all students to navigate the complex college admissions landscape successfully.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2402468</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Hayes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura Hayes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[LCobb2000@yahoo.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000862377</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[LEARNING NETWORK, LLC, THE]]></Name>
<CityName>ALLEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>750134873</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2142509930</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1915 NATCHEZ TRCE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>SW6LSA3HY843</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE LEARNING NETWORK, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[LEARNING NETWORK, LLC, THE]]></Name>
<CityName>ALLEN</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750134873</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1915 NATCHEZ TRCE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>537300</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6856</Code>
<Text>ARTIFICIAL INTELL &amp; COGNIT SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~989117</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
