<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MPS-Ascend: Matthew Yeung, Postdoctoral Fellowship:]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mun Chan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mchan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Matthew Yeung is awarded an NSF Mathematical and Physical Sciences Ascending Postdoctoral Research Fellowship (NSF MPS-Ascend) to conduct a program of research and activities related to broaden participation by groups underrepresented in STEM. This fellowship supports the research project entitled MPS-Ascend: Ultrafast Electron Dynamics in Solids under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. The host institution for the fellowship is the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. Nuh Gedik&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to elucidate the ultrafast electron dynamics in solids through comprehensive time-frequency characterization. A deeper understanding of the ultrafast electron dynamics in solids will pave the way for more compact and efficient extreme ultraviolet  sources, particularly beneficial for applications like nanoscale imaging. The project will utilize PHz field-sensitive detectors to elucidate underlying electron dynamics in solid-state higher-harmonic generation (sHHG). This includes resolving questions about temporal harmonic radiation profiles and the interplay between intra- and interband contributions. In addition, the transition from perturbative to non-perturbative regimes and methods to manipulate electron dynamics through crystal lattice perturbations and photonic structures will be investigated. These pioneering studies will deepen our understanding of ultrafast electron dynamics in solids, shedding light on solid-state higher-harmonic generation mechanism and guiding the manipulation of material properties on sub-femtosecond timescales.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through this project, the PI anticipates sharing the importance of this work by hosting summer lab visits and summer interns to inspire pre-college students and local community college students, respectively. By sharing personal experiences, the PI aims to encourage students to pursue careers in science, while highlighting alternative pathways to STEM careers. Furthermore, the PI plans to continue contributing to the Communication Lab at MIT, promoting broader dissemination of scientific research to diverse audience&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2402151</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>YEUNG</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew YEUNG</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<NSF_ID>000883678</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[YEUNG, Matthew]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>02139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>187Y00</Code>
<Text>ASCEND - MPS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7487</Code>
<Text>BROADENING PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~200000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
