<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CAS-MNP: Biophysical Mechanism of Interactions between Micro/Nanoplastics and the Natural Pulmonary Surfactant]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>352126.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>352126</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nosavage@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Micro/nanoplastics, tiny plastic debris arising from the environmental breakdown of plastic products, are not biodegradable and can take decades or even centuries to decompose fully. There is emerging evidence that micro/nanoplastics can enter the human body through food, water, beverages, or inhalation, necessitating a deeper understanding of their environmental, health, and safety impacts. This project is driven by two main objectives. Firstly, the research team intends to establish a pioneering microplastic library in Hawaii, where the waters and beaches are among the most contaminated by microplastics on this planet. This unique collection will be gathered from the shorelines of Oahu Island, taking into account the location and sand texture, thus offering real-world environmental context. This Hawaii-based microplastic library will serve as a valuable resource for researchers and citizen scientists exploring the eco-environmental impact of microplastics. Secondly, the research will focus on the respiratory health impacts of micro/nanoplastics. The insights gained will substantially advance current understanding of the respiratory health implications linked to micro/nanoplastic exposure. This study is poised to illuminate the pathophysiology of respiratory diseases connected to air pollution and micro/nanoplastic exposure, having clear translational implications. In collaboration with local nonprofit organizations, the PI will engage in initiatives to elevate public awareness of the microplastic crisis, fostering a sense of responsibility and informed decision-making within the community. Leveraging expertise in Pediatrics, the PI will champion efforts to reduce early-life plastic exposure to safeguard children's health and well-being, aligning with the project’s aim to mitigate the adverse effects of plastic pollution. Located at the University of Hawaii, the PI is dedicated to promoting the involvement of underrepresented groups, including Native Hawaiians, Pacific Islanders, and students from low-income families. This commitment highlights the project’s focus on fostering diversity and inclusion in science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Emerging evidence suggests that micro/nanoplastics can become airborne, penetrating deeply into the distal lungs of humans. Once inhaled, these particles encounter the natural pulmonary surfactant film, which serves as the primary defense mechanism within the lung alveoli. A notable difference between micro/nanoplastics and engineered nanomaterials is the significant heterogeneity in their morphology and composition. This heterogeneity is a critical risk factor that influences their interaction with the surfactant film. Despite the growing body of research, the precise biophysical mechanisms that govern these interactions remain largely unknown, as does their potential to adversely affect respiratory health. The objective of this project is to achieve a mechanistic understanding of how micro/nanoplastics from real environmental sources impact respiratory health. The research will focus on two specific goals: First, the research team aims to establish a pioneering microplastic library in Hawaii. This unique collection of microplastic samples will be sourced from the shorelines of Oahu Island, providing a tangible environmental context. Each sample will undergo comprehensive physical and chemical characterization. The composition and morphology of these samples will be compared with reference polymeric materials and microplastics prepared from commercial plastic products, aged under fully controlled laboratory conditions. Second, the research will test a novel hypothesis that micro/nanoplastics affect the biophysical function of natural pulmonary surfactant through heteroaggregation with the surfactant film. Specifically, the PI will explore whether the biophysical mechanism involves direct binding between micro/nanoplastics and surfactant phospholipids or proteins. This experimental approach will integrate biophysical simulations, physicochemical analyses, and complementary inhalation toxicological studies. The knowledge gained from this study is expected to provide valuable insights into the specific biophysical impacts of micro/nanoplastics on surfactant phospholipids/proteins, significantly advancing current understanding of the respiratory health implications associated with micro/nanoplastic exposure. Located at the University of Hawaii, the PI is committed to promoting the participation of underrepresented groups, including Native Hawaiians, Pacific Islanders, and students from low-income families. In collaboration with local nonprofit organizations, the PI is actively engaged in efforts to raise public awareness of the microplastic crisis, fostering a sense of responsibility and informed decision-making in the community. Leveraging expertise in Pediatrics, the PI advocates for reducing early-life plastic exposure to protect the health and well-being of children, aligning with the project’s goal to mitigate the adverse effects of plastic pollution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2403397</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yi</FirstName>
<LastName>Zuo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yi Zuo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yzuo@hawaii.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000520893</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2425 CAMPUS RD SINCLAIR RM 1]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NSCKLFSSABF2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222247</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2425 CAMPUS RD SINCLAIR RM 1]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>117900</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Interactions Program</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090Z</Code>
<Text>CAS-Critical Aspects of Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~352126</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
