<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Translation Potential of a Cloud Platform for Scientific Software and Data]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Molly Wasko</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mwasko@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924749</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this I-Corps project is based on the development of an open platform that makes cloud computing accessible to computational scientists of all backgrounds. This approach can be used for a variety of computational science tasks, like training neural networks or running simulations of climate models. A potential advantage of this platform includes access to sophisticated cloud computing techniques without requiring the specialized knowledge and supercomputing resources that universities, companies, or labs may lack. This solution could help overcome obstacles at smaller institutions, including Historically Black Colleges and Universities, Hispanic Serving Institutions, and/or Primarily Undergraduate Institutions, that often lack supercomputing resources on campus. Overall, this cloud computing platform can increase access to specialized knowledge and tools to make running computational science tasks simpler, less costly, and more accessible. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translation potential of the technology. The solution is based on the development of an initial version of an open cloud-based platform, called ADVISER (Advanced Cloud-based Data and Visualization Integrated Simulation EnviRonment) that includes Icepack, the name for a set of computational glaciology tools for solving the equations of motion of glacier flow in the cloud. This platform also includes additional computational science software services and is able to support more types of cloud computing instances. These features of the technology platform make computational science tasks on the cloud as simple to run as tasks on local computers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/22/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/22/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2403650</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Hyde</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Andrew B Hyde</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dabh@alumni.stanford.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000825841</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>NASHVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>372032416</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 21ST AVE S]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GTNBNWXJ12D5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>NASHVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372032416</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 21ST AVE S]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7942</Code>
<Text>HIGH-PERFORMANCE COMPUTING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
