<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[GOALI: Volatile and Thermally Stable Precursors for the Thermal Atomic Layer Deposition of Lanthanide Metal and Lanthanide Silicide Films]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>554853.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>554853</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the support of the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Charles Winter of Wayne State University is investigating new molecules and chemical reactions that can enable the growth of metal and metal-silicon thin films for advanced transistors. A particular focus will be understanding how variations in the structures of precursor molecules affect their ability to give high purity metal and metal-silicon films. The Winter research group will use an emerging technique known as atomic layer deposition to deposit metal and metal-silicon films from the new precursors. Atomic layer deposition permits films to be grown with atom-level control and affords perfect coating of narrow and deep nanoscale features in computer chips. If successful, the approach to lanthanide metal atomic layer deposition being put forward in this proposal has the possibility to significantly influence the future development of chemical compounds used in thin film growth. Additionally, the new precursor molecules and chemistry will be potentially useful for the manufacturing of computer chips. Professor Winter works with research students at many levels, including undergraduates, graduate students, and postdoctoral fellows.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this research program, Professor Charles Winter and his research team will explore the development of chemical precursors and thin film growth processes for lanthanide metal and lanthanide-silicon thin films for use in advanced transistor structures. Major focuses of the project will include exploring the synthesis and properties of new lanthanide molecules for use as thin film growth precursors, use of these precursors in the growth of lanthanide metal and lanthanide-silicon thin films using atomic layer deposition, and exploration of the properties of the new materials. The research, education, and outreach activities will be enhanced by collaboration with Dr. Mark J. Saly of Applied Materials through the GOALI program. Students who work on this project will participate in 3-month internships at Applied Materials. Additionally, research students from underrepresented groups are to be involved in this project. The research project will be shaped by industrial perspective and offers fertile opportunities for technology transfer and impact on computer chip design and performance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2403780</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Saly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark J Saly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mark_saly@amat.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000948797</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Winter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles H Winter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chw@chem.wayne.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000323834</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wayne State University]]></Name>
<CityName>DETROIT</CityName>
<ZipCode>482023692</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3135772424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5700 CASS AVE STE 4900]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M6K6NTJ2MNE5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WAYNE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wayne State University]]></Name>
<CityName>DETROIT</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>482023692</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5700 CASS AVE STE 4900]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>688500</Code>
<Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~554853</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
