<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Long term perspective on the Holocene CO2 Conundrum: the role of Southern Westerly Winds]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>239554.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>239554</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alan Wanamaker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>awanamak@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927516</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO2), starting ~ 6000 years ago, is unique among prior warm periods, in which greenhouse gases decreased following a decrease in solar forcing. To date, the cause for the increase in atmospheric CO2 during this period is poorly known. Early human activities associated with new agricultural practices may have been partly responsible, but recent work has suggested that the migration of the Southern Westerly Winds (SWW) may have altered carbon cycling and storage. While this may be a compelling explanation, it does not address whether this process was unique to the Holocene as compared with previous warm periods. To address this knowledge gap, the team will generate proxy records for the last 900,000 years in the Southern Ocean and evaluate several hypotheses regarding changes in CO2 levels. The project provides an opportunity for early career researchers and students to develop their research programs and take part in outreach activities. This research is relevant to society given its implications for understanding the role of humans in climate change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of this proposal is to reconstruct the SWW movement during earlier warm periods (interglacials) and compare those with the response of the Southern Ocean biological pump, atmospheric CO2, and other climate metrics. Specifically, the investigators will use sediments collected during Expedition 379T, along the southern Chilean Margin (site J1001; 46° 24.3’S, 77° 19.4’W 3067 mbsl) to generate a foraminiferal oxygen isotope stratigraphy and an alkenone sea surface temperature record, which will be compared to records of climate, CO2 and insolation. Project participants will compare the Holocene with five earlier warm periods (MIS 5e, 9e, 11c, 13, and 19), characterized by both similar, and different orbital parameters as compared with the Holocene. Nitrogen isotope records during these warm intervals will be used to assess variations in upwelling and nutrient utilization relative to bottom seawater temperature and ∆CO3 records.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2404710</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samantha</FirstName>
<LastName>Bova</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samantha C Bova</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sbova@sdsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000714815</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Diego State University Foundation]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN DIEGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>921821901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5250 CAMPANILE DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>51</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA51</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H59JKGFZKHL7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN DIEGO STATE UNIVERSITY FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>H59JKGFZKHL7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Diego State University]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN DIEGO</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921821020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5500 CAMPANILE DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>51</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA51</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>162000</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1324</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY AND PREDICTABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~239554</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
