<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[STTR Phase I: Packed Bed Thermal Energy Storage (PBTES) in sCO2-based thermo-mechanical energy storage for short and long durations]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>274723.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>274723</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mara E. Schindelholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>marschin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924506</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader/commercial impact of this STTR Phase I project involves the development and deployment of an integrated energy storage solution designed to harness and store excess energy from renewable sources such as wind and solar. This project addresses the critical need for effective energy storage systems to manage the intermittency of renewable energy sources. The anticipated commercial impacts include significant advancements in grid stability and the potential reduction of reliance on fossil fuel-based peaker plants. The market for grid-scale energy storage is projected to reach billions of dollars globally, positioning the technology to capture a substantial share of this growing market. Additionally, the project is expected to contribute to environmental sustainability by facilitating a higher penetration of renewable energy sources into the grid, thus reducing carbon emissions and enhancing air quality. The successful development and implementation of this technology could also foster greater scientific understanding of advanced energy storage systems and promote further technological innovations within the renewable energy sector.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project stems from its innovative approach to combining thermal and mechanical energy storage using supercritical carbon dioxide (sCO2) as the heat transfer fluid in a Packed-Bed Thermal Energy Storage (PB-TES) system. The research objectives focus on optimizing the heat transfer efficiency and minimizing mechanical losses in the system, aiming for a heat transfer efficiency greater than 90% and a levelized cost of storage (LCOS) below $60/megawatt hour (MWh). The research will involve detailed design, modeling, and testing of PB-TES configurations to handle the high pressures of sCO2 and achieve efficient thermal management. Anticipated technical results include the development of a scalable, cost-effective energy storage system that can be rapidly deployed and integrated with existing renewable energy infrastructures. This project not only aims to advance the state-of-the-art in energy storage solutions but also enhances the scalability and economic feasibility of renewable energy systems, contributing significantly to the field of energy engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2404520</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hitesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Bindra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hitesh Bindra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hbindra@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000656227</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Palash</FirstName>
<LastName>Panja</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Palash Panja</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Palash@earthen.info]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826355</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[EARTHEN INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>CHANDLER</CityName>
<ZipCode>852261140</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8013007420</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6401 W ORCHID LN]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GPMKDELF6V79</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EARTHEN ENERGY INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[EARTHEN INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>CHANDLER</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852261140</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6401 W ORCHID LN]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>150500</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~274723</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
