<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Elucidating the Assembly of Higher-Order Anion Foldamers: The Influence of Charge, Sterics and the HBeXB]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>575457.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>575457</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Suk-Wah Tam-Chang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>stamchan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928684</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With support from the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry (MSN) program in the Division of Chemistry, Orion Berryman and his group of the University of Montana are exploring new ways to control the shape and properties of extended molecules. These molecules are designed to adopt helical shapes that maintain a pore down the middle of the helix. The pores will be precisely defined with chemical groups that will be used to control the function of the molecules. This research seeks to understand how changing three parameters will influence the helical shape of the molecule: (i) the charge state of the molecule, (ii) attaching large groups to the exterior of the molecule, and (iii) changing the functional groups on the molecule. This work aims to produce water soluble molecules that bind tightly to negatively charged species and discover ways to switch between helical shapes using external stimulus like light.  Knowledge to be gained from this research may inform the design of materials for molecular recognition with applications in sensing, separation science, and environmental remediation. In addition to the research training of graduate and undergraduate students, including members of underrepresented groups, this project will maintain a collaboration with a local high school science teachers to develop new methods of crystallization and incorporate crystallography into local high school science classes. This project will also continue a collaboration with spectrUM science museum to host chemistry demonstrations for chemistry summer camps and expand a crystal related science exhibit that Dr. Berryman previously developed. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Berryman group seeks to understand how to use noncovalent interactions to bind anions and predictably assemble supramolecular structures of higher-order (multi-strand) helical foldamers. This project will develop an approach to simultaneously control molecular structure and strengthen halogen bonding building on the hydrogen bond enhanced halogen bonding concept. Modular oligomeric strands of phenylethynyl foldamers will be synthesized and studied to reveal important non-covalent interactions that govern the formation of double and triple helical anion foldamers.  The specific aims of this project are to: (i) establish how internal functionalization of the helical foldamer dictates higher-order foldamer assembly, (ii) understand how the location of charge influences what assembly forms and generate higher-order foldamers in water and (iii) study steric factors and produce switchable, higher order anion foldamers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/18/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/18/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2404207</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Orion</FirstName>
<LastName>Berryman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Orion Berryman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[orion.berryman@umontana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000642933</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/18/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Montana]]></Name>
<CityName>MISSOULA</CityName>
<ZipCode>598120003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4062436670</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[32 CAMPUS DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DAY7Z8ZD48Q3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MONTANA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Montana]]></Name>
<CityName>MISSOULA</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>598120003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[32 CAMPUS DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>688500</Code>
<Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~575457</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
