<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Creating Inclusive Scientific Societies through Policies and Practices]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2029</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>190425.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>190425</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keri Sather-Wagstaff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ksatherw@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922534</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Creating Inclusive Scientific Societies through Policies and Practices (CRISSPP) project brings three universities, University of Michigan, University of Connecticut, and University of North Texas into a partnership to develop, implement, and assess a set of evidence-based guidelines and practices for scientific organizations (beginning with Psychology) to promote inclusion and minimize systemic exclusion. The research literature indicates that academic exclusion includes social, informational, and epistemic exclusion, and professional societies can play a central role in members’ academic careers, facilitating the dissemination of their scholarship and providing opportunities to establish prominence within the field. The guidelines and practices will help professional societies create and sustain positive disciplinary environments that lead to success for all faculty. The project will empower organizations to shape individual members’ experiences of inclusion/exclusion and the organization’s climate in four critical areas: governance, awards, conferences, and publications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CRISSPP guidelines and practices will (1) conduct climate surveys and audits, (2) construct interventions (to include transparency audits, toolkits, including guidelines and rubrics as appropriate, commitment to optimal processes, pathway development (for governance), educational workshops and, (in the case of conferences), a brief daily online climate assessment tool), and (3) assess the overall impact of these interventions on the organizations and on members’ sense of belonging. The guidelines, practices, and lessons learned will initially be shared within Division 9 of the American Psychological Association and up to nine additional partner organizations in psychology, reaching over 20,000 members. This partnership will be evaluated internally and externally, formatively and summatively, to improve the guidelines and practices for other organizations and identify implementation issues that may need to be addressed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The NSF ADVANCE program is designed to foster gender equity through a focus on the identification and elimination of organizational barriers that impede the full participation and advancement of diverse faculty in academic institutions.  Organizational barriers that inhibit equity may exist in policies, processes, practices, and the organizational culture and climate.  ADVANCE "Partnership" awards provide support for the adaptation and adoption of evidence-based strategies to academic, non-profit institutions of higher education and non-academic, non-profit organizations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2404537</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martinque</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martinque K Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Martinque.jones@unt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000810349</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Texas]]></Name>
<CityName>DENTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>762051132</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9405653940</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1112 DALLAS DR STE 4000]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G47WN1XZNWX9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH TEXAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Texas]]></Name>
<CityName>DENTON</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1155 UNION CIR #305250]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>016Y00</Code>
<Text>ADVANCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>011Z</Code>
<Text>ADVANCE PLAN D</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7568</Code>
<Text>ADVANCE-PAID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~190425</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
