<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Eastern States Section Meeting of the Combustion Institute]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harsha Chelliah</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hchellia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927281</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this award is to provide support for the 2024 Spring Technical Meeting of the Eastern States Section of the Combustion Institute will be hosted by the University of Georgia, Athens, GA, commencing the evening of Sunday, March 10, 2024, and concluding at noon on Wednesday, March 13, 2024. The broader significance and importance of this meeting is providing a forum for graduate students, postdoctoral students, faculty and other researchers to network and share progress in this area of research. This conference is a gathering of combustion researchers in academia, industry, and government from the East Coast region of the United States. The conference's technical program consists of a series of plenary lectures, contributed oral presentations, and information social gatherings. Many of the papers will be presented by students and the meeting is an opportunity for students to network with their peers and faculty from other institutions. A goal of the meeting is to expose students to the latest research and offer opportunity for career development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference brings together leading experts to give plenary talks in several areas. Sessions will include the topic areas of Computationally and Data Intensive Research, Detonations and Supersonic Combustion, Diagnostics, Fire Research, Heterogeneous Combustion/Spray and Droplets, IC Engines, Gas Turbines, and Rockets, Laminar Flames, Novel Energy Conversion Techniques, Reaction Kinetics and Fuels, Soot and Nanomaterials, Turbulent Flames. A particular focus of this conference is on graduate and undergraduate students: providing an opportunity for these students to present and get feedback on their research and enhancing their oral presentation and technical writing skills. The support from NSF will be used to award travel grants to non-local students and registration support for local students in an effort to increase student participation at the meeting, particularly students from underrepresented institutions that may not have the financial means to fully support student travel to conferences. Hence the conference will support the training of future workforce in combustion and related field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2406534</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brandon</FirstName>
<LastName>Rotavera</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brandon Rotavera</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rotavera@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000776570</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>140700</Code>
<Text>CFS-Combustion &amp; Fire Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~10000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
