<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Strengthening mechanisms of Axially bi-Continuous Graphene/Nickel (ACGN) Composites for Breaking the Strength-Ductility Trade-off Condition]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>562789.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>562789</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy C. Crone</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wcrone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Graphene, a two-dimensional carbon material, is ultra-strong, flexible, and lightweight. These mechanical advantages can be combined with conventional metal to manufacture graphene-metal composites with enhanced mechanical performance. This project will achieve a fundamental understanding of the strengthening mechanisms of such composites by developing and utilizing bi-continuous graphene-nickel composites as a model. The results of this project will also guide the development of new theoretical models and innovative designs of graphene-based composites. High-performance composites, characterized by both strength and deformability, are relevant to a wide range of applications, including automotive/aerospace composites, sports equipment, protective armor, and high-strength cables. This project will integrate research and engineering training opportunities by fostering interdisciplinary research, education, and outreach opportunities across individuals from K-12 to undergraduate and graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to deepen our understanding of the deformation mechanisms in axially bi-continuous graphene-metal composites. Graphene (Gr) offers excellent mechanical strength far beyond conventional metal and, therefore, is often dispersed in a metal matrix to develop macroscopic Gr-enhanced metal matrix composites for structural applications. However, such composites suffer from the intrinsic trade-off between strength and ductility due to weak Gr-metal interfaces. In this work, fine nickel wires coated by axially continuous graphene structures are used to break the intrinsic trade-off and achieve excellent combined strength and ductility. However, the exact mechanism(s) responsible for the observed enhancements are not well understood mainly due to the complex coupling of various size-dependent strengthening mechanisms. This project will reveal the underlying mechanisms by developing and utilizing new laser-based material processes and microdevice-based characterization methods. This project will provide valuable scientific knowledge on the intricate relationship between graphene structures, grains, and dislocations in such bi-continuous composites and their effect on mechanical behavior.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2406730</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Qiong</FirstName>
<LastName>Nian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Qiong Nian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[qiong.nian@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000756287</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wonmo</FirstName>
<LastName>Kang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wonmo Kang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wonmo.kang@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000863722</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>163000</Code>
<Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>022E</Code>
<Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~562789</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
