<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Research Initiation: LIONS Bridge Program:A Program Aimed at Enhancing Learning, Inclusivity, Opportunities, and Nurturing Students from Historically Excluded Groups in Engineering]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>191439.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>191439</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alice Pawley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>apawley@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927286</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The LIONS Bridge program is an exciting initiative aimed at increasing diversity in engineering. This innovative summer bridge program will provide strong support to incoming students from historically excluded groups, making engineering education more inclusive and accessible. Through this program, participants will receive tutoring, mentorship from peers, faculty, and industry professionals, and engaging activities such as field trips and community service. These efforts will help students feel more confident and prepared as they begin and continue through their engineering studies. By addressing the need for diversity in STEM fields, this project will work to ensure that students from all backgrounds have the opportunity to succeed. With tailored support and a welcoming environment, the program will improve recruitment and retention rates of underrepresented students in engineering. Moreover, the project aligns with the NSF’s goals of the Professional Formation of Engineers: Research Initiation in Engineering Formation (PFE: RIEF) program. By supporting research in the professional formation of engineers and fostering a more diverse engineering workforce, this initiative contributes to broader societal progress and aligns with NSF’s commitment to an innovative and inclusive engineering profession.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project at the University of North Alabama (UNA) will address the ongoing need for diversity, equity, and inclusion (DEI) in higher education, particularly within engineering programs. This initiative will focus on creating a summer bridge program for incoming engineering students from historically excluded groups. The primary goals of the project will be to design and assess the bridge program, explore the impact of mentorship on student success, and prepare Dr. Amber Pete to conduct necessary engineering education research. The program will provide participants with tutoring, mentorship from peers, faculty, and industry professionals, field trips, community service opportunities, and two fundamental engineering courses. Its objectives aim to improve recruitment and retention rates and boost students' confidence. The research questions driving this project will include: How effective will the summer bridge program improve academic performance and retention among historically excluded students? What role will mentorship play in supporting these students' success in engineering education? To address these questions, the team will employ quantitative and qualitative methods, including examinations, GPA tracking, retention rates, and student feedback. Key partnerships for this project will involve collaboration with high schools and community organizations to establish a support network for students. Additionally, the interdisciplinary team, led by Dr. Pete and comprising faculty from engineering, mathematics, science, and social sciences, all with extensive experience in their respective fields, will ensure a comprehensive approach to program development and evaluation. Two STEM researchers, known for their STEM education work in their fields, will serve as primary mentors to Dr. Pete, while other co-PIs, each with a unique set of skills and expertise, will assist with evaluation methodologies. The expected outcomes of this project will include creating a successful and replicable bridge program model, enhanced mentorship frameworks, and significant contributions to engineering education and DEI initiatives. The broader impacts will extend to improving diversity in STEM fields, fostering an inclusive academic environment, and potentially influencing DEI practices at regional universities. By continuously assessing and refining the program, UNA will aim to build a more equitable and accessible pathway to engineering careers, ultimately contributing to a more diverse and innovative engineering workforce. These outcomes will not only benefit the immediate participants but also have a ripple effect, influencing the broader engineering education landscape.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Division of Engineering Education &amp; Centers (EEC) and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2407224</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Candice</FirstName>
<LastName>Quinn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Candice M Quinn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cquinn@una.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000917887</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Padgett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary Padgett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gpadgett@una.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000986294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sara L Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sjohnson34@una.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000803175</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Hunt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrea Hunt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ahunt3@una.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000680058</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amber</FirstName>
<LastName>Pete</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amber J Pete</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[apete@una.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000929096</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/24/2024</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Alabama]]></Name>
<CityName>FLORENCE</CityName>
<ZipCode>356320002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2567654937</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 HARRISON PLZ]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MEMJEJHP6KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH ALABAMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MEMJEJHP6KZ6</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Alabama]]></Name>
<CityName>FLORENCE</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>356320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 HARRISON PLZ]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>134000</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>915000</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~191439</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
