<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Equipment: MRI: Track 1 Acquisition of an X-ray Photoelectron Spectrometer for Materials Chemistry Research and Undergraduate and Graduate Student Training]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>642440.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>642440</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Meulenberg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmeulenb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927106</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Supported by the Division of Materials Research at the National Science Foundation, the acquisition of a modern X-ray photoelectron spectrometer (XPS) at the University of San Diego will enable fast progress on a broad set of current challenges in chemistry.  XPS is one of the main tools capable of identifying the elemental composition of solid surfaces. A new class of solids known as metal organic frameworks (MOFs) will be studied in order to improve applications in chemical reactions, molecular storage and separation, and sensor development. Additionally, other metal-containing solids important in the development of energy storage and conversion will be studied.  Impacts beyond these specific research aims include new training opportunities for undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral scholars in the San Diego region at SDSU, USD, and UCSD. Acquisition of a high throughput XPS at USD will enable students and scholars from multiple departments &amp; institutions in the San Diego area to strengthen and build connections with local industry.  There will be immediate impacts to the undergraduate curricula in multiple courses, including physical, analytical, environmental chemistry, and general chemistry.  Finally, the PI is active in efforts to increase diversity in STEM and will leverage the acquisition of an XPS in training and outreach through workshops and demonstrations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The acquisition of a modern X-ray photoelectron spectrometer (XPS) at the University of San Diego will enable fast progress on a broad set of advanced materials chemistry challenges.  Studies of the surface and defect chemistry of metal organic frameworks (MOFs) will enable broad control over MOF surface chemistry, enhancing applications of MOFs in molecular storage and separation, sensing, and catalysis. Identification of metal oxidation states in MOFs following molecular adsorption will shed light on catalysis. Additionally, the surface chemistry of transition metal dichalcogenides, metallic nanostructures and heterogenous materials will be uncovered, enhancing the development of novel materials for chemical sensors, energy storage, and energy conversion applications. Impacts beyond these specific research aims include new training opportunities for undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral scholars in the San Diego region at SDSU, USD, and UCSD. Acquisition of a high throughput XPS at USD will enable students and scholars from multiple departments &amp; institutions in the San Diego area to strengthen and build connections with local industry.  There will be immediate impacts to the undergraduate curricula in multiple courses, including physical, analytical, and environmental chemistry, as well as first-semester general chemistry at USD which introduces the photoelectric effect.  Finally, the PI is active in efforts to increase diversity in STEM and will leverage the acquisition of an XPS in training and outreach through workshops and demonstrations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2407018</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eleanor</FirstName>
<LastName>Gillette</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eleanor Gillette</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[egillette@sandiego.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000801956</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
<LastName>Benz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lauren Benz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[laurenbenz@sandiego.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000622932</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN DIEGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>921102476</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6192606825</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5998 ALCALA PARK FRNT]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>51</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA51</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6S1GT51XD56</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN DIEGO</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921102476</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5998 ALCALA PARK FRNT]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>51</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA51</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>118900</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8611</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficiency and End Use</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~642440</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
