<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Multifunctional, low carbon nanocomposite fibers derived from seaweed]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>275000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vincent Lee</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vinlee@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925041</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader/commercial impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project seeks to phase-out fossil fuel-based textiles with sustainable, non-toxic fabric alternatives with enhanced properties. Currently, fabrics for high performance applications require toxic additives or coatings that may pollute air and water systems; additionally, most of them come from fossil fuels, contributing to global warming. If successful, the proposed project will produce novel seaweed-based textiles with enhanced properties like fire and ultraviolet blocking and infrared shielding properties. These properties are inherent to the material; thus, no further treatment will be needed, simplifying the manufacturing process. The material will be attractive to US work apparel and outdoor activewear manufacturers seeking to increase the sustainability of their products. The business model will be commercialization of the raw material and licensing the technology so manufacturers can fabricate the textiles to their needs. By doing so, the company requires less operational investment, easing its introduction to the market.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project uses seaweed biopolymers combined with nanomaterials to create fibers and fabrics. The enhanced properties like fire resistance, ultraviolet protection and heat shielding, as well as the mechanical properties of the fibers, can be finetuned depending on the formulation and the production method. The aim is to develop a formula that will produce flexible fibers capable of being woven into fabrics with high performance characteristics. The team will vary the formulation chemistry, the spinning process and will test how it affects the mechanical and chemical characteristics. The project will focus on obtaining a fully plastic-free knitted yarn where UV protection, heat shielding, and fire resistance are achieved without adding plastic binders, coatings, or films.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2409680</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Derek</FirstName>
<LastName>Saltzman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Derek Saltzman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[grants@soarceusa.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000962612</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/28/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SOARCE, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
<ZipCode>328277584</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9549348742</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6555 SANGER RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MBHDGFL7M2Y5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOARCE, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SOARCE LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328264223</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4032 IVEYGLEN AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>537100</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~275000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
