<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: eQuanta's Next-Gen STI Diagnostic Device: Unveiling the Power of Graphene-Based]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>275000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hahn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to provide rapid, effective, affordable, non-invasive, and easy-to-use diagnosis of viral and non-viral sexually transmitted infections (STI), such as chlamydia, gonorrhea, syphilis, HIV, hepatitis C, and trichomoniasis. STI are estimated to be present in one out of five people in the U.S. and the estimated direct medical cost associated to their treatment is approximately $16B. While early diagnosis will ultimately contribute to better public health outcomes and economy, the principal barrier in seeking a diagnosis is the lack of available health services, cost, long clinic waiting times, invasive sample collection methods and the negative social stigma associated with looking for STI testing. This project will develop an affordable and point-of-care diagnostic device for STI, that will not only reduce diagnostic time but also lower healthcare costs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project advances an innovative STI diagnostic device. This project leverages self-assembled chemistry to form tailored cavities, which are sensitive and selective to the biomarkers of interest. The project aims to validate preliminary studies indicating the device's capability to detect viruses, opioids, and biomarkers for STI diseases, enabling early disease diagnosis and quantification of viral or bacterial loads in exhaled breath or urine. Phase I of this project will be focused on the fabrication of a device composed of an array of sensors to detect biomarkers of viral and non-viral STIs with high selectivity and sensitivity from day one of contagion. Detection of hepatitis C, HIV, chlamydia, gonorrhea, syphilis, trichomoniasis biomarkers from cervical mucus discharge/swabs will be evaluated. Additionally, user testing on a clinical research environment will be undertaken at Ragon Institute.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2409808</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shadi</FirstName>
<LastName>Emam</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shadi Emam</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[quarksencorp@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000970986</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[QUARKSEN LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>MANSFIELD</CityName>
<ZipCode>020481548</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2254486698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[241 FRANCIS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>R2XKUC52Q7N5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>QUARKSEN LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[QUARKSEN LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>BRIGHTON</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021353954</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[99 CHESTNUT HILL AVE APT 209]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>537100</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~275000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
