<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Louis Stokes B2B Alliance: Puget Sound B2B Alliance (PSA)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1498959.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>511538</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonja Montas-Hunter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smontash@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927404</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A diverse scientific, technical, engineering, and math (STEM) workforce not only unlocks the potential for innovation through the utilization of diverse backgrounds, experiences, and perspectives, it also fortifies the strength of scientific endeavors and bolsters the competitiveness of the nation on a global scale. Two-year colleges are strategically positioned to expand and diversify this workforce. The Puget Sound Alliance (PSA) is an established Bridge to the Baccalaureate (B2B) Alliance of three Washington State public two-year colleges: North Seattle College, Pierce College, and Green River College. These institutions serve ~38,900 students each year within western Washington’s Puget Sound region. The region is a global center of STEM innovation and employment where almost 90% of the region’s family-sustaining jobs in STEM require at least a baccalaureate degree. In its first four years, the PSA deployed an array of evidence-based strategies to improve student engagement and retention, with an emphasis on undergraduate research experiences for participating students. These strategies, combined with robust student support, helped the PSA realize a 34% increase in the transfer rate of participating students to STEM programs at baccalaureate degree granting institutions across the Alliance.  In this iteration, the PSA will continue proven strategies and implement three new foci: 1) mental health and well-being interventions, 2) experiential learning opportunities, and 3) improved faculty mentor training, to effect a 40% increase in the number of participating students transferring to STEM baccalaureate programs over a three-year duration. These efforts will directly serve over 270 student participants and provide funding for an additional 240 participants to pursue research and other activities known to increase engagement and retention during the three-year project. Thousands of other students will also indirectly benefit from the lasting institutional changes driven by the colleges’ participation in the PSA. Ultimately, the PSA aspires to educate and diversify new generations of STEM workers and researchers to help expand and diversify the nation's workforce and increase the number of STEM baccalaureate and graduate degrees earned by students from historically underrepresented populations in these fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project’s intellectual merit is derived from both the experienced leadership team and the array of evidence-based interventions and strategies leveraged by the PSA. Both the current efforts and the three new foci are well-supported by the literature on broadening participation in STEM. The PSA aims to continue proven strategies and implement new, innovative strategies to affect a 40% increase in the number of LSAMP-eligible students transferring to STEM baccalaureate programs over a three-year duration. The primary goal of the PSA will be to strengthen LSAMP-participating students’ STEM identities and significantly increase the number of these students who transfer from Puget Sound Alliance colleges to baccalaureate STEM programs of study at four-year universities. The Alliance will ensure the rigor and success of their efforts by conducting a mixed-method evaluation and assessment plan to generate new knowledge about the impact of PSA activities on LSAMP participants’ identity, sense of belonging, and intention to transfer. This project will be realized through established partnerships spanning two-year colleges, four-year universities, K-12 school districts, and regional STEM employers. These partners bring a commitment, expertise, and shared enthusiasm for equity-oriented approaches that seek to transform the two-year college student experience and, ultimately, foster greater participation in the region’s STEM workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2409204</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ann</FirstName>
<LastName>Murkowski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ann J Murkowski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ann.murkowski@seattlecolleges.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000432812</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chitra</FirstName>
<LastName>Solomonson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chitra G Solomonson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[csolomonson@greenriver.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000568215</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elysia</FirstName>
<LastName>Mbuja</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elysia A Mbuja</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[embuja@pierce.ctc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Solemsaas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel Solemsaas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Rachel.Solemsaas@seattlecolleges.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000986403</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Seattle Community College District Office]]></Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981223803</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2069342026</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1500 HARVARD AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XW9JC593M6M7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SEATTLE CENTRAL COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>JQTZWL5U8XJ8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Seattle Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981223803</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1500 HARVARD AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>913300</Code>
<Text>Alliances-Minority Participat.</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~511538</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
