<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: The Next Generation of Conversations: Albany at Louisiana Tech]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>206875.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>206875</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Arcady Mushegian</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amushegi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928528</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In 1979, Professor Ramaswamy H. Sarma initiated the Albany Conversations on Biomolecular Structure and Dynamics at the State University of New York, Albany. This biennial event evolved into a five-day gathering attended by hundreds of scientists from over 20 countries. Since its inception, the Conversations have attracted scientists of all career stages, from Nobel Laureates to students, to engage in collegial interchange without distinction of rank. The event fosters global collaboration and knowledge exchange in computational, theoretical, and experimental biomolecular research. After 20 successful Conversations, which contributed to numerous collaborations and launched many careers, Professor Sarma is passing the torch to the Next Generation of scientists, with Louisiana Tech University chosen as the new host. This strategic move aims to further advance scientific innovation and collaboration between emerging scientists and field leaders alike. The Next Gen Conversations will provide budding scientists the same opportunities that shaped previous generations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Next Generation of Conversations aim to address current challenges in structural biology and foster scientific collaboration across diverse expertise levels. Building on the legacy of the Albany Conversations, this conference series will provide a platform for scientists, ranging from Nobel laureates to early career researchers, to engage in scientific discourse, explore novel ideas, and establish collaborations. Unifying informatics-based techniques such as next-generation sequencing, machine learning, and artificial intelligence with physics-based imaging and structural techniques, will be required to advance the current understanding of biomolecular mechanisms. The Next Generation Conversations will focus on promoting the unification of cross-cutting and trans-disciplinary scientific efforts, emphasizing collaboration and knowledge exchange. Louisiana Tech University is within a 5 to 6 hour drive of numerous major metropolitan areas in the Mississippi Delta/Gulf South region, a strategic location for the Next Generation Conversations to also broaden participation among underrepresented institutions and communities. Bringing the Next Generation of Conversations to the rural south will directly address disparities in scientific representation and promote broader societal impacts in this region.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/09/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2412981</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Bishop</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas C Bishop</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bishop@latech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000357981</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/09/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana Tech University]]></Name>
<CityName>RUSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>71272</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3182575075</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[RAIL ROAD AVE WYLY TWR 1620]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>PAMDY6DMVVE7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA TECH UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana Tech University]]></Name>
<CityName>RUSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>71272</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[RAIL ROAD AVE WYLY TWR 1620]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>111200</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~206875</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
