<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: EAGER: The long reach of culture: Cultural contexts and developmental outcomes of  childhood exploration and interactions with nature]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>142165.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>142165</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna V. Fisher</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>avfisher@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928451</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Numerous studies note that, over the past several decades, children in many Western societies spend less time engaged in independent exploration, less time in outdoor green spaces, and more time in structured activities which are supervised by adults. While these shifts frequently reflect parental concerns for their children’s safety and academic development, recent studies highlight risks associated with a loss of independence and time spent in nature among children. With that in mind, the current study examines children’s exploratory behavior in two societies where opportunities for independence and time spent in nature are cultural priorities in childhood. The research team investigates children’s independent exploration of their environments (e.g., playing in their neighborhood without adult supervision) and the types of environments children explore (e.g., green spaces versus playgrounds). The researchers then examine how these experiences may be associated with children’s spatial cognition, executive function, and well-being. Finally, the researchers survey the children’s parents to establish possible links between parenting behavior and children’s outcomes. It is anticipated that this study can help parents and educators develop a more beneficial balance between (1) protecting children’s safety and structuring their experiences, and (2) promoting autonomy, exploration, and experience in natural environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project assesses children’s exploratory behavior and time spent in different environments through several means including: GPS-tracking via phone, a vegetation index which is combined with GPS data, and a questionnaire concerning children’s experiences in nature. The researchers combine these measures with experience sampling methodology using text messages throughout the testing period so that children can provide information about their location, activity, and mood. Children complete a series of measures assessing (1) spatial ability, including a virtual navigation video game and a mental rotation task, and (2) executive function assessments from the NIH Toolkit Cognitive Battery and parental report. Additionally, researchers use questionnaires to document children’s well-being (via self-report) as well as strengths and difficulties (via parental report). Finally, parents complete questionnaires regarding their parenting style, such as their socialization goals and concerns about risky play.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2413866</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mariah</FirstName>
<LastName>Schug</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mariah Schug</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mschug@widener.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000572616</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/20/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Widener University]]></Name>
<CityName>CHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>190135700</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6104994396</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 UNIVERSITY PL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GP1SKG5MFH79</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WIDENER UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Widener University]]></Name>
<CityName>CHESTER</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>190135792</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 UNIVERSITY PL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>169800</Code>
<Text>DS -Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~142165</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
