<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Synthetic Biology: Engineering, Evolution and Design (SEED) Conference]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48725.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48725</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David J. Klinke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dklinke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922890</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The 2024 Synthetic Biology, Engineering, Evolution and Design (SEED) Conference will have an expanded range of topics and will emphasize burgeoning areas of synthetic biology such as synthetic applications for climate change and sustainability, and Big-Data and Synthetic Biology. The broader range of topics will allow the conference to host scientists and engineers with diverse backgrounds. The conference will also allow students and early career professionals to share their work and learn about new advances in a rapidly growing field. Additionally, the conference will promote the continuous growth of members of the synthetic biology community, encouraging discussions among normally separated scientists and engineers and encouraging collaborations, which are critical for the development of new synthetic technologies and applications for biotechnology, agriculture, and medicine.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Over the past decade, the field of synthetic biology has rapidly developed from a research-based, theoretical discipline to one that is impacting society and will continue to grow in applications into the future. Since 2014, SEED has been the primary technical conference to gather people working in synthetic biology, including chemical and biological engineers, biologists, chemists, electrical engineers, and computer scientists. The conference gathers an interdisciplinary audience to share technical presentations on cutting edge research and applications, to network and develop collaborative relationships, and to connect people that may otherwise not have opportunities to interact. Attendees include leaders in the field, established researchers, early career professionals and trainees who will lead the field in the coming decades. SEED’s goal is to share insights into next-generation development strategies in synthetic biology research and industry. This conference is supported by the Systems and Synthetic Biology Cluster of the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/30/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/30/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2413726</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Evan</FirstName>
<LastName>Flach</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Evan Flach</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[evanf@aiche.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000662136</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/30/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Institute of Chemical Engineers</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100055991</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6464951350</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>120 WALL ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[23 FLO]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KLPNCLPDAS45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN INSTITUTE OF CHEMICAL ENGINEERS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Institute of Chemical Engineers]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100055991</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[120 WALL ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~48725</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
