<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[IUCRC Planning Grant, Florida A&M University: Center for Science, Technology and Advanced Research in Space (C-STARS)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The planned Center for Science, Technology, and Advanced Research in Space (C-STARS) seeks to form a  multidisciplinary hub that supports and serves the rapidly growing sector of space manufacturing. C-STARS brings academic researchers together led by University of Florida and three partner universities (Florida Institute of Technology, Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University and Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University) with spaceflight providers to help industries transition to the space manufacturing sector and improve the production of unique medicines, therapeutics, electronics, and materials that can benefit the people of Earth. The rapid increase in private sector investment and competition has increased the demand for in-space manufacturing technologies and products  critical to a new space-based industry.  Despite the advantages and expanding access, conducting research and manufacturing in space is limited by experience, data reproducibility, and standardized hardware technologies. C-STARS brings together broad expertise and experience in space research across the State of Florida, including the Florida Spaceport, which is the busiest spaceport in the U.S. to ensure an efficient and effective transition to commercial space research and operations for its industry partners. Additionally, C-STARS will develop new corporate mentoring programs, curriculums, certifications, and internship programs to train the future workforce in this dynamic and rapidly changing field thereby ensuring that the US achieves and sustains global space manufacturing preeminence.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;The planned Center for Science, Technology, and Advanced Research in Space (C-STARS) serves as a critical nexus to advance technologies, processes and operation protocols associated with in-space manufacturing to benefit life on Earth and sustain life during deep space missions. Manufacturing in the microgravity environment provides unique physical advantages that cannot be replicated on Earth enabling the production of novel and potentially higher quality products. C-STARS combines the unique experiences, resources, and perspectives of its academic partners to help support industry transition their products and operations to the space environment in areas such as regenerative medicine, diagnostics, artificial intelligence, biomonitoring, bioenergy systems, additive manufacturing of electronics, and materials recycling. Products arising from these thrust areas have the potential to advance cell therapies, mitigate human diseases, recycle space electronics, and improve the overall sustainability of space manufacturing. In proximity to the nation’s busiest spaceport and through partnerships with manufacturing companies, launch providers, and STEM-focused education centers, C-STARS is uniquely positioned to assist companies’ de-risk, high value manufacturing needs, promote large-scale company portfolio growth, and support diverse workforce training. Together, C-STARS creates a sustainable, efficient, and effective collaboration with industrial partners to ensure U.S. maintains its leadership in the field of space manufacturing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2413277</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Satyanarayan</FirstName>
<LastName>Dev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Satyanarayan Dev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[satyanarayan.dev@famu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000700706</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Teek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David P Teek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[david.teek@famu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000770193</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University]]></Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323070001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8505993531</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1700 LEE HALL DR #201]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>W8LKB16HV1K5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>W8LKB16HV1K5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University]]></Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323070001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1700 LEE HALL DR #201]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>576100</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~20000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
