<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Translation potential of a tampon-like menstrual cup and applicator system]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this I-Corps project is the development of a device for internal use during menstruation to collect menstrual fluid using a menstrual cup and applicator.  Currently, the average menstruator spends $20 on feminine hygiene products per cycle, but often experiences unnecessary discomfort or embarrassment when using pads and tampons. In addition, these commonly used products put them at a higher risk for developing endometriosis, toxic shock syndrome, and polycystic ovary syndrome. Although menstrual cups are available on the market, many menstruators won't convert from their current solutions due to the product's intimidating size and difficulty with insertion and removal. This technology addresses these concerns and may bridge the gap between the convenience of tampons and the benefits of menstrual cups.  Women have reported that menstrual cups may provide increased comfort, less interference with activities, less irritation, decreased odor, and the ability to wear a cup for longer periods of time than a pad or tampon.  The technology may offer a sustainable and easy-to-use menstrual cup that provides users a safe solution with long-lasting comfort and function.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translational potential of the technology. The technology is based on the prior development of an intravaginal menstrual cup and applicator to collect menstrual fluid. The technology uses a bell-shaped cup and loop tab design in combination with a tampon-like applicator. The product’s bell-shape provides optimal capacity for collecting menstrual fluid and is ergonomically designed to fit comfortably within the vaginal canal. For insertion, the device uses a common folding technique, known as the C-fold. The flexible silicone device is inserted into the polycarbonate plunger-applicator to be deployed into the vaginal canal. For removal, a loop at the base of the cup provides an attachment point for a biocompatible and adjustable cord. This design allows for mess-free and easy extraction. The cup has been shown to have a longer wear time, reducing the need for frequent changes.  In addition, the solution has an eco-friendly, reusable design that may result in a significant reduction in environmental waste.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/15/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/15/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2413962</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Thompson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lizabeth L Thompson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lschleme@calpoly.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000464341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/15/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Polytechnic State University Foundation]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN LUIS OBISPO</CityName>
<ZipCode>934079000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8057562982</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 GRAND AVE BLDG 15]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MC4RJJM9XLT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CAL POLY CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Polytechnic State University]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN LUIS OBISPO</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>934079000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 GRAND AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
