<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: International Year of Quantum (IYQ) Educational Leadership Conferences]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99983.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99983</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wu He</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wuhe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>International Year of Quantum Educational Leadership Conferences (IYQ Conferences), a partnership between Stony Brook University and Brookhaven National Laboratory (BNL), will advance physical science literacy and diversify the science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) pipeline by disseminating critical information regarding quantum information science and technology (QIST) access, teaching, and learning for K-12 school district leaders, teachers, and students. IYQ Conferences are planned for Fall 2024 to coincide with the upcoming International Year of Quantum in 2025. This innovative approach to K-12 quantum education will be a replicable model for grass-roots efforts to implement quantum learning and reform state-level STEM curricula to reflect QIST advancements in research and practice. The first one-day conference, the IYQ School District Leadership Conference, will host 100 STEM leaders who serve as superintendents, assistant superintendents, and/or STEM directors. The project will strengthen their commitment to district-wide quantum education so they may facilitate QIST learning. The second one-day conference, the IYQ Teacher Leadership Conference, will host 120 K-12 STEM teachers and 40 high school students at BNL. This event is designed to engage, inspire, and motivate K-12 teachers and students in learning QIST research innovations and connection to STEM disciplinary content. When considering indirect impacts, the 100 school district leaders oversee approximately 250,000 K-12 students, and the 120 teacher participants will indirectly impact 15,000 K-12 students, for a total of 265,000 students. This represents a monumental large-scale effort to broaden participation in QIST education. In addition, a newly formed EduQation Network will disseminate resources and opportunities to all district leaders and teachers throughout the Southeast New York region and beyond.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;IYQ Conferences will focus upon diversity in two ways: (1) promoting quantum sciences and computing among precollege school district leaders, teachers, and students, particularly those with high representations of  traditionally underserved students, and (2) establishing a regional network for coordinating resources and training for implementing QIST curricula and promoting careers in developing next-generation technologies. Research and evaluation activities are aligned with the overarching goals of ITEST, including (1) the development of QIST knowledge and practices that promote critical thinking, reasoning, and communication skills; and (2) increased student knowledge and interest in QIST careers and academic pathways. The research and evaluation plan will measure both immediate and midterm outcomes for school district leaders, teachers, and students. The research plan includes both quantitative and qualitative components to measure immediate outcomes and outcomes 3-4 months post-conference. The project team will further analyze outcomes with a 6-month review of participant involvement in the newly developed QIST education network. The outcomes will be analyzed through quantitative measurement of website views and posts, along with interviews with teachers and administrators to determine district-level policy shifts and initiatives and teacher implementation of QIST content and career advisement. This project is funded by the Innovative Technology Experiences for Students and Teachers (ITEST) program, which supports projects that build understandings of practices, program elements, contexts and processes contributing to increasing students' knowledge and interest in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) and information and communication technology (ICT) careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2414742</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dominik</FirstName>
<LastName>Schneble</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dominik Schneble</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Dominik.Schneble@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000078054</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Kelly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angela M Kelly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[angela.kelly@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000499016</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tzu-Chieh</FirstName>
<LastName>Wei</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tzu-Chieh Wei</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tzu-chieh.wei@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000602954</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL L]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL LIBRARY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>722700</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>1300PYXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[H-1B FUND, EDU, NSF]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>045176</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~99983</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
