<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[PFI-RP: A Novel Technique for Sustainable and Resilient Enhancement of Coastal Soils]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1000000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samir M. Iqbal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smiqbal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927529</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this Partnerships for Innovation – Research Partnership (PFI-RP) project is to develop innovative, cost-effective, and environmentally friendly soil improvement solution for coastal regions. This technology addresses a hidden but serious climate-induced hazard to coastal civil infrastructure due to seawater intrusion and concomitant soil salinization. Traditional calcium-based methods of stabilization are neither effective nor sustainable due to high energy consumption and large carbon emissions in their manufacturing process. This technology offers a greener alternative with a significant market potential and applications to civil infrastructure, water systems, and other ground improvement projects.  The market size is expected to grow to $30.2 billion by 2032. This project seeks to create socio-economic benefits by enhancing the sustainability and climate resilience of coastal communities. Additionally, the project addresses global issues such as conserving energy and resource recovery by recycling waste materials. The use-inspired, translational research will replace the current, non-sustainable calcium-based stabilization practice, generating jobs and promoting the adoption of the new materials and technologies. An integrated entrepreneurial educational and leadership development plan will be used to train graduate students to become future entrepreneurship leaders in advanced, next-generation soil improvement technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project presents an innovative, cost-effective, and practical solution to improve saline coastal soils when traditional Portland cement-based methods are ineffective or even problematic. The soil improvement technology addresses technological, industrial, and market needs by developing cost-effective and ‘greener’ soil stabilizer derived from abundant industrial waste (i.e., fly ash-based geopolymer). Such a soil stabilizer is technically sound for treating salt-bearing coastal soils. The research objectives of this project are to: (i) Optimize fly ash-based geopolymers suitable for improving coastal salt-bearing soils; (ii) Develop a soil improvement procedure that is ready for engineering implementation by holistically considering strength development, volume change, and durability through medium-scale laboratory experiments; and (iii) Demonstrate cost effectiveness, and environmental and resiliency benefits of the soil improvement technology by performing life cycle cost and environmental impact assessments, facilitating commercialization and adoption.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2414953</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Martin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly Martin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kimberly.martin@keller-na.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000880483</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mingjiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Tao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mingjiang Tao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[taomj@wpi.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000285742</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anand</FirstName>
<LastName>Puppala</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anand J Puppala</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[anandp@tamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000357815</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Worcester Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5088315000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 INSTITUTE RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HJNQME41NBU4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WORCESTER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Worcester Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 INSTITUTE RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>166200</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~1000000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
