<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Using Peptides for Biomolecules Encapsulation, Storage, and Preservation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jaime A. Camelio</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcamelio@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922061</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a versatile biomolecule preservation solution with applications spanning diverse industries, including pharmaceuticals, cosmetics, food, personal care, agriculture, and more. This innovation stands to address significant societal and commercial challenges by enhancing the stability and longevity of biomolecules. An initial focus will consider the protein based pharmaceutical sector, especially in logistics and manufacturing, with a $265.16 billion market in 2022 and projected growth. When examining existing protein preservation methods such as lyophilization and cold temperature storage, the integration into lyophilization services for biopharmaceuticals and the cold logistic chain in healthcare sectors collectively accounts for an estimated $23 billion in revenue in 2022. Additionally, there are opportunities to benefit the agriculture and household products sectors by addressing analogous storage challenges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a technology involving simple peptides designed for the formation of highly porous particles and foams upon air drying. These peptides exhibit a unique capability for phase separation, creating porous solid foams that efficiently trap and protect diverse molecular payloads. These designed peptides, distinct from biological counterparts, enable a reversible drying-induced phase separation and encapsulation process. Upon reintroduction of water, the porous solid foams, resembling dry powder, and effortlessly dissolves, showcasing an efficient release and dispersion mechanism for molecular payloads. This technology offers several advantages, including mechanical robustness and size tunability of the porous particle powders. Unlike traditional emulsification methods, this approach does not necessitate mechanical energy but relies on an energy-efficient evaporation process for phase separation and encapsulation. Moreover, the use of biocompatible and biodegradable peptides enhances the environmental- and cost-effectiveness of the system. Ongoing research focuses on expanding the applications to encapsulate pharmaceutical, nutraceutical, and cosmetic payloads, showcasing the broad potential of this technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/29/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2414552</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rein</FirstName>
<LastName>Ulijn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rein Ulijn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rulijn@gc.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000683315</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Research Foundation CUNY - Advanced Science Research Center]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100311246</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2124133330</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[85 SAINT NICHOLAS TER]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EUYXHRL5MLL3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Research Foundation CUNY - Advanced Science Research Center]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100311246</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[85 SAINT NICHOLAS TER]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
