<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel: NSF Student Travel Grant for the 2024 ACM International Conference on Mobile Systems, Applications, and Services (MobiSys)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Lyles</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jlyles@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922087</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Association for Computing Machinery’s International Conference on Mobile Systems, Applications, and Services (ACM MobiSys) is the premier academic conference for presenting innovative and significant research of mobile systems, applications, and services. The research topics of MobiSys span multiple disciplines, including wireless networks and communication, mobile sensing and crowdsourcing applications, wearable computing, vehicular and robotic wireless systems, operating systems, distributed algorithms, data management, energy management, sensors, security, and privacy. ACM MobiSys brings together academic, industry, and government professionals to a single-track, highly selective forum, to exchange technological advances of mobile systems, applications, and services. Authors will have the opportunity to present their work and all attendees have a chance to interact with other researchers who perform leading-edge research in this domain. Attending MobiSys is of paramount importance for students pursuing research in this field. The goal of this student travel support is to widen the student audience and promote the level of interaction and research engagement of students, especially ones who are not well-funded, under-represented, or otherwise unlikely to be able to attend this high-profile conference on mobile systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The grant will support approximate 10-12 student participants from recognized U.S. institutions of higher education. The opportunity will be widely advertised among the potential conference attendees. Awardees will be selected by a student travel grant committee, based on student qualification and benefits to be received from attending the conference. Priority will be given to underfunded or underrepresented students. Student awardees will attend the conference and have opportunities to exchange innovative ideas in a vibrant field, which will significantly influence their future research directions. By enabling students (who might not otherwise be able) to attend the conference, this project increases the dissemination of MobiSys’s research results to a larger and more diverse audience. It also integrates research and education of students by enabling students to observe high-quality presentations and interact with other researchers. By giving consideration in granting awards to women and minority students, it widens the participation among underrepresented groups. Furthermore, by advertising the opportunity among a wide range of colleges and universities, participants from a more diverse set of institutions would be able to attend and benefit from the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2414460</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Xia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen Xia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[stephen.xia@northwestern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000956674</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>EVANSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>602080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[633 CLARK ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EXZVPWZBLUE8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>EVANSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602083118</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2145 Sheridan Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>736300</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~20000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
