<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Defects in Semiconductors GRC/GRS]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yaroslav Koshka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ykoshka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924986</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Non-technical description:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Semiconductors are essential for a variety of applications including computing, power, energy and quantum information. A key component in determining a semiconductor’s properties are defects in the semiconductor crystal. Thus, understanding and controlling defects in semiconductor materials and devices has been of fundamental importance to the semiconductor industry from its inception. In the ever-changing landscape of semiconductor technologies, advancements are required in theory, characterization, and control of defects. The Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Defects in Semiconductors is held biannually and offers a unique opportunity for scientists and technologists to address key questions and opportunities associated with defects across the full spectrum of semiconductor materials and devices. The off-the-record format of the conference allows for full and frank discussion of new discoveries and challenges, enabling the acceleration of discovery. The Gordon Research Conference is complemented by a highly successful Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) designed by and for graduate students and postdoctoral fellows. Attendance at both the GRS and GRC provides young scientists with a unique opportunity to actively engage in this area of research that is of fundamental importance to existing and future developments in semiconductor and quantum technologies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical description&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will bring together experts and early career scientists in theory, characterization, control, and device impact of defects in a broad range of semiconductors. Focus areas include defects under extreme conditions, defects in low-dimensional systems, new defect discovery and identification for quantum information applications, advances in modelling correlated electron systems, perovskites resistance to defects and breakthroughs in characterization. Technological applications range from electronics for power generation, power distribution, and lighting to spintronics and quantum information processing. The two-day GRS precedes the GRC, acclimatizing young scientists to the unique style of Gordon Conferences and encouraging them to share and present their ideas to their peers. The knowledge gained at the GRS/GRC will assist their research pursuits and provide opportunities to foster new research linkages and obtain mentorship from experts in the field. Students and post-doctoral fellows will take the new knowledge and linkages they gain at the GRS/GRC back to their research groups, thereby broadening research opportunities and direction.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2414677</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kai-Mei</FirstName>
<LastName>Fu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kai-Mei Fu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kaimeifu@uw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000586827</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/14/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5586 POST RD UNIT 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>106Z</Code>
<Text>Microelectronics and Semiconductors</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8607</Code>
<Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~5000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
