<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel: IEEE International Conference on Healthcare Informatics (IEEE ICHI 2024) Doctoral Consortium Travel Scholarship]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Goli Yamini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gyamini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925367</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports ten doctoral students in educational institutions in the United States' to participate in IEEE International Conference on Healthcare Informatics (ICHI 2024) Doctoral Consortium Program in Orlando, Florida, USA. Students who are selected will receive funding to cover their expenditures on registration, travel, and lodging. Students will be scheduled for a rapid-fire talk to present a synopsis of their work, which provides a forum for expert and peer critique of students' research with the goal of improving their science. Awardee students will also have the opportunity to receive networking support and career advice from internationally recognized experts. The consortium also features a panel discussion covering topics relevant to doctoral students (e.g., dissertation proposal, dissertation execution, job search, and grant seeking). This award promotes the training and development of the future generation of leaders and workforce, as well as enhances the participation of women and minority students in this critical field. Therefore, this award promotes interdisciplinary research by inviting student participants from diverse fields to advance the research at the intersection of computing and health informatics. Overall, the award support brings together students with experts who might not otherwise engage with one another and engage in multidisciplinary science in the area of health. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ICHI 2024 is the premier community forum focusing on the application of computer science principles, information science principles, information technology, and communication technology to address problems in healthcare, public health, and everyday wellness. The conference highlights the most novel technical contributions in computing-oriented health informatics and the related social and ethical implications. ICHI 2024 exposes participants to different scientific disciplinary approaches, supports networking with conference attendees and is designed to support the development of the next generation of scholars in health- and bioinformatics. Specific topics of interest for this conference cover various facets of health informatics research grouped into three tracks: analytics track, human factors track, and system track. The ICHI conference has the following goals: (1) Foster interdisciplinary education among healthcare informatics students, researchers, and practitioners. (2) Promote research design and methodology development in the emerging fields. (3) Coalesce knowledge translation between academia and industry/government. The conference has been organized successfully every year since 2010 in Washington DC, USA (ICHI 2010), 2012 in Miami, Florida, USA (ICHI 2012), 2013 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA (ICHI 2013), 2014 in Verona, Italy (ICHI 2014), 2015 in Dallas, Texas, USA (ICHI 2015,), 2016 in Chicago, Illinois, USA (ICHI 2016), 2017 in Park City, Utah, USA (ICHI 2017), 2018 in New York City, USA (ICHI 2018), 2019 in Xi’an, China (ICHI 2019), 2020 in Oldenburg, Germany (ICHI 2020), 2021 in Victoria, Canada (ICHI 2021), 2022 in Rochester, Minnesota (ICHI 2022), and 2023 in Houston, Texas, USA (ICHI 2023).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2414093</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhan</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhan Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zzhang@pace.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000785002</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pace University New York Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100381502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2123461200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 PACE PLZ]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y738A5L1B3V1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PACE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pace University New York Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100381502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 PACE PLZ]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>736400</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~18000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
