<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: Understanding the Stability of MXene-Confined Nanolayer Catalysts for Ethane Dehydrogenation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>165802.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>165802</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The traditional chemical process for producing plastic and other polymeric products from natural gas starts with the thermal steam cracking of ethane or propane to produce ethylene and propylene.  For ethane, in particular, the overall process is extremely energy-intensive resulting in huge emissions of the greenhouse gas carbon dioxide (CO2).  Catalytic processes offer opportunities to reduce the energy demands and associated CO2 emissions, but are hampered by the formation of carbon deposits (i.e., coke) on the catalyst surface, and coalescence of the small platinum (Pt) catalyst particles into larger particles – both of which decrease the catalyst performance and require frequent catalyst regeneration.  The project addresses both deactivation modes via a novel class of catalysts known as MXenes.  Recently, the investigators developed an atomically thin Pt nanolayer catalyst supported on a molybdenum-titanium-carbon MXene.  The catalyst was evaluated for the catalytic dehydrogenation of ethane and propane into ethylene and propylene, and, as compared to Pt nanoparticles, the Pt nanolayer catalyst showed superior coke-resistance, sinter-resistance, high activity and selectivity toward ethylene and propylene.  Nevertheless, further advances in catalyst design are needed for commercial use.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;The project will advance the basic science of heterogeneous catalysis by addressing a critical gap in understanding the stability of the unique Pt nanolayer/Mo 2TiC2 MXene catalyst.  A multidisciplinary research approach will be undertaken, involving materials synthesis, in situ/operando characterization, theoretical computation, kinetics measurement, and reaction-diffusion model development.  Collectively, the research thrusts will provide foundational insights related to the stability and coking resistance of MXene-supported Pt-group catalysts, thus providing a basis for improved catalyst formulations and designs.  Beyond the technical aspects, the knowledge gained from this project will foster the development of a skilled technical workforce and drive innovation in the chemical and petroleum industries. The multidisciplinary research and the integration of research and education will provide both undergraduate and graduate students with a unique training experience in materials science, catalysis science, reaction engineering, computational chemistry, and kinetic modeling. The research results will be integrated with chemical engineering curricula at both Louisiana Tech University and Iowa State University, and also support K-12 STEM outreach at local schools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2414205</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yue</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yue Wu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yuewu@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000528779</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112103</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1350 BEARDSHEAR HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[515 MORRILL ROAD]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DQDBM7FGJPC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>DQDBM7FGJPC5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112105</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[515 MORRILL RD, 1350 BEARDSHEAR HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>164200</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~165802</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
