<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Doctoral Dissertation Research: Messaging to Reduce Cannabis Use among US Young Adults]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29878.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29878</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>roconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927263</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The US cannabis policy and retail contexts have markedly changed in the past decade. During this time, cannabis use prevalence increased in adults, particularly young adults and certain racial, ethnic, sexual, and gender minorities The disproportionate use rates may reflect evidence of cannabis industry target markets. States vary regarding their regulations for cannabis advertising (e.g., health claims, youth-targeting) and required health warnings, which may have implications for cannabis-related disparities. Advertising restrictions are important, given that product ads and/or characteristics (e.g., flavors) may appeal to specific groups, and the use of health claims, price promotions, and various marketing channels (e.g., digital media). Health warnings can effectively communicate risks and reduce substance use rates. This research aims to reduce cannabis use and related disparities by advancing the evidence regarding risk perceptions, use decisions, and their determinants, specifically cannabis regulations and industry marketing. This study is among the first to address key research gaps including limited research: a) comprehensively analyzing cannabis marketing data; b) using industry market research strategies to understand lifestyle profiles of young adults most likely to use cannabis; and c) of cannabis ad and warning messages.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This mixed-methods study will address 3 aims. Aim 1 examines cannabis marketing characteristics (e.g., advertising content, media channels used, ad expenditures) over time with regard to state and local cannabis retail rules by analyzing existing longitudinal marketing data. Aim 2 assesses cannabis marketing exposure, perceptions, and use behaviors (i.e., intentions, use) over time across young adults with different lifestyle profiles by analyzing data from an existing national cohort of diverse young adults. Aim 3 explores the impact of different ad and warning messages on risk perceptions and use decisions among young adults by conducting a series of online survey-based experiments. This research protects public health and improves population-level well-being by advancing evidence regarding social determinants of cannabis use to inform regulatory efforts to reduce use among disproportionately-impacted groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2415890</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carla</FirstName>
<LastName>Berg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carla Berg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[carlaberg@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000989341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuxian</FirstName>
<LastName>Cui</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuxian Cui</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ycui15@gwu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000989491</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1918 F ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECR5E2LU5BL6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY (THE)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520042</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[950 New Hampshire Ave NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>132100</Code>
<Text>Decision, Risk &amp; Mgmt Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~29878</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
