<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 NanoFlorida Conference: New Frontiers in Nanoscale interactions]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nosavage@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[Nanotechnology research and commercialized products are increasing their presence and being integrated into society and will likely remain at the forefront of scientific discoveries and applications for the next decade and beyond. Advancing nanoscience and disseminating the advances in the field remains a pivotal need. To this end, the Florida Association for Nanotechnology founded in 2019, creates a collaborative network of researchers, faculty, industry affiliates, and students in the diverse fields of nanoscience and nanotechnology. Herein proposes to conduct its annual NanoFlorida Conference to be held on April 20-21, 2024, in Tallahassee, Florida, hosted jointly by Florida State University and Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University.  The conference aims are: i) to discuss advances in the understanding of nanoscale interaction, processing  and awareness, and ii) provide a platform for scientific exchange with a focus on enhancing student and postdoc participation in the conference.  Having extensive experience in organizing professional student conferences, the Principal Investigator will utilize post-conference surveys and publications of presenters’ research to measure the success of this year’s conference objectives. Conference will feature and promote collaborative and interdisciplinary research by hosting presentations by experts in the field, and providing new insights into nanoscale interactions for nanoscientists, clinicians, and engineers, and expanding multidisciplinary STEM education toward the next generation workforce. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The annual NanoFlorida Conference, which aims to promote and increase awareness of nanotechnology applications and nanoscale interactions, will be held in Tallahassee, FL on April 20-21, 2024, hosted by Florida State University and Florida Agricultural and Mechanical University. This year’s conference will include symposia on advances in nanoscale interactions, artificial intelligence in nanotechnology, nanomaterials, and devices for biosensing, and their applications in energy, medicine, agriculture, and space sciences; and provide new opportunities for students to network with researchers from academic institutions and the broader nanotechnology industry. The Conference will use funds to support presenters ensuring diversity, inclusion, access, and equity in selecting these students, postdocs, and faculty participants and oral or poster presentations. Conference objectives encompass promoting collaborative and interdisciplinary research, expanding multidisciplinary education and research projects, hosting presentations by experts in the field, and providing new insights into nanoscale interactions for nanoscientists, clinicians, and engineers. Students will have the opportunity to meet researchers from other institutions and industry settings, forming professional relationships that provide long-term benefits to advance their STEM education and careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2415310</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shyam</FirstName>
<LastName>Mohapatra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shyam S Mohapatra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Fan.network.info@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000991426</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>FLORIDA ASSOCIATION FOR NANOBIOTECHNOLOGY, INC</Name>
<CityName>LUTZ</CityName>
<ZipCode>335584864</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8133124248</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>16704 TOBACCO RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>WTCDCM9B8BP6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA ASSOCIATION FOR NANOBIOTECHNOLOGY, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FLORIDA ASSOCIATION FOR NANOBIOTECHNOLOGY, INC]]></Name>
<CityName>LUTZ</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>335584864</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[16704 TOBACCO RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1179</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Interactions Program</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~30000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
