<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Foundations of Molecular Modeling and Simulation Conference (FOMMS)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29825.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29825</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Dawes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rdawes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927486</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is funded by contributions from the Chemical Theory, Models, and Computational Methods program of the Division of Chemistry, the Interfacial Engineering and Process Systems, Reaction Engineering, and Molecular Thermodynamics programs of the Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental and Transport Systems and the Condensed Matter and Materials Theory program of the Division of Materials Research. This grant will make it possible for over 30 graduate students and postdocs and 10 early career researchers to attend the 90th triennial conference on the Foundations of Molecular Modeling and Simulation (FOMMS 2024) to be held in Snowbird, UT from July 28 to August 1, 2024. Molecular-level modeling and simulation are ubiquitous tools for advancing science and engineering in applications ranging from the design of new materials to understanding how drug molecules interact with protein receptors in the body. The FOMMS conference series was initiated in 2000 to foster interaction among academic, national laboratory, and industrial molecular researchers developing and applying molecular-based computational methods. FOMMS 2024 will feature 15 plenary speakers, one keynote speaker, a FOMMS Metal Lecture, workshops with an educational focus, and two poster sessions. With no parallel sessions, the meeting structure is designed to encourage formal and informal interactions between established and early career researchers and promote mentoring of the latter. The diverse and international selection of invited speakers strikes a balance between industrial and academic researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theme of FOMMS 2024 is “Molecular Modeling Across Scales”, recognizing the key role connecting disparate length and time scales plays in making prediction and using physics-based modeling to understand complex systems. Participants include experts from molecular simulations, proteins and biological systems, acceleration algorithms, soft materials and complex fluid, simulation-based engineering &amp; science, and quantum computing and emerging architectures for modeling and simulation, computational quantum chemistry, statistical mechanics, molecular simulation and theory, and continuum and engineering process simulation. The conference will serve as a venue to bring together experts from different fields to spur new discussions and seed collaborations that will lead to innovative applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2416473</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Evan</FirstName>
<LastName>Flach</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Evan Flach</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[evanf@aiche.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000662136</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Institute of Chemical Engineers]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100055991</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6464951350</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[120 WALL ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[23 FLO]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>KLPNCLPDAS45</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN INSTITUTE OF CHEMICAL ENGINEERS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Institute of Chemical Engineers]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100055991</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[120 WALL ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>140300</Code>
<Text>Proc Sys, Reac Eng &amp; Mol Therm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>141700</Code>
<Text>Interfacial Engineering Progra</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>176500</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>688100</Code>
<Text>Chem Thry, Mdls &amp; Cmptnl Mthds</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>054Z</Code>
<Text>(MGI) Materials Genome Initiative</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~29825</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
