<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Ninth Biennial Conference on Social Dilemmas]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49786.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49786</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Lutz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nlutz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927280</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Ninth Biennial Conference on Social Dilemmas builds upon a rich tradition of interdisciplinary collaboration initiated at Indiana University by Nobel Laureate Elinor Ostrom. This conference series, initiated in 2003, aims to deepen the understanding of collective action in social dilemma settings such as public goods provision, natural resource extraction, and climate change. Social dilemmas are situations where individual incentives conflict with collective interests. Understanding their dynamics is essential for developing effective policies and strategies that promote cooperative behavior for the greater good. The conference promotes and disseminates state-of-the-art research on social dilemmas. Furthermore, the ninth conference seeks to identify scientific and political issues concerning social dilemmas, with emphasis on relatively under researched and highly relevant areas such as conflict resolution, environmental and climate change economics, revisited considering recent developments, and the increasing use of Artificial Intelligence in these contexts. The introduction of Artificial Intelligence's (AIs) role in solving social dilemmas to the workshop's agenda is a particularly timely and innovative addition. This event brings together leading scholars from diverse disciplines, to share their latest research and insights. Emphasizing mentoring, the conference includes dedicated sessions for young scholars, particularly those from underrepresented groups, to support their professional growth and inclusion in these crucial research fields. These efforts aim to facilitate the inclusion and exchange of diverse perspectives and enhance the effectiveness of self-organized collective action and policy initiatives addressing critical societal challenges. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Ninth Biennial Conference on Social Dilemmas convenes a multidisciplinary group of researchers to discuss advanced topics in social dilemmas. The conference will feature sessions on a broad range of topics, featuring research that spans various methodologies, including theory, experimental methods, survey methods, and field data analysis. Specific sessions will be dedicated to pressing contemporary issues such as conflict resolution, environmental economics, and AI applications to social dilemmas. A significant component of the conference is its mentoring program, designed to support graduate students and junior faculty by providing them with high-quality feedback and fostering long-term professional relationships. This initiative aims to diversify the research community by prioritizing the inclusion of women, minorities, and researchers facing financial barriers. Mentoring activities include structured interactions between senior and junior researchers, dedicated mentoring lunch meetings, and a breakfast session focused on demystifying the publication process. These mentoring activities provide young scholars with the guidance and support necessary to advance their research careers. The conference builds on the success of previous social dilemma workshops, which have consistently promoted state-of-the-art research and generated new collaborations. Research presented at the conference will be disseminated through a special issue in a peer-reviewed journal, continuing the tradition of past publications. The conference represents a unique opportunity to advance the understanding of collective action problems and develop practical solutions to some of society’s most pressing challenges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2417765</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Walker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James M Walker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[walkerj@indiana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000350099</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniela</FirstName>
<LastName>Puzzello</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniela Puzzello</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dpuzzell@indiana.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000645687</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ala</FirstName>
<LastName>Avoyan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ala Avoyan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aavoyan@iu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000990272</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>BLOOMINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>474057000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[107 S INDIANA AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YH86RTW2YVJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>BLOOMINGTON</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474057000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[107 S INDIANA AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>132000</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~49786</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
