<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RII FEC: Advancing Climate Neutrality in Farming Communities through Upcycling Natural Fiber Reinforced Fireproof Vitrimer Composites]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2028</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5999999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>3000000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OIA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>OIA-Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benjamin J. McCall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bjmccall@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927916</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This multidisciplinary project is spearheaded by a R2 Historically Black College and University (Southern University and A&amp;M College) and includes collaborators from three R1 institutions (University of Delaware, Clemson University, Louisiana State University), a technical college (Trident Technical College), and a minority-owned small business (BrightMa Farms). The project aims to develop sustainable materials and manufacturing methods that address the impacts of climate change. The project focuses on two main goals. First, the project will create innovative farming methods to improve soil and plant conditions in areas affected by climate change to grow natural fibers. Second, researchers will use these natural fibers to replace synthetic fibers like carbon or glass in making high-performance, fireproof, and recyclable composite materials. These new composites will provide a climate-neutral and sustainable solution for various applications that require lightweight materials. This approach not only aims to reduce greenhouse gas emissions but also offers economic opportunities for communities disproportionately affected by climate change, fostering a resilient and sustainable agricultural sector. Additionally, the project emphasizes workforce development by training a diverse group of students and professionals, ranging from pre-college students to junior faculty, enhancing the STEM workforce essential for addressing climate challenges. This initiative aligns with NSF’s mission to promote the progress of science, advance national health, prosperity, and welfare, and secure national defense by contributing to the development of innovative and sustainable solutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technically, the project aims to address several challenges in converting natural fibers into high-performance composites. The research focuses on enhancing natural fiber properties through advanced plant and farming management techniques, designing fireproof shape memory vitrimers (FSMVs) using machine learning, and developing novel fiber alignment processes. The challenges include variability in fiber properties, poor fiber-matrix compatibility, high moisture absorption, and susceptibility to flame. By combining natural fibers with FSMVs, the project aims to protect the fibers from fire hazards. The research will generate fundamental knowledge on the processing and optimization of natural fibers, ensuring good suspension in dispersion fluids and high packing efficiency in aligned composites. The project will also explore the production of complex parts using in-plane extensible short fiber composites, optimizing processes to meet performance and cost requirements for mass-market applications. The collaboration with BrightMa Farms will facilitate the training of displaced minority farmers, transitioning research findings into practical applications. Ultimately, the project aims to demonstrate the feasibility and scalability of these sustainable composites that can be used in various applications, such as consumer goods and automotive, replacing traditional metallic solutions and advancing sustainable manufacturing practices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2418415</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dirk</FirstName>
<LastName>Heider</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dirk Heider</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[heider@udel.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000238699</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guoqiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Guoqiang Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[guoqiang_li@subr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000360421</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cheng</FirstName>
<LastName>Yan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cheng Yan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cheng.yan@sus.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000919759</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maryam</FirstName>
<LastName>Jahan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maryam Jahan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[maryam_jahan@subr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000816249</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gang</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gang Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gli@clemson.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000317872</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southern University]]></Name>
<CityName>BATON ROUGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>708075304</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2257712809</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[730 HARDING BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H7CJA7NX9WN3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTHERN UNIVERSITY AND A &amp; M COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southern University]]></Name>
<CityName>BATON ROUGE</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708075326</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[801 HARDING BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>194Y00</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR RII Track-2 FEC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5294</Code>
<Text>USGCRP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~3000000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
