<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Thiol-Based Redox Regulation and Signaling GRC and GRS: Mechanisms and Consequences of Redox Signaling]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Loretta Jackson-Hayes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lojackso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924286</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award supports the 9th biennial Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and the associated Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) on Thiol-Based Redox Regulation and Signaling to be held July 13-19, 2024, at the Rey Don Jaime Grand Hotel in Castelldefels, Spain. This GRC/GRS brings together a diverse international community of chemical biologists, biochemists, cell biologists, and physiologists for a multi-day intensive meeting to present and discuss the latest research in the field, outline the future directions of that work, and establish collaborative relationships to accomplish this future research. The focused, intimate conference format will offer ample opportunities for attendees to engage in in-depth research discussions and facilitate networking. Funds from this award are strictly applied to defray registration costs for U.S.-based graduate students and postdoctoral trainees, to facilitate attendance of a diverse groups of participants from early stages of their careers. A unique professional development opportunity for junior scientists is provided by the GRS. This pre-GRC component of the Conference experience is organized by and for graduate students and postdoctoral fellows, enabling conference planning experience and programming focused on integrating junior scientists into the redox signaling community, promoting the engagement and mentoring of the next generation of scientists, and ensuring the continued vitality of this research field. GRC attendees abide by a strict off-the-record policy to encourage open communication and collaboration, creating a distinctive intellectual experience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theme of the 2024 GRC is the mechanisms of thiol-based redox signaling, with an emphasis on the spatial and temporal aspects of signaling within and between cells that control life and death decisions. Major meeting topics include tools and technologies for redox biology, signaling via low molecular weight thiols and post-translational modifications, redox control of protein biogenesis and turnover, reactive sulfur species and protein-redox switches, lipid oxidation and redox-dependent cell death, inter-organelle and inter-cellular redox crosstalk, host-pathogen and immune responses, and redox-signaling in metabolism and age-associated pathologies. This GRC/GRS will integrate research, education, training, and career development by strongly encouraging the active participation of a diverse group of junior scientists (graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and newly appointed faculty) in all aspects of the conference. In addition to formal talks, the conferences include designated time for poster sessions from individuals of all career stages. Poster previews during the morning plenary GRC sessions, a career development panel during the GRS, and a PowerHour event during the GRC, will further support the professional growth of all members of our community. The success of the meeting will be assessed using established GRC guidelines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2418618</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Sevier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carolyn Sevier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[css224@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000919156</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5586 POST RD UNIT 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~15000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
