<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Translation Potential of Agricultural Nanofertilizers]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Molly Wasko</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mwasko@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924749</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this I-Corps project is based on the development of nanofertilizers, fertilizers composed of nanoparticles, which have shown potential in enhancing crop yields. Currently, the high cost associated with nanomaterial manufacturing limits the use of nanofertilizers outside of research. Addressing this critical hurdle, the potential advantage of this innovation is the development of a new manufacturing platform for the production of low-cost nanofertilizers using green chemistry methods. This technology could make nanofertilizers accessible to domestic and global agriculture within the next 10 years. Overall, the broad applicability of nanofertilizers has the potential to enable high throughput manufacturing of crop-specific fertilizers. This approach could lead to mass-customization of fertilizer composition, tailored to an individual grower’s needs, to maximize efficiency using more sustainable farming practices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translation potential of the technology. The solution is based on the development of highly bioavailable nanoparticle-based fertilizers for increasing nutrient use efficiency and leverages a green chemistry approach for the scalable manufacturing of nanoparticle-based fertilizers. This innovative approach focuses on nanofertilizers, fertilizers composed of nanoparticles, which have shown potential in enhancing crop yields while significantly reducing the amount of raw material nutrient ingredients and waste. The efficacy of this innovation stems from the superior bioavailability of nanoparticles, which allows plants to uptake nutrients more efficiently than traditional fertilizers. Furthermore, nanofertilizers can be tailored through minor production chemistry changes, enabling specific benefits like crop selectivity in weed-rich areas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/22/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/22/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2418523</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Zimmerman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julie B Zimmerman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[julie.zimmerman@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000194351</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/22/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW HAVEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065113572</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[150 MUNSON ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIV</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FL6GV84CKN57</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW HAVEN</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065118917</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[17 Hillhouse Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9223</Code>
<Text>ENVIRON BENIGN CHEMICAL SYNTH &amp; PROCESS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
