<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[LEAPS-MPS: Controllable Disorder as a Path to Many-Body Entanglement in Quantum Magnets]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mun Chan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mchan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical Description:&lt;br/&gt;Quantum information technologies rely on quantum entanglement, or the intrinsic linking of one quantum object to another. An important research objective is to gain a fundamental understanding of many-body quantum entanglement involving large numbers of quantum objects. Certain magnetic materials known as geometrically frustrated magnets provide a valuable platform for this topic of study because they may exhibit many-body entanglement at low temperature. This project advances the search for promising quantum-entangled frustrated magnets through a systematic investigation of the role of atomic-scale disorder in promoting or hindering many-body entanglement. The results illuminate strategies for utilizing disorder to promote quantum-entangled ground states and contribute to a deeper understanding of many-body quantum entanglement in general. These research activities are integrated into education and outreach efforts including intensive undergraduate mentoring, summer research internships for diverse students, and a new organization called the Physics Breakfast Club that supports regional high-school physics teachers by building community and providing teaching resources.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Technical Description:&lt;br/&gt;Recent work suggests that disorder in certain types of frustrated magnets can stabilize entangled magnetic states such as a quantum spin liquid. This project explores that idea in the context of rare-earth pyrochlore compounds with mixed atomic species on the nonmagnetic metal/metalloid site. The level of random disorder can be controlled by the size mismatch of the different atomic species, allowing a systematic investigation of the influence of disorder on the formation of a quantum spin liquid or a related phase in disordered pyrochlore compounds. The goals are to develop guiding principles for utilizing disorder as a tool for stabilizing entangled magnetic states and evaluate the potential of disordered pyrochlores for achieving these states. The magnetic and structural properties of the materials are characterized by state-of-the-art techniques including x-ray and neutron total scattering, muon spin spectroscopy, and inelastic neutron scattering. This multi-modal methodological approach is ideally suited to gaining a comprehensive understanding of the local disorder and its effect on the magnetism in pyrochlore compounds, while also providing a template for similar studies on other materials in the future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2418438</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Frandsen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin A Frandsen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[benfrandsen@byu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000806396</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brigham Young University]]></Name>
<CityName>PROVO</CityName>
<ZipCode>846021128</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8014223360</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[A-153 ASB]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JWSYC7RUMJD1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BRIGHAM YOUNG UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brigham Young University]]></Name>
<CityName>PROVO</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>846021042</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[A-153 ASB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>217Y00</Code>
<Text>LEAPS-MPS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~249997</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
