<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[LEAPS-MPS: Understanding Clusteroluminescent Prenylated Deep Eutectic Solvents]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aschmolt@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924716</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is being funded by the MPS-LEAPS (Launching Early-Career Academic Pathways) Program and managed by the Broadening Participation (CHE-BP) Program in the Division of Chemistry. With this support, Professor Agatemor and his students at the University of Miami intend to develop and investigate photoluminophores that emit light in an aqueous environment using biocompatible and eco-friendly deep eutectic solvents (DESs). Photoluminophores, molecular entities that emit light after absorbing photons, are used in many aspects of modern life, including medicine, energy, and chemical synthesis. However, most currently used photolumiphores are toxic and quench their emission in an aqueous environment, limiting their real-world applications. Successful implementation of the project described here could enable a holistic description of photoluminescence and potentially lead to the development of sustainable science and technologies, including solar energy harvesting technologies and solar photochemical synthesis procedures.  Professor Agatemor will also contribute to strengthen diversity and inclusion in the STEM community in this project by providing hands-on training on chemical synthesis, characterization, and cell biology to students from underrepresented groups in STEM, specifically African American and Hispanic undergraduates. The training opportunity is expected to foster students' interest in STEM careers through interaction with potential role models and mentors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project aims to investigate the mechanism behind the photoluminescence of DESs.  The DESs will be facilely synthesized by mixing hydrogen bond donors with acceptors in different molar ratios, allowing control of physico-chemical and photophysical properties. The central postulation is that molecular interactions are important to the photoluminescent behavior of the DESs. Therefore, molecular interactions, such as pi-pi and hydrogen bond interactions, within the DESs and the DES-water system will be elucidated using viscometry, UV-vis absorption spectroscopy, and 1H-1H two-dimensional magic-angle spinning nuclear Overhauser effect spectroscopy.  Steady-state and time-resolved photoluminescence spectroscopies will be used to investigate the mechanism underpinning the DES emission in an aqueous environment. The photochemistry of the DES will be investigated in cell culture assays and through photochemical synthesis protocols. An expected outcome of the project is to allow students to appreciate the power of chemistry in harnessing light for various real-world applications and develop the skills for a successful STEM career.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2418863</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christian</FirstName>
<LastName>Agatemor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christian Agatemor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cxa903@miami.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000920042</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Miami]]></Name>
<CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
<ZipCode>331462919</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1320 SOUTH DIXIE HIGHWAY STE 650]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RQMFJGDTQ5V3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Miami]]></Name>
<CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331462508</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1301 Memorial Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>217Y00</Code>
<Text>LEAPS-MPS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7487</Code>
<Text>BROADENING PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~250000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
