<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[LEAPS-MPS: Enzyme-Responsive Polyolefin as A Programmable Antifouling Material]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel Savin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dsavin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924644</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Microorganisms such as bacteria and algae commonly exist in nature (e.g., in soil and oceans). Like humans settling down and building houses on land, bacteria prefer to attach to solid, wet surfaces in nature and build “houses” known as biofilms (e.g., the slime layer on our teeth or on ship hulls) to survive. Cells living in biofilms “eat” through the attached surfaces, causing significant structural and functional damage, a process known as biofilm-mediated biofouling. For example, biofilms can cause the metal in power plants to rust by secreting corrosive metabolic products or extracting electrons from the metal as “food.” This problem costs U.S. power plants about $50 billion annually. As the need for sustainable energy, such as wind power, grows, tackling biofouling becomes crucial. With the award from the LEAPS-MPS program, researchers at the University of New Haven aim to develop new antifouling materials that respond to chitinase, an enzyme commonly produced by microorganisms in Nature. These materials will be studied to determine how they prevent and remove bacterial and algae growth. This research could lead to coatings that are long-lasting and effective in preventing and removing the settlement of microorganisms, especially for use in offshore wind farms and existing power plants. In addition to advancing scientific understanding, this project supports educational and diversity initiatives. It will train a diverse group of undergraduate and graduate students in materials and surface engineering. The project will also engage high school students from rural areas through a summer camp called "Engineering Your Future," promoting innovation and interest in engineering careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This LEAPS-MPS project investigates the antifouling capabilities of a novel enzyme-responsive polyolefin, specifically poly(N-hydroxyethyl 5-Norbornene 2,3-dicarboxymide) (PNHND), in response to the enzyme chitinase. The research focuses on understanding the relationship between the properties of polyolefin surfaces, such as hydrophobicity and texture, and their effectiveness in preventing and removing microbial adhesion. A series of enzyme-responsive antifouling surfaces will be created using particle dispersion techniques. The study will test these surfaces against bacteria (Pseudomonas aeruginosa) and algae (Chlorella vulgaris) due to their common presence in marine environments. Additionally, the enzyme response kinetics of the polyolefin will be characterized. The outcome of this project will lead to a better understanding of how microorganisms interact with polyolefin surfaces, eventually leading to the systematic design of new antifouling materials. Educational initiatives will include recruiting, retaining, and training a diverse group of students in materials and surface engineering and introducing high school students to biomaterials through a summer camp. The project's broader impacts include potentially significant reductions in biofouling costs for energy facilities and advancements in biodegradable, programmable plastics to address plastic waste issues.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2418289</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Huan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Huan Gu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hgu@newhaven.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000935177</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Haven]]></Name>
<CityName>WEST HAVEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>065161916</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2039327000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 BOSTON POST RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FZBDVM1MBTN9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW HAVEN, INCORPORATED</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Haven]]></Name>
<CityName>WEST HAVEN</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065161916</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 BOSTON POST RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>217Y00</Code>
<Text>LEAPS-MPS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7273</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL RESEARCH &amp; EDUCA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~249997</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
