<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[LEAPS-MPS: Sustainable Synthesis of Substituted Tetrahydrofuran Products Using Heterogeneous Catalysts]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2026</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249935.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249935</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samy El-Shall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>selshall@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927416</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project, funded by the MPS-LEAPS (Launching Early-Career Academic Pathways) Program and managed by the Broadening Participation (CHE-BP) Program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Leslie A. Nickerson and her students at Idaho State University will perform studies that aim to develop methods using sustainable heterogeneous catalysts to synthesize substituted tetrahydrofuran (THF) products in good yield in both batch and flow systems. Substituted THF products are common moieties found in a variety of drugs. Current syntheses present challenges with the use of corrosive and toxic metal halide acid catalysts and the generation of metal-containing waste that is not easily recyclable. Professor Nickerson and her students will develop new processes for synthesizing substituted THF products with high levels of stereoselectivity using heterogeneous catalysts and sustainable solvents. Their studies could provide practical and sustainable methods to organic synthesis that can replace toxic and environmentally hazardous reactions and processes and generate less waste and more environmentally friendly products. Additionally, a diverse learning assistant program will be developed to enable the incorporation of more active learning in the classroom and provide students with role models and peer mentors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Professor Nickerson and her students will synthesize a collection of allylic acetal starting materials to test with a variety of heterogeneous catalysts to stereoselectively synthesize substituted tetrahydrofuran cores. Heterogeneous catalysts to be tested include zeolites and clays as non-toxic and environmentally sustainable alternatives to the traditional metal halide catalysts. Batch and flow systems will be explored to demonstrate the flexibility of heterogeneous catalysis in both academic and industrial settings. The reaction methodology including solvent, catalyst loading, temperature etc. will also be explored and optimized in both systems. Additionally, the mechanism of this process will be explored to determine if the tetrahydrofuran cores are formed similarly in both homogeneous and heterogeneous reactions. Further differences between homogeneous and heterogeneous versions of this reaction will be tested including identifying any impact of pore size on stereoselectivity in this process. Their results will help to contribute to the knowledge of heterogeneous catalysis as a sustainable and effective option and begin to elucidate the impact of pore size and 3D constraints to stereoselective processes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2418851</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leslie</FirstName>
<LastName>Nickerson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leslie A Nickerson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[leslienickerson@isu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000870388</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Idaho State University]]></Name>
<CityName>POCATELLO</CityName>
<ZipCode>832015377</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2082822592</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[921 S 8TH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JJC9GJJJL4M7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IDAHO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Idaho State University]]></Name>
<CityName>POCATELLO</CityName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>832015377</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[921 S 8TH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>217Y00</Code>
<Text>LEAPS-MPS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090Z</Code>
<Text>CAS-Critical Aspects of Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7487</Code>
<Text>BROADENING PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~249935</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
