<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Nanoscale Science and Engineering for Agriculture and Food Systems Gordon Research Conference and Seminar]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This conference grant provides support for U.S.-based graduate students, postdoctoral fellows, and/or early career investigators to attend the June 22-28th, 2024 Nanoscale Science and Engineering for Agriculture and Food Systems Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) at the Southern New Hampshire University in Manchester, NH. The goal of the 2024 GRC/GRS Nanotechnology for Agriculture and Food Systems is to provide academic and governmental scientists and engineers, both senior and junior, postdocs, and graduate students, as well as scientists and engineers from business, and non-governmental organizations with the framework necessary to address complex questions at the interface of agriculture, food, and nanotechnology required to develop safe and sustainable nano-enabled applications in food and agriculture systems. A diverse range of invited speakers and discussion leaders from 12 countries will present a comprehensive vision of critical and emerging nanotechnology research advances across the field of agricultural, environmental, and food science. The objectives of this GRC/GRS are: 1) Bring together experts, emerging investigators and stakeholders to discuss nanotechnology advances, directions, and needs in food and agriculture; 2) Identify cutting-edge research and emerging opportunities to address global challenges of food security, environmental sustainability, food safety, and agricultural productivity, and 3) Embolden the knowledge that “nano in food &amp; agriculture” represents a single unifying concept, rather than two distinct subfields. With growing agricultural demands on diminishing arable lands, agricultural output and food production will require innovative technologies and a collective voice of scientists, engineers, and stakeholders to address global needs. The impact of nanotechnology within information science, biotechnology, plant science, animal science, crop, and food science/technology, agricultural and biosystems engineering, and environmental science and engineering are envisioned to lead to revolutionary advances in the next 5-15 years for sustainable food production. The successful achievement of this vision requires the profound intellectual commitment of scientists and engineers in a highly integrated engagement across numerous disciplines. Nanotechnology has the potential to revolutionize global agricultural and food systems in numerous ways, and this GRC/GRS will help build a diverse community committed to advancing work in the area of nanotechnology for agriculture and food systems, leading to novel ideas and approaches to create a sustainable future. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nanoscale science and engineering has an important role in creating safer, more productive, and sustainable agriculture and food systems. Given that research at the nanoscale in agriculture and food systems is only in its second decade, it is anticipated that the “new” applications to participate in this GRC/GRS will come from persons relatively early in their careers. To encourage open communication, each conference member agrees that the presented information is private and not for public use. This collaborative GRC/GRS environment, with an emphasis on sharing previously unpublished information, enables the cultivation of innovative approaches to address the most critical global challenges. The GRC/GRS chairs will actively aim to achieve a high level of diversity distribution that includes gender, rank, professional, geographical, disability, and ethnic diversity. The significant diversity distribution of scientists and engineers will provide a viable cadre of talent to form a strong intellectual infrastructure required to develop safe and sustainable nano-enabled applications. Further, it is expected that this GRC/GRS will facilitate long-lasting international collaboration among young and senior professionals. These collaborations are expected to provide opportunities for joint projects that are anticipated to benefit U.S. science and engineering, and society at large. It is expected that this GRC/GRS will have immediate benefits for U.S. researchers who attend, and amplify benefits for domestic and international environmental sustainability efforts that originate from the exchange of ideas and collaborative projects through time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant is co-funded by the CBET's Environmental Sustainability, Biosensing, and Nanoscale Interactions programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2418296</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carmen</FirstName>
<LastName>Gomes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carmen Gomes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[carmen@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000644563</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Kah</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melanie Kah</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[melanie.kah@auckland.ac.nz]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000994095</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>117900</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Interactions Program</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>764300</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>790900</Code>
<Text>BIOSENS-Biosensing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~25000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
