<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Conference on New Developments in Probability]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>43766.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>43766</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Wilmer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ewilmer@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides support for US-based researchers to attend the Conference on New Developments in Probability (CNDP) at the Centre de Recherches Mathématiques (CRM) at Université de Montréal September 26-28, 2024. This meeting is the third CNDP, a conference series jointly organized with Women in Probability. This conference has two main goals. The first is to bring together leading experts, researchers, and scholars to explore the latest advancements in the field of probability theory and to share cutting-edge research. The second goal is to provide a platform for early career researchers in probability theory to present their work in an environment which cultivates collaboration. Probability is the backbone of many mathematical disciplines, providing the language and tools for reasoning about uncertain outcomes and making predictions based on available information, with applications in diverse fields of science, engineering, and economics. Over the years, this area has witnessed remarkable growth, with novel methodologies, techniques, and applications that transform our understanding of uncertainty and randomness. The conference is expected to have a lasting impact on the academic community of researchers in probability theory, and to foster a collaborative environment that encourages the exchange of ideas and knowledge among experts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2024 Conference on New Developments in Probability seeks to highlight recent breakthroughs in the field of probability, in particular, advancements in the areas of stochastic processes and random matrices, interacting particle systems, statistical inference and machine learning, random graphs and networks, high-dimensional probability, and stochastic analysis. This meeting will contribute to advancing the field of probability through diverse perspectives and innovative ideas, fostering the exchange of ideas and opportunities for collaboration. The conference will feature research presentations from speakers representing a range of career stages. This includes short talks by early career participants (postdocs and graduate students) who will receive advising and feedback on delivering research presentations, providing them with invaluable networking opportunities and mentorship experiences. There will be emphasis on both theoretical foundations and practical applications, leading to new research directions and interdisciplinary collaborations. The CNDP also seeks to highlight the contributions of researchers from underrepresented groups in probability, increasing their visibility within the academic community, which will lead to more opportunities for collaborations, grants, and academic positions, ultimately empowering them to progress in their careers. More details can be found at the conference website http://womeninprobability.org/CNDP.html&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2419167</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jing</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jing Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jingwang@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000703534</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tai</FirstName>
<LastName>Melcher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tai A Melcher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[melcher@virginia.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000241579</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229034833</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1001 EMMET ST N]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JJG6HU8PA4S5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RECTOR &amp; VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229034833</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1001 EMMET ST N]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>126300</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~43766</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
