<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Protein Processing, Trafficking and Secretion GRC/GRS]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Loretta Jackson-Hayes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lojackso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924286</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award supports the Protein Processing, Trafficking, and Secretion Gordon Research Conference (GRC), a seminal event held for the 15th time at Colby-Sawyer College from July 14-19, 2024, alongside the preceding Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) organized by graduate students and postdoctoral fellows on July 13-14, 2024, at the same venue. Beyond showcasing the latest discoveries in the field, these gatherings serve as crucial platforms for professional growth, nurturing the next generation of scientists, and driving societal impact through advancements in science. In addition to traditional presentations, the meetings foster interactive dialogue, providing attendees with invaluable opportunities for professional development and collaboration. From daily lunches with esteemed speakers to informal sessions with Nobel Laureates, participants engage in vibrant exchanges, transcending career stages to collectively explore new frontiers and address pressing technical and conceptual barriers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This combined GRC/GRS on Protein Processing, Trafficking, and Secretion has evolved since its inception in 1994. Originally centered on hormonal and neuropeptide biosynthesis, it now stands as a unique convergence for researchers delving into the intricate mechanisms orchestrating protein and membrane trafficking within cells, and their influence on cellular functions pivotal for health and development. The program, underscored by a multidisciplinary approach spanning biology, chemistry, computer science, engineering, mathematics, and physics, is uniquely positioned to advance mechanistic understanding across molecular, subcellular, and cellular realms. By spotlighting cutting-edge technologies and fostering interdisciplinary discourse, the conference catalyzes innovative solutions to longstanding challenges at the intersection of cell biology and physics. Ultimately, by unraveling the fundamental regulation and molecular underpinnings of protein trafficking and secretion, the research discussed has the potential to have transformative societal impacts in biotechnology and medicine rooted in understanding the dysregulation of these processes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/26/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2419301</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
<LastName>Blume</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>v</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julia v Blume</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[julia.vonblume@yale.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000992578</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mondira</FirstName>
<LastName>Kundu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mondira Kundu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Mondira.Kundu@stjude.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000990652</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5586 POST RD UNIT 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~15000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
