<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[LTER Network Office: Pathways to Participation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2029</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5499991.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1089757</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kendra McLauchlan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmclauch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922217</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Long term research- the continued measurement of a set of variables that build towards addressing a research goal over decadal scales- has played a unique role in environmental biology. Long term research has revealed dynamic ecosystem processes and informed management decisions across the U.S. and beyond. The Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) Network has enabled many important discoveries at individual sites. By synthesizing across multiple sites and biomes, general patterns of ecosystem functioning at regional to continental scales can be discovered. Working at these spatial and temporal scales requires additional coordination and dedication to synthesis activities. The LTER Network Office (LNO) catalyzes synthetic research, education, and engagement activities across the twenty-seven sites of the LTER Network. The LNO creates the collaborative space needed to share, challenge, and test new approaches to synthesizing and learning from LTER data and other types of long-term data. The LNO adds value to long term research by: (1) training and engaging LTER graduate students and early career scientists in synthesis, team science, and reproducible methods; (2) assisting LTER sites to become more accessible, safe and welcoming for students, staff, and investigators from all cultural and economic backgrounds; (3) facilitating the synthesis of existing long term data; and (4) maintaining robust connections with other research networks. The LNO fosters shared visioning and governance essential for maintaining collaborative relationships within the network. The LNO also works with partner organizations to ensure that ecological science continues to provide important and useful perspectives. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The LNO delivers a suite of demonstrably successful synthesis and coordination activities. The LNO enables synthesis working groups for 1-2 years; shorter-term hybrid-model synthesis groups; the network website and newsletter; and databases of site information, participants, and products. LNO activities focus on four key needs: (1) technical and interpersonal skills related to team synthesis for early career researchers, (2) identification of practices that build an inclusive, safe, and supportive culture for research, (3) new toolkits and mentoring communities as well as staff to help implement these practices across the LTER Network, and (4) connection of LTER participants with each other and with the broader environmental biology research community to promote synthesis and shared practices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050, 47.074, 47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2419138</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Halpern</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin Halpern</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[halpern@nceas.ucsb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000436702</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
<LastName>Downs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martha R Downs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[downs@nceas.ucsb.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000799078</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>SANTA BARBARA</CityName>
<ZipCode>931060001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3227 CHEADLE HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G9QBQDH39DF4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>SANTA BARBARA</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931060001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3227 CHEADLE HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>119500</Code>
<Text>LONG TERM ECOLOGICAL RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>529200</Code>
<Text>ANT Integrated System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1195</Code>
<Text>LONG TERM ECOLOGICAL RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>0100CYXXDB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~1089757</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
