<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Student Support for 2024 IEEE/ASME International Conference on Advanced Intelligent Mechatronics (AIM); Boston, Massachusetts; 15-18 July 2024]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yue Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yuewang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924588</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant provides funding to support a Student Travel Program for the 2024 IEEE/ASME International Conference on Advanced Intelligent Mechatronics (AIM) in Boston, Massachusetts, on 15-18 July 2024. The IEEE/ASME International Conference on Advanced Intelligent Mechatronics (AIM) is a flagship conference of IEEE/ASME Transactions on Mechatronics (TMECH). The AIM brings together an international community of experts to discuss the state of the art for new research results, perspectives of future developments, and innovative applications relevant to mechatronics, robotics, control, automation, and related areas. AIM 2024 will feature presentations of contributed and invited papers, recent publications on IEEE transactions of Mechatronics, tutorial sessions, as well as plenary and semi-plenary sessions and workshops. The conference provides a unique opportunity for students to interact with members of the professional community in a stimulating setting and to exchange ideas with a broad group of colleagues. The large number of workshops and tutorial sessions during the conference and the interactive format of many of the presentations will allow additional opportunity for student training and learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The AIM 2024 conference covers a broad range of topics, mirroring the varied applications of control and systems technology in intelligent mechatronic systems, from analysis and design through simulation and hardware and software implementation. Mechatronics technology has played a critical role in the development of many contemporary infrastructures affecting everyday life. Today, mechatronics engineering techniques are central in the design, operation, and security of cyber-physical systems, where they can inform users about ways to operate large networks (e.g., energy, communications, computer, traffic) and to make them robust to deliberate and accidental disturbances. The grant for the Student Travel Support Program will contribute to broadening participation and promoting inclusivity at the AIM 2024 Conference and the research society in general.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2419294</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yan</FirstName>
<LastName>Wan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yan Wan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yan.wan@uta.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000553070</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Arlington]]></Name>
<CityName>ARLINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>760199800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[701 S NEDDERMAN DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LMLUKUPJJ9N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT ARLINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Arlington]]></Name>
<CityName>ARLINGTON</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>760199800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[701 S. NEDDERMAN DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>756900</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~20000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
