<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Investigating the role of ATM1, a Class VIII myosin, in Arabidopsis root cell proliferation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1089467.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1089467</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Loretta Jackson-Hayes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lojackso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924286</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Organ formation in plants and animals relies on communication between cells. This project is focused on determining how organ size is influenced by communication between cells. This study will be carried out in the model plant Arabidopsis thaliana, which is closely related to crops such as canola and broccoli. Our experiments will be directed at roots, which are a critical plant organ for water and nutrient uptake. This research could result in agricultural advances based on tractable strategies to inform root growth. A key societal outcome of this project is broadening participation in STEM (science, technology, engineering, and mathematics) research. This project will provide hands-on research experiences for 400 high school students from diverse backgrounds via annual Science Bound Saturday workshops and 60 students via a 5-day summer short course at Iowa State University. These events will support the recruitment of underserved students to undergraduate STEM fields to improve equity and representation in STEM research. In addition, this research will be carried out by undergraduate students, two postdoctoral scholars, and one staff scientist using a mentored framework that sustains participation in cross-cutting research and strengthens partnerships between academia and non-profit research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Organ formation in multicellular organisms requires cellular communication and cell proliferation. An outstanding question in developmental biology is how cell proliferation is regulated in response to multiple growth cues, such as sugars and hormones. This project will identify the cellular basis of cell proliferation using the model plant Arabidopsis thaliana, which extensively relies on post-embryonic development for de-novo organogenesis. While it is known that in Arabidopsis roots the hormone auxin and sucrose play central roles in cell proliferation, the downstream cellular conduits of these growth cues are not well understood. This project will test the hypothesis that Arabidopsis thaliana myosin 1 (ATM1) influences sugar-driven cell proliferation in roots via an integrated and collaborative research plan. Objective 1 will focus on isolating ATM1-binding proteins to identify potential mechanisms for regulating cell division and intercellular trafficking. Objective 2 will measure cytoskeletal dynamics in roots without ATM1 to elucidate the relationship with cell cycle and cell division processes. Objective 3 will identify the function of ATM1 related to plasmodesmata to understand how intercellular trafficking influences cell division. These objectives will be achieved using interdisciplinary and complimentary approaches, including genetic, molecular, microscopic, and biochemical techniques. The experimental findings will be shared via preprints, publications, and via public datasets. The long-term goal of this work is to inform future strategies for organogenesis and plant resilience to nutrient stress.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2419621</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Burch-Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tessa M Burch-Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tburch-smith@danforthcenter.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000618625</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Walley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin W Walley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jwalley@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000719954</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dior</FirstName>
<LastName>Kelley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dior R Kelley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dkelley@iastate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000727486</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112103</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1350 BEARDSHEAR HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[515 MORRILL ROAD]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DQDBM7FGJPC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>DQDBM7FGJPC5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1350 BEARDSHEAR HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>111400</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>727500</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~1089467</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
