<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Travel Support for IWOTA 2024]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25600.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wing Suet Li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>winli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924630</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will cover travel for sixteen U.S.-based early-career mathematicians to attend the International Workshop in Operator Theory and Applications (IWOTA), to be held at the University of Kent in Canterbury, United Kingdom, during August 12 - 16, 2024. The conference is not only the largest operator theory in the world, but it is also considered the premier event that connects operator theory to other disciplines that employ operator theoretic techniques and related mathematical results. IWOTA 2024 will be devoted to all aspects of operator theory and its applications and will feature top researchers from all around the world. Having such a major event organized in Canterbury will also provide a unique opportunity to reinforce research ties between some of the best experts in the field in the United States and the United Kingdom.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many problems in physics, mathematics, and engineering can be best described by representing complex physical entities as large arrays of numbers and mathematical symbols called matrices. Matrices help us visualize how linear transformations act on vector spaces; determining their structure reveals important properties of the transformations. Hilbert space operators are infinite-dimensional generalizations of matrices. The generalization of a vector is often a function, so operators are frequently modeled as multiplications on spaces of functions. IWOTA 2024 will consist of ten plenary speakers, eleven semi-plenary speakers, and several special sessions. The topics of the special sessions include harmonic analysis and related areas, orthogonal polynomials and special functions, Jordan algebra structures, differential operators and mathematical physics, multivariable operator theory, hypercomplex analysis, free analysis and convexity, quantum information, noncommutative geometry and operator spaces, random matrices and free probability, finite and infinite dimensional moment problems, Herglotz functions and composite materials, linear algebra and control theory, systems theory/control theory, numerical ranges, spectral problems and computation, positive operators and their dynamics, operator semigroups and evolution equations, fractional calculus operators, operators on Banach spaces and lattices, operator theory on analytic function spaces, special matrices, and operator theory and applications. The conference website is https://blogs.kent.ac.uk/iwota2024/.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420818</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raul</FirstName>
<LastName>Curto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raul E Curto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[raul-curto@uiowa.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000182506</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>522421316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[105 JESSUP HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z1H9VJS8NG16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE UNIVERSITY OF IOWA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>522421316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[105 JESSUP HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>128100</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~25600</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
