<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[CSR: Small: Agile, Fine-Grained, General Function Serving for Dynamic Real-Time Deployment]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel Andresen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dandrese@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922177</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to develop software systems for robust and efficient support of interactive Artificial Intelligence-enabled services. An increasing number of applications rely on pre-trained Machine Learning models for their operation, such as computer vision tasks, natural language processing, and recommendation systems. Cyber-physical systems (e.g., autonomous navigation) also operate in a tight control loop of sensing the environment, perception, and performing corresponding actions.These applications collectively can be characterized by requiring Machine Learning models to be both accurate and able to respond within strict deadlines. Such responsiveness is mission-critical, as a late response can bear undesirable consequences, no matter how accurate. And yet, these applications are deployed in increasingly heterogeneous and unpredictable environments. This project’s novelties lie in building software frameworks that are able to navigate this accuracy/responsiveness tradeoff space automatically with high efficiency in real time. Its broader significance and importance lies in enabling robust AI-powered applications to withstand unpredictable deployment conditions in domains spanning healthcare, cyber-physical systems, online recommendation systems, and AI-assisted search and rescue operations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To address these challenges, this project develops agile mechanisms and policies for serving a family of models instead of a fixed model for a single prediction task. Its ability to activate different models near-instantaneously in-situ enables operating across heterogeneous devices without retraining the neural network for the served model. This saves on training cost – amortized over multiple heterogeneous devices and per-device dynamic deployment conditions (e.g., latency budget variation, processor frequency scaling, battery level, etc.) These unpredictable sources of variability are supported by the novel combination of this project’s mechanism and policy that schedules a stream of ML prediction tasks. The project generalizes inference serving, decoupling ML serving mechanisms from the policies that control query scheduling decisions. This project aims to produce system software artifacts that will be open sourced for the general public. Research outcomes from this project will be incorporated in several courses at both graduate and undergraduate level, collectively attracting more than 165 students annually. This is in addition to the prompt dissemination of research outcomes to the public through conference proceedings, seminar talks, and invited keynotes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420977</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexey</FirstName>
<LastName>Tumanov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexey Tumanov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[atumanov@gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000811119</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Tech Research Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303186395</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[926 DALNEY ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320315</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>735400</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~600000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
