<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[HSI Pilot Project: Improving Student Success through Agile Project Management Teaching and Learning]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonja Montas-Hunter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smontash@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927404</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With support from the Improving Undergraduate STEM Education: Hispanic-Serving Institutions (HSI Program), this Track 1 Pilot Project aims to improve Hispanic and underrepresented student success through Agile project management teaching and learning. At Georgia Gwinnett College (GGC), Information Technology (ITEC) Department is the department with the largest student population and shifts towards a more ethnically diverse student body. As the percentage of Hispanic, black/African American, and first-generation students increases significantly, so does the need to address the gaps in their retention and graduation rates, which are much lower than those of white and Asian students. Hispanic and other underrepresented students encounter various obstacles that hinder their full engagement in technology learning opportunities, such as language, social, and structural barriers. To overcome these barriers, the project proposes to integrate the teaching and learning of Agile project management in the ITEC courses to improve the academic outcomes and career readiness of ITEC students, especially those from Hispanic and underrepresented groups. Agile not only has been successfully applied in industry projects, but also has been adapted to manage class projects and life projects. Applying Agile will help students to become more productive, organized, and satisfied. The expected outcomes of the project are increased student knowledge on Agile, increased student academic success, and improved student career preparation for Agile project management.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific aims of the project are to improve teaching and learning in Agile project management to enhance success for students, including Hispanic and underrepresented students, and to provide mentoring and career development opportunities. The project includes the development of inclusive Agile project management teaching materials and assisting faculty in creating Agile integrated course projects to enhance Agile learning, so that students can improve their academic performance and better balance their life, study, and work. The project will also include mentoring activities for participating students, partnering with student organizations to host workshops and competitions on project management and provide opportunities for students to participate in Agile projects in industry. These activities will help students to learn the skills of a project manager in real life, build relationships with project managers in industry, and encourage them to pursue a career as a project manager, which may increase the diversity of this field. The project objectives include increased enrollment, retention, and graduation rates, developing a skilled workforce, and promoting equity in Information Technology fields. The project team will conduct research on determining and evaluating which Agile project management teaching methods and project procedures are most suitable for the unique needs of the low-income, first generation, minority, and underrepresented students. The research findings and project results will be published and shared with the STEM education community to improve the education outcomes and success of Hispanic and underrepresented students. The HSI Program aims to enhance undergraduate STEM education and build capacity at HSIs. Projects supported by the HSI Program will also generate new knowledge on how to achieve these aims.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420312</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrian</FirstName>
<LastName>Heinz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrian Heinz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aheinz@ggc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000556692</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shuhua</FirstName>
<LastName>Lai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shuhua Lai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[slai@ggc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000624573</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shuting</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shuting Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sxu@ggc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000679252</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hyesung</FirstName>
<LastName>Park</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hyesung Park</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[hpark7@ggc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000853609</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Gwinnett College]]></Name>
<CityName>LAWRENCEVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>300437409</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6783610291</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 UNIVERSITY CENTER LN]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JERJUDKCYLE3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA GWINNETT COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>D7C9V83N2MR5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Gwinnett College]]></Name>
<CityName>LAWRENCEVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>300437409</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 UNIVERSITY CENTER LN]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>077Y00</Code>
<Text>HSI-Hispanic Serving Instituti</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~200000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
