<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[IRES: Fostering Ocean Renewable Energy Expertise through International Collaborations with European Countries]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>448041.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>448041</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kristin Kuyuk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kkuyuk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924904</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The White House's Ocean Policy Committee developed the Ocean Climate Action Plan in March 2023, prioritizing using the ocean’s power to mitigate climate change, including ocean waves and offshore wind energy. To take advantage of the leading research and facilities in European countries and better train the next generation of the workforce in the fields of offshore wind energy and ocean wave energy in the United States, this project annually selects a cohort of eight U.S. undergraduate and graduate students to engage in immersive research experiences at leading European institutions known for their advancements in ocean renewable energy. Through this international collaboration, students gain valuable skills, knowledge and connections, preparing them to become future leaders in sustainable energy technologies. In addition, this project also emphasizes diversity and inclusion, involving students from varied backgrounds and underrepresented groups, thus contributing to a more diverse and globally competitive STEM workforce. The project resonates across educational, economic, environmental, and societal domains, promoting diversity and inclusion within STEM fields, advancing technical knowledge in renewable energy, and preparing a new generation of scientists and engineers with global perspectives on sustainability challenges and opportunities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research focuses on innovative solutions for ocean renewable energy, addressing critical areas such as control of wave energy converters, optimization of offshore wind platforms, offshore wind turbine reliability analysis, and mooring systems for marine energy devices. Students are sent to renowned European institutions including Maynooth University in Ireland, the University of Plymouth in the U.K., the Norwegian University of Science and Technology in Norway, and the Technical University of Denmark in Denmark.  In this project, students work alongside renowned European experts, engaging in projects that involve advanced yet important topics such as control algorithm design, system optimization, reliability analysis, and structural analysis. By integrating academic research and cross-cultural experiences, this project aims to push the boundaries of current renewable energy technologies, stimulate creativity, and contribute to the global transition towards sustainable energy systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420175</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lei</FirstName>
<LastName>Zuo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lei Zuo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[leizuo@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000526519</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaofan</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaofan Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lxiaofan@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000952785</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GNJ7BBP73WE9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>ANN ARBOR</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091079</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1109 GEDDES AVE, SUITE 3300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>288Y00</Code>
<Text>Intl Rsrch Exp for Stds (IRES)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5914</Code>
<Text>WESTERN EUROPE, OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5946</Code>
<Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~448041</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
