<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel Grant: 2024 Image Science Gordon Research Conference and Gordon Research Seminar]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique Dagenais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddagenai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922980</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposal requests support for early-career investigators across all possible diversity to participate in the Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Image Science following a four-year gap imposed by the pandemic from 2018-2022.  The support to a diverse pool of early-career investigators will ensure long-term sustainability towards building a strong image science community. &lt;br/&gt;        The June 9-14, 2024, GRC conference theme is “Advances in Imaging and Visualization at the Junction of Physics, Engineering, and Data Science.” which is focused on the appropriate acquisition and efficient uses of the massive volume of imaging information now collected in many fields of imaging. We aim to build Image Science as an independent field of study via detailed interdisciplinary discussions and by fostering the success of a new generation of image scientists.  &lt;br/&gt;       The unique feature of this conference compared with more conventional imaging venues is the bringing together of renowned speakers from disparate application areas, including astronomy, biology, medicine, remote sensing, quantum imaging, optics and photonics displays, and security and defense industries, in a forum that encourages each to describe their most significant challenges and most promising solutions, to foster cross-fertilization between these fields. &lt;br/&gt;       We value and strive to increase the percentage of women and other underrepresented minorities in the sciences, including LBGTQ+ people, in building a strong, diverse, equitable and inclusive image science community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A technical description of the project:&lt;br/&gt;The proposal requests support for early-career investigators across all possible diversity to participate in the Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Image Science following a four-year gap imposed by the pandemic from 2018-2022.  The support to a diverse pool of early-career investigators will ensure long-term sustainability towards building a strong image science community. &lt;br/&gt;        Intellectual Merit: Imaging systems will usher in the next generation of innovations across a wide range of applications from nanoscale to macro scale. The June 9-14, 2024, GRC conference theme is “Advances in Imaging and Visualization at the Junction of Physics, Engineering, and Data Science.” which is focused on the appropriate acquisition and efficient uses of the massive volume of imaging information now collected in many fields of imaging. Speakers give ~40-minute presentations in a single-track format with ~20 minutes of discussions following each presentation that experts lead in the field. At the center of each presentation is a discussion of the core challenges shared by image scientists and novel techniques for acquiring and displaying information to maximize decision performance. We aim to build Image Science as an independent field of study via detailed interdisciplinary discussions and by fostering the success of a new generation of image scientists. The unique feature of this conference compared with more conventional imaging venues is the bringing together of renowned speakers from disparate application areas, including astronomy, biology, medicine, remote sensing, quantum imaging, optics and photonics displays, and security and defense industries, in a forum that encourages each to describe their most significant challenges and most promising solutions, to foster cross-fertilization between these fields. All speakers are invited based on their field leadership and willingness to debate fundamental issues shared by everyone developing, evaluating, and applying imaging across disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;         Broader Impact: The GRC format in a small remote venue promotes innovative interdisciplinary thinking that leads to breakthroughs. An environment where leading senior scientists debate core issues is valuable to young investigators trying to build prosperous independent careers in imaging in industry and academia. All attendees are invited to present a poster describing their research in poster sessions, a key element of the Gordon Conference format. Dedicated two-hour time slots are planned daily for all participants and presenter to gather around the posters and discuss the work presented. The 2024 Image Science GRC is committed to developing a diverse program and inclusive conference atmosphere through a discussion-focused program, fundraising efforts focused on supporting historically underrepresented participants, and a concerted effort to attract and accept a variety of applicants from diverse backgrounds and institutions. We strive to increase the percentage of women and other underrepresented minorities in STEM. We will host a GRC Power Hour designed to address diversity and inclusion in the scientific workplace by providing a safe environment for informal and meaningful conversations amongst colleagues of all career stages. The program supports the professional growth of all members of our communities by providing an open forum for discussion and mentoring. We have two co-hosts for our Power Hour, an African-American woman and another mid-career scientist woman - both were speakers at our 2022 GRC image science. The plan for the Power Hour is for the hosts to share statistics on diversity (women and minorities) progress in STEM and share remaining challenges. We will form small groups to discuss different issues and share back with the group. Based on the 2022 survey, we plan to acknowledge the underrepresentation of LBGTQ+ people in the sciences and open discussion on how we may evolve as a community to make everyone feel included and supported. The Image Science GRC is complemented by the student-run Image Science Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) on June 7-8, 2024.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420094</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jannick</FirstName>
<LastName>Rolland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jannick P Rolland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rolland@optics.rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000112695</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>151700</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~10000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
