<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel: NSF Student Travel Grant for 2024 IEEE International Symposium on Dynamic Spectrum Access Networks (IEEE DySPAN)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Lyles</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jlyles@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922087</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This student travel grant will support students to attend the 2024 IEEE Dynamic Spectrum Access Networks (DySPAN) conference in Washington, DC, on May 13–16, 2024. DySPAN is a premier conference focused on dynamic spectrum access networks and advanced wireless research, a priority area for NSF and a national interest highlighted by the CHIPS and Science Act of 2022. The conference brings together researchers, engineers, policymakers, and industry professionals to discuss the latest developments, challenges, and innovations in dynamic spectrum access and related areas. Attending a conference in Washington, DC, may place a significant financial burden on prospective student attendees, particularly those with limited resources or not supported through existing Federal research grants. With financial assistance, students may bear the costs of attending the conference and, as such, avail invaluable opportunities for learning, networking, and career advancement. This NSF student travel grant will play a pivotal role in addressing these challenges by providing essential financial support to offset the costs for students, ensuring that the benefits of attending the conference are accessible to a broader audience from diverse backgrounds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This student travel grant will support up to 12 full-time students from U.S. universities who are first-time attendees to DySPAN, regardless of their citizenship and visa status. Each student will receive up to $1,250.00 for covering or offsetting their travel expenses to attend DySPAN. The students will be able to use their travel grants for different travel expenses, e.g., ground or air transportation, conference registration fees, lodging, and meals. In accordance with the Fly America Act, we will inform student applicants that any flights purchased using the funds from this travel grant must either be (i) on a U.S.-based carrier or (ii) ticketed through a U.S. carrier, e.g., codeshare flights on international airlines. The student travel grant announcement will encourage participation from underrepresented minorities in higher education, e.g., women, LatinX, African Americans, and Native Americans, as well as students from disadvantaged backgrounds. We will prioritize students who have accepted posters, papers, demos, or workshops at the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049, 47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420834</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joao</FirstName>
<LastName>Santos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joao Santos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[joaosantos@vt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000862499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240603359</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 TURNER ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QDE5UHE5XD16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE &amp; STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>M515A1DKXAN8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240603359</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 TURNER ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>151Y00</Code>
<Text>SII-Spectrum Innovation Initia</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>736300</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7976</Code>
<Text>EARS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~15000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
