<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[IRES: Collaborative Research to Yield Stimulating Transnational Activities in Lattice Dynamics (CRYSTAL Dynamics)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>448967.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>448967</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maija Kukla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkukla@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924940</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Collaborative Research to Yield Stimulating Transnational Activities in Lattice Dynamics (CRYSTAL Dynamics) project, led by the University of Rochester, will provide students with invaluable international experiences while performing cutting-edge research in materials chemistry. In this IRES program, undergraduate and graduate students will have the opportunity to travel to prestigious Italian institutions, including the University of Turin and the University of Modena and Reggio Emilia, to undertake interdisciplinary research on advanced materials with important technological applications, from drug development to molecular semiconductors. This initiative is crucial for developing the next generation of scientists who are globally aware and culturally fluent, addressing the national need for a diverse and well-prepared STEM workforce that has experience working on an international and interdisciplinary research team. The project prioritizes recruiting students with no previous international experience, students from primarily undergraduate institutions, and those from underrepresented communities, and provides them with unique opportunities to perform world-class research while building an extensive international collaborative network, thus enhancing their educational experiences and future career prospects. By promoting the progress of science and fostering an inclusive educational environment, this program aligns with national priorities related to STEM education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CRYSTAL Dynamics focuses on the study of lattice dynamics to generate a comprehensive understanding of the relationship between atomic structure, lattice dynamics, and bulk material properties. The project is structured around three main research thrusts: understanding forces related to solid-state phase transformations, creating dynamic molecular crystals using green chemistry methods, and utilizing quantum mechanical simulations to inform experimental work. Students will form two cohorts, one experimental and one theoretical, and will engage in interdisciplinary research projects, such as synthesizing and characterizing dynamic crystals and developing computational tools for predicting material behaviors. The collaborative effort involves internationally-recognized researchers from the University of Rochester, the University of Turin, and the University of Modena and Reggio Emilia, and provides students with access to advanced research facilities and mentorship from leading scientists who have deep international experience. This research aims to uncover the fundamental forces that underpin bulk material phenomena, with applications in materials chemistry, semiconductor engineering, and the pharmaceutical industry. The program will also enhance the practical skills, cultural fluency, and professional development of the students, contributing to the broader goal of preparing a diverse, globally-competent STEM workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420126</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Ruggiero</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael T Ruggiero</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[michael.ruggiero@rochester.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000787801</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Rochester]]></Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>146113847</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5852754031</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[910 GENESEE ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F27KDXZMF9Y8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ROCHESTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Rochester]]></Name>
<CityName>ROCHESTER</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146113847</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[910 GENESEE ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>288Y00</Code>
<Text>Intl Rsrch Exp for Stds (IRES)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5920</Code>
<Text>ITALY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~448967</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
