<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel: NSF Student Travel Grant for 2024 IEEE International Conference on Computational Photography (ICCP)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924768</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports student participation across all levels (undergraduate, master’s, doctoral) from US-based institutions in the IEEE International Conference on Computational Photography (ICCP) 2024, to be held as an in-person event between July 22-24, 2024, at the Ecole Polytechnique federal de Lausanne, in Lausanne, Switzerland. ICCP is the premier annual conference dedicated to computational photography (now in its sixteenth iteration) and supports a research community across optics, image/signal processing, computer vision and graphics, and sensors/electronics. The ICCP 2024 program includes keynote and invited talks, paper presentations, poster and demo sessions, and networking events. This program creates rich opportunities for cross-pollination of ideas across research and application areas and provides both junior and senior researchers with an environment where they can engage in brainstorming and mentoring discourse.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award facilitates participation from a diverse group of students in ICCP 2024 including: underrepresented students; students from research labs that traditionally do not attend ICCP but work on closely related problems; and students that would not otherwise have the resources to attend. The award provides travel grants for 10 selected US-based students. Applications are solicited broadly across the US, and recipients of the travel grants are selected by a committee formed by the ICCP 2024 organizing team. Each travel grant partially covers travel and lodging costs and includes a conference registration waiver. Recipient students are invited to attend all aspects all elements of the ICCP 2024 program (paper presentations, keynote talks, invited talks, poster and demo sessions, reception, breaks and networking events); present their research work as a poster at the ICCP 2024 poster sessions; and participate in a mentoring session with faculty and industry professionals providing research and career development advice. This will support their career development and increase diversity and student participation in ICCP 2024, and the broader computational photography community. This will also help increase the number of active researchers and educators for STEM fields, advance the research goals for computational photography, and have downstream effects of accelerating the research and development of technologies with broad beneficial societal impacts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420736</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Suren</FirstName>
<LastName>Jayasuriya</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Suren Jayasuriya</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sjayasur@asu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000753682</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NTLHJXM55KZ6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852813670</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[660 S MILL AVENUE STE 204]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>749500</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~20000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
