<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[The Decline of Government R&D in Innovation: Establishing Facts and Evaluating Consequences]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>474942.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>474942</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Feeney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfeeney@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Since World War II, the U.S. federal government has been the country’s largest funder of research and development (R&amp;D), with tripartite objectives of national defense, health, and economic growth. Much attention has been given to studying large expansions of federal R&amp;D investment. Yet federally-funded R&amp;D, as a share of domestic R&amp;D or GDP, has been on decline since its twentieth century peak—an era which has also seen a major reorientation of the federal portfolio from defense to biomedicine. The consequences of these changes are not yet fully understood. A traditional economic view is that public R&amp;D fills gaps that markets leave behind. However, since the 1950s the U.S. (and global) innovation system have matured significantly, potentially leaving fewer gaps for public R&amp;D to fill. Moreover, though the impacts of past public R&amp;D investments often inspire new ones, there is less evidence on the effects of public R&amp;D drawdowns and budget cuts to inform choices when renewing funding for programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research evaluates the impacts of declining public R&amp;D and the pivot away from defense innovation. Using recently-collected long-run data on government-funded invention, paired with new data on the postwar scientific workforce, this project examines (i) the effects of federally-funded R&amp;D on the development of complex, science-based technologies (i.e., “deep tech” innovation); and (ii) the impacts of large and abrupt cuts to defense research in the 1970s (before which the Department of Defense was nearly as large a funder of basic research as NSF) on the U.S. innovation system, including science, scientists, universities, and high-tech industries. The project results improve understanding of science and technology with new evidence on the effects of government withdrawal from R&amp;D funding and produces new approaches to evaluating public-private R&amp;D spillovers and identifying regularities and tensions that inform future policy choices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420824</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Gross</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel P Gross</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[daniel.gross@duke.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000797400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>DURHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054640</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 W MAIN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TP7EK8DZV6N5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>DURHAM</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054640</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 W MAIN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y00</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~474942</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
