<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel: NSF Student Travel Grant for 2024 IEEE International Symposium on Hardware Oriented Security and Trust (HOST)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dan Cosley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcosley@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928832</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will fund travel for 60 students for the International Symposium on Hardware-Oriented Security and Trust (HOST), held in Washington, DC, May 6-9, 2024.  Trusted hardware is the foundation of cybersecurity.  The rapid proliferation of computing and communication systems with increasing computational power and connectivity into every sphere of modern life has brought security to the forefront of system design, test, and validation. The emergence of new application spaces for these systems in the internet-of-things (IoT) regime is creating new attack surfaces as well as new requirements for secure and trusted system operation. Additionally, the design, manufacturing and the distribution of microchip, printed circuit board (PCB), as well as other electronic components are becoming more sophisticated and globally distributed with a number of potential security vulnerabilities. Thus, hardware plays an increasingly important and integral role in system security with many emerging vulnerabilities and defense mechanisms relating to hardware. The HOST conference aims to facilitate the rapid growth of hardware-based security research and development. HOST highlights new results in hardware and system security. Relevant research topics include techniques, tools, design/test methods, architectures, circuits, and applications of secure hardware.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project's broader significance and importance include professional development for undergraduate and graduate students as well as continued growth of the symposium. Students' attendance enables them to learn about the latest tools, design methods, architectures, circuits, and novel applications of secure hardware.  Students will also receive ample opportunities for networking with researchers, interactions with industrial sponsors and exhibitors for internships and full-time positions, and opportunities to receive feedback on their own research.  Selection criteria include presentation at the conference, being first-time attendees, financial need, and institutional and demographic diversity, with a goal of growing the talent pool of cybersecurity researchers. The hardware security research community itself will benefit by having a broader and larger audience at the event.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420830</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fareena</FirstName>
<LastName>Saqib</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fareena Saqib</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[fsaqib@uncc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000677805</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Charlotte]]></Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9201 UNIVERSITY CITY BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>JB33DT84JNA5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHARLOTTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>N8DMK1K4C2K5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Charlotte]]></Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9201 UNIVERSITY CITY BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>806000</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~24000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
