<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Fire-Resistant Polymer Composites Using Recycled Processed African-American Hair]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>275000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader/commercial impact of this Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project is in addressing an increasing need to develop more eco-friendly, non-toxic fire-resitant materials in applications ranging from protective gears for firefighters, for industrial workers working in hot environments, and in construction materials such as tiles, wall panels, and roofing.  Creating improved fire-resistant materials for homes, buildings, and personnel will decrease costs to homeowners and insurance companies and can potentially save lives. The rise in global temperature, and the escalating frequency and severity of structural and wildfire incidents at scale, combined with need to use non-fossil fuel based materials in industry underscores this critical need. This project is likely to to introduce a brand new natural polymer - Afro hair- to develop as an additive to fire-resistant products. A successful development of this technology is also likely to create economic opportunities for a broader section of society that would participate in this novel endeavor.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Processed African-American hair possess notable characteristics such as a high nitrogen content, robust elliptic structure, and cross-linked cell membranes. When subjected to high heat levels, these cell membranes expand and create a protective barrier, hindering oxygen from reaching the substrate and thus preventing the spread of fire and heat. The processed material does not liquefy, merge, or melt and can act as insulation or a barrier, impeding or reducing fire spread. This remarkable discovery represents a significant advancement in creating lightweight, fire-resistant building materials, clothing, and reinforcing fire-resistant plastics.  Phrase I R&amp;D plan focuses on optimizing material compositions where African-American hair loading in the composite mix will adjusted through scientific experimentation for processing ease and improvement of desired properties. These compositions will be then used to develop prototype products that meet or surpass the industry performance standards set by existing fire-resistant products.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2420037</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chera</FirstName>
<LastName>Howard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chera S Howard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cherahoward39@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000836690</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FORSEE, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>PRATTVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>360661918</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3347994310</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1851 RIVERTON DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NK9VSBL32HB4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FORSEE, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FORSEE, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>PRATTVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>360661918</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1851 RIVERTON DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>537100</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090Z</Code>
<Text>CAS-Critical Aspects of Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~275000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
