<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Understanding and tailoring molecular interactions governing the formation of nanoparticle mesocrystal tiles at functionalized fluid interfaces]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Shahab Shojaei-Zadeh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sshojaei@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928045</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award aims to understand how nanoscale colloidal particles can be assembled into larger, more complex structures at fluid interfaces. This process is crucial for creating new materials with advanced properties to drive innovations in various fields such as electronics, energy, and medicine. The challenge lies in arranging these nanoparticles in a controlled and predictable manner, akin to assembling a precise and intricate mosaic. By gaining a deeper understanding of the factors that influence nanoparticle assembly, this research will provide valuable design principles for arranging particles into functional superstructures where they can interact in programmable and purposeful ways. These insights could have potential applications in areas ranging from chemical catalysis to emerging fields like quantum computing, leveraging the unique electronic properties of the particles in the assembly. This project also supports the education and training of future scientists and engineers. It engages underrepresented groups, fostering diversity in the scientific community, and includes outreach efforts to inspire young students in K-12 to explore science, technology, engineering, and mathematics fields. The outcomes of this research will contribute to the national interest by promoting scientific progress and technological innovation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project seeks to explore and control the interfacial dynamics governing the formation of discrete tiles of nanoparticle assemblies on a functionalized fluid interface. Addressing the grand challenge of organizing nanoparticles into higher-order structures with purposeful interactions, the research focuses on creating discrete, isolated nanoparticle mesocrystal tiles. The project combines experimental and computational methods to investigate and manipulate the thermodynamic and kinetic factors influencing nanoparticle assembly at fluid interfaces. The innovative approach includes decoupling complex transport and reaction processes through state-of-the-art in-situ experimental techniques and computational modeling. The goal is to achieve precise control over nanoparticle assembly, alignment, and attachment, leading to the programmable design of nanoparticle mesocrystal tiles with specific sizes, shapes, and properties. This research will fill critical gaps in understanding nanoparticle arrangement and attachment mechanisms and establish design principles for the formation of metamaterials with tailored functionalities. The project also emphasizes broader impacts, providing interdisciplinary training for students, engaging underrepresented groups, and developing educational modules to demystify nanoscale assembly for K-12 students. The project aims to disseminate findings widely through publications, presentations, and community engagement, advancing scientific knowledge and stimulating interest in nanoscience and engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2421525</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fernando</FirstName>
<LastName>Escobedo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fernando A Escobedo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[fe13@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000405638</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tobias</FirstName>
<LastName>Hanrath</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tobias Hanrath</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[th358@cornell.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000501174</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[341 PINE TREE RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G56PUALJ3KT5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>ITHACA</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148535205</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[350 Olin Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>141500</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~450000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
