<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MCA: Towards a Theory of Engineering Identity Development & Persistence of Minoritized Students with Imposter Feelings: A Longitudinal Mixed-methods Study of Developmental Networks]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>306762.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>126212</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eleanor Sayre</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>esayre@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922997</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project aims to advance the principal investigator’s research agenda on developmental relationships as mechanisms for career advancement of women and people of color. The investigator will undertake a new area of research by exploring imposter syndrome among women and minoritized students and intersectionality in STEM while also gaining  expertise in latent growth curve analysis.  The project aims to develop a theory on the relationship between minoritized students’ developmental networks and their engineering identity and disposition development.  The research includes a longitudinal data analysis, experimental research, use of Subject-Object Interview (SOI) to assess developmental stage empirically as an antecedent of developmental networks, and quantitative and qualitative examination of  Imposter Phenomenon (IP).  The study integrates the Social Cognitive Career Theory and the theoretical framework of intersectionality to theorize the value of developmental networks s a relational space that can enable minoritized students to address imposter feelings stemming from the conflict between their multiple identities through intersectional identity work. Nine propositions are offered to examine the mechanisms through which a network of developers can build capacity of minoritized students in engineering to engage in intersectional identity work needed to develop an engineering identity and persist.  The results of the project are expected to broaden the understanding of factors that increase STEM persistence among women and minoritized students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will examine three overarching research questions: (1) What individual and developmental factors determine the optimal structure and content of developmental networks needed for supporting women and students of color to develop a stable engineering identity needed to persist in engineering over time? (2) How does the structure  of one’s developmental network in terms of strength of relationships with developers similar and dissimilar to women and minoritized students in terms of race/gender and density in regard to the extent to which those developers know each other influence their likelihood of overcoming imposter feelings and develop engineering identity to persist in engineering over time? (3)How does the content of one’s developmental network in terms of culturally relevant mentoring support received from developers from multiple social spheres influence their likelihood of overcoming imposter feelings and develop engineering identity to persist in engineering over time? Quantitative and qualitative data will be collected from minoritized engineering students who will participate in surveys, workshops, and exercises and analyzed using correlational analysis, means, standard deviations, reliability analysis of scale, demographic instruments, latent growth curve modeling, and structural equation modeling. The study will develop theory about developmental networks that can guide interventions designed to increase STEM persistence of women and minorities in engineering. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is funded by the Mid-Career Advancement program that offers opportunities for scientists and engineers to substantively enhance and advance their research program through synergistic and mutually beneficial partnerships.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2421846</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rajashi</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghosh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rajashi Ghosh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rajashi.ghosh@drexel.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000588752</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/09/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Teachers College, Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276605</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126783000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[525 W 120TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DBM1C8MDJ5L3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEACHERS COLLEGE COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Teachers College, Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276605</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[525 W 120TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>162Y00</Code>
<Text>ECR:BCSER Capcity STEM Ed Rscr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>101Z</Code>
<Text>MCA-Mid-Career Advancement</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8055</Code>
<Text>Capacity-Building Projects</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002122DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF Education & Human Resource]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2021~126212</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
