<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Translation potential of a mosquito larvicide that uses encapsulated essential oils in yeast]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this I-Corps project is the development of an insecticide to control mosquitoes that works by killing mosquito larvae before they can grow into adults. Current mosquito populations are building resistance to commonly used pesticides, which may increase the spread of pathogens carried by mosquitos that cause diseases such as dengue, Zika, and chikungunya. This technology provides an alternative that targets mosquito larvae using a formulation that allows for precise application, minimizing environmental impact and avoiding harm to non-target organisms.  In addition, the product is biodegradable and may meet the need for safer and more efficient mosquito control. The goal is to help combat mosquito-borne diseases while providing a sustainable alternative to conventional chemical mosquito control.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translation potential of a mosquito control technology that uses the natural properties of essential oils to create a safer and more effective mosquito larvicide. The challenge with existing larvicides is that they often harm the environment and are becoming less effective as mosquitoes develop resistance. This solution involves encapsulating essential oils in yeast cells, which are a favorite food of mosquito larvae. Encapsulating essential oils into yeast protects the oils from breaking down and reduces the risk of harming other wildlife. This product has been tested successfully in both laboratory and field trials, as well as against mosquito larvae that have developed resistance to traditional larvicides. The product is non-toxic to humans and other mammals at the doses used, and is made from food-grade materials, which may enhance public acceptance. In addition, this larvicide may play a key role in reducing mosquito populations and the diseases they spread, offering a more sustainable and environmentally friendly solution for public health.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2421923</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivy</FirstName>
<LastName>Hurwitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ivy Hurwitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ihurwitz@salud.unm.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000996413</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center]]></Name>
<CityName>ALBUQUERQUE</CityName>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052726264</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[SPONSORED PROJECTS OFFICE]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>G389MFAYJNG9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[MSC10 5550]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
