<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[HSI Implementation and Evaluation Project: STEM Student Empowerment through Mentorship, Family-Centric Innovation Activities, and Artificial Intelligence Research]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499865.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499865</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonja Montas-Hunter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smontash@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927404</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the support from the Improving Undergraduate STEM Education: Hispanic-Serving Institutions (HSI) Program, this IUSE-HSI Track 2 Implementation and Evaluation project aims to enhance successful experiences and graduation of first-generation students, including Hispanic and female students majoring in math, computer science, and engineering. Having access to higher education is crucial to promoting economic mobility and social integration and is particularly important as it addresses the significant underrepresentation of certain groups in STEM fields, which has a profound impact on innovation. This project addresses this challenge by providing a combination of student support, mentorship programs, and engaging family-oriented activities to promote community engagement and foster a culture of inclusivity and excellence in STEM education. By integrating AI research opportunities and emphasizing STEM ideas relevant to the local community, the project will prepare students for careers in technology and innovation. Ultimately, this project aims to create a more equitable and diverse STEM landscape, empowering students to succeed and thrive in their academic and professional journeys.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will be guided by three project objectives: 1) Provide student support and mentorship to first-generation students, including Hispanic and female students to facilitate and increase the 4-year graduation rate from STEM degree programs. 2) Organize family-centric initiatives that bridge education, research, and community to empower successful STEM students, shaping the future of STEM disciplines. 3)Increase the engagement of students in AI research through multidisciplinary research and applications relevant to the local community. The research methods involve mentorship programs that connect students with role models and peers, offering guidance and networking opportunities. Family-oriented activities will engage students' support systems to cultivate an inclusive environment. Additionally, AI research opportunities will provide students with hands-on experience, enabling them to acquire valuable skills relevant to STEM careers. Expected results include improved access and inclusion within the College of Engineering, increased graduation rates and a replicable framework for effective recruitment and support strategies. The ultimate goal is to use this data to inform sustainable efforts that move beyond the proof-of-concept stage, resulting in long-term positive outcomes aligned with the goals of the HSI program. By sharing effective and proven strategies, the project will offer a scalable model that can be adapted to address disparities and support broadening participation in STEM. The HSI Program aims to enhance undergraduate STEM education and build capacity at HSIs. Projects supported by the HSI Program will also generate new knowledge on how to achieve these aims.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2421155</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Audrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Meador</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Audrey Meador</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ameador@wtamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000729109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vinitha Hannah</FirstName>
<LastName>Subburaj</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vinitha Hannah Subburaj</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[vsubburaj@wtamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000776448</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Behnam</FirstName>
<LastName>Askarian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Behnam Askarian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[baskarian@wtamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000877863</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fatemehsadat</FirstName>
<LastName>Tabei</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fatemehsadat Tabei</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ftabei@wtamu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000989264</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[West Texas A&M University]]></Name>
<CityName>CANYON</CityName>
<ZipCode>790160001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8066512732</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2501 4TH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TRMGFQWVM1N8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WEST TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>ZM3QVJ8ACN11</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[WEST TEXAS A & M UNIVERSITY]]></Name>
<CityName>CANYON</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>790160001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2501 4TH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>077Y00</Code>
<Text>HSI-Hispanic Serving Instituti</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~499865</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
