<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Bioanalytical Sensors Gordon Research Conference and Seminar]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aleksandr Simonian</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimonia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Sensors play many roles in our lives from including in diagnostics for diseases and providing real-time information on our health status through smart watches. The 2024 Bioanalytical Sensors Gordon Research Conference and Gordon Research Seminar will bring together the world’s experts and early career researchers in sensors with a focus on addressing grand challenges in health monitoring and diagnostics. This conference will create an environment that promotes interactions between and learning across a diverse and global group of scientists, students, and practitioners at various stages in their careers, and lay the groundwork for advances that can impact public health on a global scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Sensors designed for analytical performance and usability can turn the tide of pandemics, bridge gaps in healthcare disparities, and provide insight into key biological processes. Because of the prominent roles sensors play in our lives and their potential for even further integration and future growth led by emerging applications, establishing a diverse and global community of experts to discuss outstanding challenges and the possible approaches for solving them is a key need with relevance to biomedical research, health, food security, forensics, and other disciplines with public benefit. The 2024 Bioanalytical Sensors Gordon Research Conference and Research Seminar seeks to fulfill this need in an intimate, inclusive, and scholarly setting. The audience for this conference is interdisciplinary, as solutions that ultimately impact the general public require collaboration across basic and applied sciences. Research inclusive of chemistry and physics, microbiology and immunology, biomedical and electrical engineering, human factors research, and global health will be represented at the 2024 Bioanalytical Sensors conference. Participants from industry, entrepreneurs, clinicians, and professional practitioners are integral parts of efforts to innovate and translate sensing and diagnostic technologies. The conference will highlight cutting edge topics that include point-of-care diagnostics, wearable sensors, advances in microfluidics, and remote sensing. The overall program is additionally diverse with respect to career stage, gender, ethnicity, and country of origin. Invited participants (speakers, discussion leaders, Power Hour leaders, Chairs, and Vice-Chairs) include late, mid, and early-career investigators who will all share a forum to discuss challenges, opportunities, and future applications of sensing on health and our understanding of the natural world.  The conference will foster a stimulating atmosphere for objective and detailed critiques of unpublished results describing cutting edge biosensing technologies. Interactions between attendees will catalyze collaborations leading to future advances in sensing that will be disseminated broadly in the literature and also tangible, real-world solutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2421053</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Mace</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles R Mace</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Charles.Mace@tufts.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000643991</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>723600</Code>
<Text>BioP-Biophotonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>790900</Code>
<Text>BIOSENS-Biosensing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>108E</Code>
<Text>Bioelectronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1639</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8028</Code>
<Text>Sensor Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~24999</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
