<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: The 9th International Clumped Isotope Workshop (ICIW) at Stony Brook University]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49550.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49550</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Margaret Fraiser</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfraiser@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924660</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides participant support for the 9th International Clumped Isotope Workshop (ICIW), to be held at Stony Brook University, in Stony Brook, New York from August 25th-28th, 2024. The ICIW is a gathering of stable isotope geochemists connected by a shared interest in the study of clumped isotope geochemistry and other rare stable isotopes. The ICIW will be a forum for discussing consistency and quality of methods between laboratories, calibration using created and natural samples, and new scientific applications. As a smaller meeting than larger, society-organized conferences, the ICIW is held every 1-2 years and alternates between academic host institutions in North America and Eurasia. Participants range from undergraduate students to senior faculty. Research presentations given during the meeting will be a mix of conference-style talks and open format poster sessions focused on work led by graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, and other early career scientists. The 9th ICIW will closely follow the Goldschmidt Conference, organized by the Geochemical Society, to broaden both domestic and international participation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 9th ICIW will consist of two and half days of technical sessions, with mornings and early afternoons reserved for thematically organized conference-style oral presentation sessions, and one afternoon poster session. A local and northeastern United States regional organizing committee, a majority of whom are early career faculty, are organizing the meeting logistics and designing the scientific programming. Topics to be covered include advances in analytical techniques, clumped isotopes of organic molecules and natural gases, paleoenvironmental reconstruction, diagenesis, and the extension of lessons learned from the clumped isotope community to other, rare isotope research communities (e.g., triple oxygen isotopes). This award will be used to cover conference costs for students and early career researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2421880</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Henkes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory A Henkes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gregory.henkes@stonybrook.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000735304</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL L]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>M746VC6XMNH9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>STONY BROOK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[W5510 FRANKS MELVILLE MEMORIAL LIBRARY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>729500</Code>
<Text>Geobiology &amp; Low-Temp Geochem</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>745900</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>GEOBIOLOGY &amp; LOW TEMP GEOCHEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>SEDIMENTARY GEO &amp; PALEOBIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~49550</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
