<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel Support for International Conference on Molecular Vapor Phase Epitaxy (ICMOVPE XXI)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Lane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>plane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922453</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The International Conference on Metal Organic Vapor Phase Epitaxy (ICMOVPE XXI) is an important venue for the presentation of the latest advances in materials and device technologies. The commercial application of MOVPE continues to expand world-wide and it is critically important that the USA has trained engineers working in this field to provide for the US-based economic expansion. The participation of young scientists and engineers will contribute to the dissemination of new knowledge and generate an important source of new technical human resources trained in this critically important materials manufacturing technology. Supporting stronger interactions of these new research scientists and engineers will advance their careers and support the generation of new technological advances. NSF support will help to create a strong and active cadre of new talent in the USA which can contribute strongly to the future of the research and development of advanced semiconductor production and manufacturing in our country. This talent is critically needed if the USA is to maintain its leadership in advanced semiconductor technology and technical talent development is an important component of the USA’s CHIPS and Science Act.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 21st International Conference on Metal Organic Vapor Phase Epitaxy (ICMOVPE XXI) will present the latest advances in science, technology and applications of MOVPE and related growth techniques. This is the pre-eminent Conference in the field and the papers presented represent the leading-edge research done worldwide. The goal of the conference is to create a vibrant and stimulating atmosphere for furthering new and impactful research on MOVPE and related growth techniques. The speakers and discussion leaders are drawn from a wide range of fields and include experimentalists and theoreticians practicing in materials science and engineering research. Topics that will be covered include fundamental studies and modeling of epitaxial processes; Group IV, III-V, and II-VI semiconductors and devices; semiconducting oxides and epitaxial dielectrics; 2D materials and van der Waals heterostructures; heteroepitaxy of mismatched alloys and III-Vs on silicon; low-dimensional structures. This year’s Conference will feature a combination of invited and contributed talks, poster sessions and an industrial exhibit.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Due to the importance and cross-cutting nature of this conference, it is being supported by the Electronic and Photonic Materials program in the Division of Materials Research in the Directorate for Mathematical and Physical Sciences; the Electronics, Photonics, and Magnetic Devices program in the Division of Electrical, Communications, and Cyber Systems in the Directorate for Engineering; and the Advanced Manufacturing program in the Division of Civil, Mechanical and Manufacturing Innovation (CMMI) in the Directorate for Engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2422258</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Russell</FirstName>
<LastName>Dupuis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Russell D Dupuis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dupuis@gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000309667</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mallory</FirstName>
<LastName>Starr</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mallory R Starr</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[starr@mrs.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000919583</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Materials Research Society]]></Name>
<CityName>WARRENDALE</CityName>
<ZipCode>150867537</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 KEYSTONE DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MFPJGRD1NWE3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MATERIALS RESEARCH SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Materials Research Society]]></Name>
<CityName>WARRENDALE</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>150867537</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 KEYSTONE DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>177500</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>106Z</Code>
<Text>Microelectronics and Semiconductors</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8615</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Devices and Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~12000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
