<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Society Prioritizes Our Recruitment of Every Scholar (SPORES): A mentoring program with the goal of diversifying, advancing, and promoting future mycologists.]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>46553.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>46553</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aardra Kachroo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>akachroo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Society Prioritizes Our Recruitment of Every Scholar (SPORES) workshop, hosted by the Mycological Society of America (MSA), is dedicated to diversifying the field of mycology and advancing future mycologists. Mycology, the study of fungi, is crucial for understanding the biology of these organisms with complex interactions within ecosystems, including nutrient cycling and symbiotic relationships with plants. Fungi also play a vital role in medicine, agriculture, and biotechnology, with applications ranging from antibiotic production to bioremediation. Diversity in scientific communities is essential for fostering innovation and creativity in STEM fields. Despite previous efforts by MSA, there is still a significant gap in representation, particularly among underrepresented groups. In 2024, SPORES will expand its program at the MSA Annual Meeting, offering a platform for underrepresented undergraduate students to support their career growth by meaningfully introducing them to the scientific community. Through welcoming students, providing spaces for interaction and questions with experienced mentors, engaging in direct mentoring, and creating a community of budding scientists, SPORES will empower underrepresented undergraduate students attending the MSA conference for the first time. By promoting diversity and inclusion in mycology, SPORES is shaping the future of the field and ensuring that all voices are heard in the exploration and research of the mycological world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The SPORES Program at the Mycological Society of America (MSA) 2024 Annual Meeting aims to diversify mycology by recruiting and supporting early-career students from underrepresented groups. This program provides financial support and mentorship for underrepresented undergraduate students attending the conference for the first time. We plan to recruit, fund, and mentor 20 mentees, pairing them with active MSA members who will guide them before and during the meeting. The workshop will integrate research and education by offering unique educational opportunities, mentorship, networking, and exposure to cutting-edge research. SPORES seeks to create a welcoming environment for underrepresented students, fostering diversity and inclusion in mycology while providing networking opportunities and facilitating collaborations. The long-term goal is to support underrepresented students in mycology and contribute to a more diverse and equitable scientific community. The SPORES workshop will include a series of sessions and activities designed to enhance the educational experience of the participants. Mentees will have the opportunity to attend specialized workshops on topics such as experimental design, data analysis, and scientific communication, providing them with essential skills for their academic and professional development. The workshop will also feature keynote speakers who are experts in various fields of mycology, providing mentees with insights into cutting-edge research and inspiring them to pursue careers in the field. Overall, the SPORES workshop will provide underrepresented students with a unique opportunity to immerse themselves in the world of mycology, gain valuable skills and knowledge, and connect with peers and mentors who can support them in their academic and professional journey.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2422406</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Branco</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sara Branco</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Sara.branco@ucdenver.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000299030</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
<LastName>Torres Cruz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terry J Torres Cruz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ttorresc@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000995009</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Javier</FirstName>
<LastName>Tabima Restrepo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Javier F Tabima Restrepo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jtabima@clarku.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000877318</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clark University]]></Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>016101400</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5084213835</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[950 MAIN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LD3WUVEUK2N5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF CLARK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clark University]]></Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>016101400</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[950 MAIN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>047Y00</Code>
<Text>Plant-Biotic Interactions</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>112Z</Code>
<Text>Racial Equity in STEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>2886</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INSTITUTIONS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~46553</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
