<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Maintenance-Free Water Treatment using Ion Concentration Polarization]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>274994.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>274994</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader/commercial impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is in addressing the critical issue of water scarcity through an innovative membrane-free, chemical-free, more particle tolerant desalination technology. The project aims to make desalination more accessible and affordable, thereby providing communities facing water shortages with new water sources and enhanced water recycling. The technology is designed to be energy-efficient and environmentally sustainable, reducing the barriers to widespread adoption of desalination and water recycling. By advancing the field of water treatment, the project aligns with NSF’s mission to promote the progress of science and advance national health and welfare. The successful commercialization of this technology has the potential to generate significant economic benefits, including job creation and increased tax revenue, while also addressing a pressing environmental challenge.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project proposes a groundbreaking innovation in desalination technology through the development of an Ion Concentration Polarization system. Unlike traditional methods, the ICP system requires significantly less energy and eliminates the need for harmful chemical pre-treatments. The primary innovation lies in the scalable design of the Ion Concentration Polarization system, which can effectively transition from small-scale to large-scale applications. The research aims to optimize the internal flow architecture and electric current distribution to achieve a production capacity of 1,000 liters per hour from an initial 10 liters per hour at bench scale. The methodology includes rigorous experimentation and prototype development to ensure the technology's efficiency and reliability at larger scales. This advancement holds the promise of revolutionizing the desalination process, making it more viable for widespread use and significantly impacting water treatment practices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2422906</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Junghyo</FirstName>
<LastName>Yoon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Junghyo Yoon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[junghyo@nona-technologies.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000995294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NONA TECHNOLOGIES]]></Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394957</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6177106436</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[286 VASSAR ST APT F1]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>TSNFGHLZP317</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NONA TECHNOLOGIES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NONA TECHNOLOGIES]]></Name>
<CityName>Somerville</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021433260</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[444 Somerville Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>537100</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090Z</Code>
<Text>CAS-Critical Aspects of Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~274994</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
