<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Translation Potential of Smart Structural Systems for Seismic Resilience]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jaime A. Camelio</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcamelio@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922061</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this I-Corps project is focused on the enhanced safety, longevity, and resilience offered by an innovative infrastructure system. By mitigating the risks posed by natural and man-made disasters, the technology contributes to the overall sustainability and functionality of infrastructure networks. The project's phased approach to market adoption ensures strategic expansion across diverse sectors, including aerospace, defense, and healthcare. Moreover, the project facilitates cost-effective retrofitting solutions, minimizing disruptions to building occupants and industrial operations during construction. The successful implementation promises substantial tax dollar savings and broader societal benefits, underscoring the transformative potential of the proposed infrastructure solution. Overall, the project's broader impacts extend to fostering safer communities, reducing economic losses, and advancing the seismic structural resilience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translation potential of the technology. This solution is based on the development of a novel structural system that integrates shape memory alloys and steel dampers to enhance the resilience of civil infrastructure while also providing energy efficiency. The core technology focuses on the deliberate integration of structural dampers with engineered connection details into structures to minimize damage to primary structural members while also offering self-centering capabilities. The technology retrofits existing infrastructure assets and constructs new infrastructure assets in a smart and sustainable manner. With its inherent resilience against natural disasters such as earthquakes and energy efficiency, the developed structural system addresses modern infrastructure development while ensuring the longevity and functionality of critical infrastructure assets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2423888</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Togay</FirstName>
<LastName>Ozbakkaloglu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Togay Ozbakkaloglu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[togay.oz@txstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000819794</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas State University - San Marcos]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN MARCOS</CityName>
<ZipCode>786664684</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5122452314</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 UNIVERSITY DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HS5HWWK1AAU5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas State University - San Marcos]]></Name>
<CityName>SAN MARCOS</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>786664684</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 UNIVERSITY DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8616</Code>
<Text>Instr Rsrch,Metro&amp;Std NanTech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
