<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I:  Nanoscale Hybrid Optical Interconnect Platform]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>275000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samir M. Iqbal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smiqbal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927529</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial impacts of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will involve revolutionizing internal computer chip connections, called interconnects, by replacing materials like copper with light-based connections.  The high-speed interconnects are the information highways of modern-day computing systems, and, unfortunately, these highways are hitting fundamental peak capacities and interconnects are now a critical limiter to computer system performance.  This project will advance photonic integrated circuits and computer interconnects by researching commercialization pathways for a new photonic approach, called coupled hybrid plasmonics (CHP), that uses the interaction of light and metals to squeeze light and devices down to nanometer-scale sizes.  Commercialized CHP will potentially enable durable interconnect product advantages in bandwidth, power, area, and cost.  The ultimate go-to-market motivation for commercializing CHP is to enable short-distance (meters down to millimeters), all-optical interconnects and replace electronic interconnects in computer systems (e.g., in the multi-trillion-dollar Information Technology and Telecommunications markets).  The first commercialization challenge for CHP is to develop a manufacturing flow that uses mainstream processing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will bridge the gap between CHP principles and industrial manufacturing.  The primary challenge this project faces is that the CHP effect requires a new multi-layer stack – metals, dielectrics, and semiconductors – that does not exist today in mainstream silicon-photonics/semiconductor chip manufacturing facilities.  Industrial CHP manufacturing recipes and device architectures are the gateway to future proof-of-concept prototypes and then products.  The project will employ industry-standard simulation and modeling tools to rapidly design and evaluate candidate CHP recipes, devices, and circuits.  It will quantitatively benchmark CHP devices and transceivers against today’s state-of-the-art silicon photonic circuits (e.g., ring-resonator based) and assess candidates based on the bandwidth, area, and energy consumption they achieve.  The overall project goal is to create preliminary industrial manufacturing recipes and a design-library of CHP-based devices and transceiver circuits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2423362</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Cline</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian T Cline</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[Brian.Cline@lumoniq.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000938965</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[LUMONIQ INC]]></Name>
<CityName>PALO ALTO</CityName>
<ZipCode>943041130</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5125229424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3175 HANOVER ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GY2LVJBEBBF2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LUMONIQ INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[LUMONIQ INC]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787013258</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[701 Brazos St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>537100</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1084</Code>
<Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY INITIATIVE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~275000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
