<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[SBIR Phase I: Geologic Biosolid Sequestration using Preexisting Wastewater Disposal Wells]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>275000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader/commercial impact of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is in creating a new carbon sequestration method that requires significantly less energy, water, land use, and cost per ton of carbon removed. By addressing technical challenges posed by geologically sequestering biowastes such as human biosolids and agricultural manure, this project attempts to turn a waste problem into a revenue opportunity that also mitigates climate change. It is not yet known if geologic biowaste sequestration can be performed safely, and this lack of known feasibility keeps regulation from being introduced to allow it to be generally permitted. The commercial impact of the project, however, is significant. Current carbon removal credits cost over $800/ton. The proposed project could pave the way to removal of as much as 7 billion tons of CO2e in biowastes alone each year at costs as low as $10 - $20/ton. The technology has the potential to create about 400,000 high-quality jobs in the US and save local governments almost $1 billion in wastewater treatment costs per year that could be reallocated for additional social benefits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to overcome the high-risk technical challenges associated with commissioning new injection well classes, or modifying existing ones, that are focused on geologic sequestration of biowastes. The goal is to demonstrate that biowastes can be injected into the subsurface safely without inducing earthquakes, clogging reservoirs, or creating unsafe pressure buildup. Critically, it will also determine that over long periods, microbially produced greenhouse gases (CO2, methane, and nitrous oxides) emitted from the biosolids do not migrate out of the reservoir and into overlying freshwater aquifers. Other contaminants including bacteria, toxins, and other harmful chemicals will also be monitored to show that they remain permanently sequestered. Furthermore, there is currently no credible protocol for generating carbon removal credits for biowaste sequestration. This project could develop scientific basis for carbon accounting—including CO2e from methane and nitrous oxides—that generates accurate removal and offsetting credits. Thus, the project will attempt to address the unknowns associated with storing solid carbon in the subsurface and the associated carbon accounting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2423575</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brandon</FirstName>
<LastName>Schwartz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brandon Schwartz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[brandon@terraforma.co]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000994192</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[TERRAFORMA CARBON LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>STATE COLLEGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>168013864</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5714208006</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[119 S BURROWES ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 703]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MXTTV9J454M7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TERRAFORMA CARBON LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[TERRAFORMA CARBON LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>STATE COLLEGE</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168013864</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[119 S BURROWES ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>537100</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090Z</Code>
<Text>CAS-Critical Aspects of Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~275000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
