<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel: Participant Support for Micro/Nanoscale Heat and Mass Transfer International Conference]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sumanta Acharya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sacharya@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924509</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 7th ASME Micro/Nanoscale Heat &amp; Mass Transfer International Conference (MNHMT2024) will be held in Nottingham (England), UK, August 5-7, 2024. It follows the previous six conferences held in January 2008, December 2009, March 2012, November 2013, January 2016, and July 2019 with an average of about 300 attendees each. This conference is sponsored and organized by the ASME and located at the University of Nottingham campus. Research and education in micro/nanoscale heat and mass transfer have significantly advanced over the last three decades, with direct impact on many other fields and practices. The conference will provide a forum for researchers, students, and practitioners to exchange ideas on state-of-the-art research and development and identify future research needs. The conference will include keynote and invited presentations, penal discussions, as well as contributed oral and poster presentations. The NSF funding will be used to subsidize the registration fees and travel expenses for selected students, recent graduates, and panelists. Priority will be given to students from traditionally underrepresented groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;MNHMT2024 will encourage and promote academic-government-industry collaborations and international corporations. The conference will bring together experts in micro/nanoscale science and engineering whose research may have lasting impact on the development of the fields of materials, energy, transportation, environment, national security, and health care. The conference will promote and encourage international collaboration and interactions, especially in the new frontiers of micro/nanoscale heat and mass transfer and their impact on emerging technologies. Such interactions will enable future opportunities in engineering research, including new directions and transformative research. As an effort of human resource development, young researchers, including graduate and undergraduate students, postdoctoral researchers, and junior faculty members, especially those from the underrepresented groups, will be particularly encouraged to attend the conference for them to benefit from the opportunity of interactions with their peers and experts in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2423586</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhuomin</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhuomin Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[zhuomin.zhang@me.gatech.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000095189</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Tech Research Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303186395</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[926 DALNEY ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>EMW9FC8J3HN4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[771 Ferst Dr. NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>140600</Code>
<Text>TTP-Thermal Transport Process</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~20000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
