<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Neural Mechanisms of Acoustic Communication Gordon Research Conference and Seminar]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19180.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19180</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Forlano</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pforlano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924611</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The purpose of this project is to support a small meeting (~150 participants) organized by the Gordon Research Conference to discuss the neural mechanisms that underly acoustic, including vocal, communication. A primary focus of the meeting is on comparative and mechanistic approaches to the study of neural circuits that mediate interactive acoustic behavior across taxa that represent 800 million years of evolution. This approach to the study of the neural mechanisms underlying acoustic communication lends insight into general mechanisms of neural function and leads to the development of novel analytical and experimental approaches. The organizers aim to create an environment that generates conversations that will achieve a mechanistic and unifying understanding of the neural underpinnings of acoustic communication by uncovering broadly relevant algorithms. These exchanges will advance acoustic communication research by encouraging new ideas and collaborations, highlighting diversity in the field, and inspiring and mentoring  the next generation of scientists. The request funds will be used to increase institutional diversity and support of early career investigators and students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2024 Gordon Research Conference (GRC) focused on the Neural Mechanisms of Acoustic Communication (NMAC) will also include an associated Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) for pre- and postdoctoral trainees. The aim of the meeting is to assemble top researchers in the field to discuss their latest findings while also providing the opportunity for young investigators and graduate students to present their work alongside these established investigators.  The format of this small meeting  is optimized for discussions and debates and the 2024 NMAC has three specific aims: 1) To advance acoustic communication research by offering an environment that encourages questions and discussion, challenges current thinking, and provides opportunities for new collaborations; 2) to create a unique forum for interaction for researchers from a diversity of communication systems and break down boundaries between communities focused on different model systems, brain regions, research approaches; and 3) to educate new and early career investigators. There exists no meeting like the NMAC GRC for those interested in the neural circuits underlying communication. NMAC is therefore unique within the GRC family because it is focused on a behavior, rather than a brain region (e.g., cerebellum), a method (e.g., optogenetics), or a cellular process (e.g., neuroplasticity). The funds from this project will support a unique opportunity for a diverse gathering of top researchers in a highly interdisciplinary fashion to find new common ground concerning a critical and evolutionary ancient behavior whose production and perception is a fundamental feature of brain function.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2423414</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mala</FirstName>
<LastName>Murthy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mala Murthy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mmurthy@princeton.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000568633</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
<LastName>Schmidt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marc F Schmidt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[marcschm@sas.upenn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000218252</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>771300</Code>
<Text>Activation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>771400</Code>
<Text>Modulation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~19180</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
