<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 43rd Conference of Texas Statisticians]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>21000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tapabrata Maiti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tmaiti@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925307</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 43rd Annual Conference of Texas Statisticians (COTS): AI, Machine Learning, and Other Related Statistical Techniques with Applications in Healthcare, scheduled for May 9-10, 2024, will be hosted at the Houston Methodist Research Institute (HMRI), situated at 6670 Bertner Ave, Houston, TX 77030, USA. Artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML) represent a transformative force across various industries, promising advancements in fields such as medical diagnosis, national security, and crime prevention. These technologies harness the power of data to generate models capable of learning, making decisions, and predicting outcomes. Over time, they refine and adapt, becoming more effective and versatile. However, the efficacy of AI and ML relies heavily on the principles and methodologies provided by statistical science. Statistical techniques underpin the construction of robust models in AI and ML, enabling the interpretation of their outputs. This synergy between AI, ML, and statistical science forms the backbone of cutting-edge advancements in data-driven decision-making. COTS, dedicated to AI, ML, and related statistical techniques serves as a crucial platform for statisticians to exchange insights and forge collaborative opportunities. Such gatherings drive innovation, pushing the boundaries of what is achievable with the integration of AI, ML, and statistical science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;COTS 2024 is dedicated to advancing the frontiers of AI and ML and related statistical techniques, particularly within healthcare. Experts will explore how AI can revolutionize treatment methodologies by harnessing patient-specific data, genetic profiles, and medical histories to tailor treatment plans with unprecedented precision, optimizing efficacy while minimizing adverse effects. COTS 2024 is committed to assembling a diverse array of leading experts, each bringing unique perspectives and expertise to the table. By fostering a robust scientific forum, the conference aims to facilitate rigorous discussions on the most recent research discoveries, spanning from fundamental research to practical applications aimed at enhancing human health and well-being. Moreover, COTS 2024 recognizes the importance of nurturing collaboration and mentorship within the scientific community. Through various networking opportunities and interactive sessions, the conference seeks to bridge the gap between junior and senior researchers, fostering an environment where knowledge exchange flourishes and innovative ideas take root and support underrepresented groups and minorities. In essence, COTS 2024 is not just a conference; it's a catalyst for transformative change, where cutting-edge research converges with real-world applications to shape the future of healthcare and beyond. Moreover, in collaboration with NSF, COTS 2024 is committed to uplifting underrepresented groups and minorities, ensuring that the benefits of progress are inclusive and accessible to all. NSF’s funding for COTS 2024 has facilitated the integration of diverse perspectives and expertise, driving forward the mission of COTS 2024 to enact meaningful change in healthcare and beyond, while prioritizing the empowerment of underrepresented groups and minorities.&lt;br/&gt;Conference website: https://learn.houstonmethodist.org/AI-2024#group-tabs-node-course-default1&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2424045</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sunil</FirstName>
<LastName>Mathur</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sunil Mathur</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[smathur2@houstonmethodist.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000413647</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Methodist Hospital Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>HOUSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>770302602</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7134417885</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6670 BERTNER AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XJUCJAYJWYV1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>METHODIST HOSPITAL, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>XJUCJAYJWYV1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Methodist Hospital Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>HOUSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770302602</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6670 BERTNER AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>126900</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~21000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
