<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Cal State LA and UC Irvine Partnership for Research and Education in Materials (PREM) Center for Bioinspired and Architectured Materials (CBAM)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>349998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Debasis Majumdar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmajumda@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924709</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Partnership for Research and Education in Materials (PREM) Center for Bioinspired and Architectured Materials (CBAM) at Cal State LA, in collaboration with the UC Irvine (UCI) Materials Research Science and Engineering Center (MRSEC) for Complex and Active Materials (CCAM), aims to advance research in bioinspired and architected materials systems for energy, biomedical, and environmental applications while broadening the participation of underrepresented minority (URM) students. A large percentage of Cal State LA students are URM, 80 percent, hail from low-income backgrounds, qualify for Pell Grants, and are the first in their families to attend college. CBAM programs are designed to promote an inclusive research environment and enhance educational experiences, preparing diverse students for successful careers in STEM fields. Combining the strengths and resources of both institutions, the PREM CBAM will develop a workforce equipped to tackle the evolving technical challenges requiring advanced materials solutions. Central to the mission of PREM CBAM is the engagement of undergraduate and graduate students in cutting-edge interdisciplinary research projects. Collaborative research with dual mentors across partner institutions will strengthen students’ research skills and expand their professional networks, preparing them for advanced studies and successful STEM careers. Dual mentoring provides personalized academic advising and career planning. The formalized program includes near-peer mentoring, workshops, seminars, annual summer retreats, pedagogical training, and on-site research experiences at both partnering institutions. These initiatives will cultivate students' sense of belonging, STEM identity, and motivation, thereby improving recruitment, retention, and degree attainment among URM students. Furthermore, professional development opportunities for UCI Ph.D. students and postdocs will prepare academic leaders while fostering a community dedicated to broadening participation in STEM education and research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PREM CBAM initiative focuses on two major research thrusts: (1) bioinspired active materials and interfaces and (2) architectured and hybrid materials systems. These thrusts align with and complement UCI MRSEC’s cross-Interdisciplinary Research Group (IRG) themes, enhancing the collaboration’s impact and scope in studying complex interactive and active material systems. Drawing inspiration from living organisms and manipulating materials across multiple length and temporal scales, CBAM research projects aim to solve contemporary technological challenges in an intricate, sustainable, and eco-friendly manner. Equally important is that the research activities will deepen the understanding of many living systems and enhance the ability to engineer intelligent, adaptive, and responsive materials. An integrated approach combining computational design, simulation, and advanced characterization will be employed to study and control interfacial phenomena and mechanisms in these materials. This ‘materials by design’ methodology will accelerate the development of multifunctional material systems with applications critical in engineering, including energy, infrastructure, environmental remediation, and biomedicine. Through its comprehensive research and educational strategy, PREM CBAM will not only contribute to the advancement of materials science but also play a vital role in developing the next generation of scientists, engineers, educators, and entrepreneurs from historically underrepresented populations. This initiative underscores the importance of linking scientific priorities with societal needs, ensuring that the benefits of technological advancements are accessible to all.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2425229</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoqing</FirstName>
<LastName>Pan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoqing Pan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[xiaoqing.pan@uci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000332126</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yangyang</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yangyang Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yliu114@calstatela.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000745178</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Travis</FirstName>
<LastName>Hu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Travis Hu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[shu17@calstatela.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000769838</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohsen</FirstName>
<LastName>Eshraghi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohsen Eshraghi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mohsen.eshraghi@calstatela.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000683279</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State L A University Auxiliary Services Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900324226</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3233433648</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5151 STATE UNIVERSITY DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>C1ABLRAQTB48</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CAL STATE LA UNIVERSITY AUXILIARY SERVICES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State L A University Auxiliary Services Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900324226</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5151 STATE UNIVERSITY DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>791300</Code>
<Text>PREM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1711</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS EDUCATION AND RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7234</Code>
<Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~349998</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
