<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 11th International Meeting on Intercellular Communication in Plants]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Sztul</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>esztul@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 11th International Meeting on Intercellular Communication in Plants (dubbed PD2024) will bring together scientists from the global community who study plasmodesmata and intercellular trafficking. The meeting&lt;br/&gt;is scheduled to be held from September 17th to 20th, 2024 in St. Louis, Missouri at the Donald&lt;br/&gt;Danforth Plant Science Center. The funds from this award will be used to support the participation of early&lt;br/&gt;career scientists and persons not traditionally represented in science in the meeting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This meeting will focus on recent developments related to intercellular communication in plants&lt;br/&gt;and plasmodesmata, with a focus on: 1)sharing of research discoveries and progress, and (2)foster&lt;br/&gt;collaboration and encourage interdisciplinary approaches that will allow rapid future progress&lt;br/&gt;in plasmodesmata biology. The meeting is organized into seven scientific sessions&lt;br/&gt;arranged around topics including Intercellular trafficking in Development, Structure and&lt;br/&gt;Membranes of Plasmodesmata, Biophysics and Modeling of Plasmodesmata and Intercellular&lt;br/&gt;trafficking in Plant-Microbe Interactions among others. The meeting will include Keynote&lt;br/&gt;presentations from experts in the field of intercellular trafficking and from plant mechanosensing&lt;br/&gt;and plant evolution and diversity. PD2024 will especially focus on early career scientists&lt;br/&gt;with presentations in each session, a special session of ‘lightning talks’ to allow many early&lt;br/&gt;career scientists to share the ‘main stage’, and poster sessions to disseminate their work more&lt;br/&gt;directly with community members.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PD2024 conference is committed to broadening participation and will include&lt;br/&gt;persons from groups traditionally underrepresented in science. The organizing committee itself&lt;br/&gt;comprises a diversity of scientists including women, persons from minority groups and persons&lt;br/&gt;with disabilities. The provision of travel support from this award to members of&lt;br/&gt;underrepresented groups and early career scientists will allows them to participate in this conference. PD2024 will: (1) provide a safe and supportive venue where early career scientist can share their research and ideas, and (2) offer structured activities that foster network building. Funds from this award will also be&lt;br/&gt;used to provide accommodations to persons with disabilities, especially those from the&lt;br/&gt;deaf/hard-of-hearing community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/17/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2425832</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Burch-Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tessa M Burch-Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tburch-smith@danforthcenter.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000618625</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Donald Danforth Plant Science Center]]></Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<ZipCode>631322918</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3145871285</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[975 N WARSON RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MVRJYL6A9VF1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DONALD DANFORTH PLANT SCIENCE CENTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MVRJYL6A9VF1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Donald Danforth Plant Science Center]]></Name>
<CityName>SAINT LOUIS</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631322918</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[975 N WARSON RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>111400</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~15000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
