<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Collaborative Research: XULA-UChicago Partnership for Research and Education in Innovative Composite Materials]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2030</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4194359.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>910000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Debasis Majumdar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmajumda@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924709</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The overall aim of the Partnership for Research and Education in Materials (PREM) between Xavier University of Louisiana (XULA) and the University of Chicago (UChicago) Materials Research Science and Engineering Center (MRSEC) is to broaden participation in materials science and engineering careers by engaging undergraduate students in cutting-edge research. This project is significant to the national interest because of its focus on preparing home-grown talent for specialized careers in materials science and engineering. In addition, the two research thrusts proposed in this project are directly aligned with achieving national energy independence. Specifically, this project focuses on developing new composite materials for high energy density battery systems. By focusing on enhancing both the ionic conductivity and electrochemical stability of solid electrolytes, this project will lead to new materials with the potential to improve the long-term cyclability and energy density of rechargeable battery systems for portable energy storage applications. Beyond research, this project also seeks to engage a younger generation in materials science and engineering. This partnership will establish a new K-12 teacher training program, engage in summer academic enrichment programs at XULA, and begin a new community outreach effort engaging the K-12 community in materials science through art. This project is partially supported with co-funding from the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR), HBCU-UP program in the Division of Equity for Excellence in STEM (EES) in the Directorate for STEM Education (EDU), and Sustainable Chemistry from the Office of Strategic Initiatives (OSI) in the Directorate for Mathematical and Physical Sciences (MPS). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Facilitated by the XULA-UChicago PREM, this project offers newly envisioned research directions that are focused on the development of innovative composite materials through two new research thrusts. Research Thrust 1 focuses on understanding the structure-property relationships of polymer-based composite materials that include organic ionic plastic crystals (OIPC). OIPCs are an emerging class of soft material that resemble ionic liquids in their molecular struc¬ture. These unique organic salts exhibit multiple endothermic thermal transitions that are due to the ability of OIPCs to exhibit both long-range crystalline order and short-range disorder, resulting from localized rotational motion of ionic species comprising the organic salt. The properties of OIPCs are relevant to solid-state energy storage systems, electrochromic devices, and gas separation technologies. Despite their intriguing properties, the structure-property relationships of OIPCs and their polymer composites are an understudied research area within materials science. To close this knowledge gap, Research Thrust 1 will focus on (1) understanding the structure-property relationships of new OIPCs, and (2) 3D-printing of polymer/OIPC composite materials. Research thrust 2 involves the design and study of new composite materials that support solid-state lithium metal batteries and includes research projects that address four main objectives: (1) synthesis and characterization of redox-active bis(naphthoquinones), (2) computational modeling to determine the lithium intercalation mechanism in bis(naphthoquinones), (3) investigating the interfacial reactions between bis(naphthoquinone)-based cathodes and solid polymer electrolyte, and (4) preparing solid polymer electrolyte ionogels comprised of a partially fluorinated polymer matrix. Overall, the materials investigated within Thrust 2 are expected to provide robust battery cyclability in solid-state lithium metal batteries, improve ion transport and enhance the electro¬chemical stability of the polymeric solid electrolyte.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049, 47.076, 47.083</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2425025</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stuart</FirstName>
<LastName>Rowan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stuart J Rowan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[stuartrowan@uchicago.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000488555</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Asem</FirstName>
<LastName>Abdulahad</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Asem I Abdulahad</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[aabdulah@xula.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000784439</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Xavier University of Louisiana]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701251056</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5045205440</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 DREXEL DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HGAAKCE3A7P7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>XAVIER UNIVERSITY OF LOUISIANA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HGAAKCE3A7P7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Xavier University of Louisiana]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701251098</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 DREXEL DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125300</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>159400</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>915000</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090Z</Code>
<Text>CAS-Critical Aspects of Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1711</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS EDUCATION AND RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8249</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Materials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~910000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
