<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: SRCOS Summer Research Conference in Statistics and Biostatistics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>34920.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>34920</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tapabrata Maiti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tmaiti@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925307</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 59th Summer Research Conference (SRC) and Statistics Undergraduate Research Experience (SURE) will be held in Clemson, South Carolina on June 2-5, 2024. The Southern Regional Council on Statistics (SRCOS) is a consortium of statistics and biostatistics programs from 45 universities in 16 states in the Southern region. The SRC is an annual conference sponsored by the SRCOS. The purpose of the SRC is to encourage the interchange and mutual understanding of current research ideas in statistics and biostatistics, and to provide motivation and direction to further research progress. The SRC will give new researchers an opportunity to participate in the meeting and to interact closely with leaders in the field in a manner not possible at larger meetings. In addition to the graduate student participation, the 59th SRC will also include the fifth annual Statistical Undergraduate Research Experience (SURE) from June 3-5, 2024. SURE is a conference within a conference aimed to encourage the participation of undergraduate students from under-represented groups to pursue graduate education and career opportunities in STEM fields. SURE will include events specifically for undergraduate students and undergraduate mentors, such as a panel about career opportunities in statistics, a real data analytics workshop, and a speed-mentoring session with current statistics and biostatistics graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The SRC is particularly valuable for graduate students, isolated statisticians, and faculty from smaller regional schools in the southern region at drivable distances without the cost of travel to distant venues. Speakers will present formal research talks with adequate time allowed for clarification, amplification, and further informal discussions in small groups.  Under the travel support provided by this award, graduate students will attend and present their research in posters to be reviewed by more experienced researchers. Participation in SURE will encourage under-represented students to enter STEM fields, including statistics or biostatistics, and provide training to support this endeavor. The 59th SRC will strengthen the research of the statistics and biostatistics community as a whole and help bridge the gap for under-represented groups to pursue statistics or biostatistics, particularly in the sixteen states of the Southern Region. The SRCOS website can be found here: https://www.srcos.org; the 59th SRC website can be found here: https://www.srcos.org/conference; the SURE website can be found here: https://www.srcos.org/sure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/29/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2426499</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Thompson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katherine L Thompson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[katherine.thompson@uky.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000653124</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Hawk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory S Hawk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[greg.hawk@uky.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>0000A02X0</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/29/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Kentucky Research Foundation]]></Name>
<CityName>LEXINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 S LIMESTONE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[109 KINKEAD HALL]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>H1HYA8Z1NTM5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF KENTUCKY RESEARCH FOUNDATION, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Kentucky Research Foundation]]></Name>
<CityName>LEXINGTON</CityName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 S LIMESTONE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>126900</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~34920</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
