<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Collaborative Research: Multifaceted Data Collection on the Aftermath of the March 26, 2024 Francis Scott Key Bridge Collapse in the DC-Maryland-Virginia Area]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>82484.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>82484</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Siqian Shen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>siqshen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927048</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Rapid Response Research (RAPID) grant project is dedicated to a comprehensive and in-depth collection of data to analyze the extensive societal consequences following the Francis Scott Key Bridge collapse in Baltimore, Maryland. This bridge, being a part of the I-695 beltway, lacks convenient detour options. Thus, its collapse leads widespread disruptions in mobility that affected not just the immediate vicinity but also resonated throughout the broader DC-Maryland-Virginia region. The objective of this project is to methodically gather time-sensitive data on traffic flow and community responses in the wake of this event, providing a detailed assessment of its repercussions. Moreover, this incident also brings a major disruption to freight transportation and supply chains on the East Coast. Given the reliance of freight models on occasionally collected, often proprietary data from commodities surveys, state reports, and customs statistics, this study aims to fill these gaps through an integrated approach for critical trucking, maritime, rail, and supply-chain data collection. These efforts are essential for enhancing the resilience of transportation networks and supply chains against future disruptions. For a broader audience, all the collected data will be made publicly available while carefully following rules for privacy protection and existing data usage agreements. Through sharing detailed findings and facilitating a broader understanding of the incident’s impacts, this project aspires to foster a more informed and prepared society, capable of effectively navigating the challenges posed by major infrastructural failures and their far-reaching impacts on communities and economies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The catastrophic collapse of the Francis Scott Key Bridge in Baltimore, Maryland, has precipitated significant disruptions across urban transportation networks, due to the lack of convenient alternative routes, affecting daily commutes for an estimated 34,000 individuals. Moreover, the collapse introduced considerable logistical difficulties, particularly in the Port of Baltimore, a critical national and international trade node. This project aims to develop a comprehensive data collection methodology, incorporating data integration and enhancement through existing data platforms (e.g., augmentations in commuting, trucking, rail, and marine traffic data alongside social media analytics), comprehensive surveys (e.g., examining travel behavior, community impact, and economic repercussions), and targeted interviews (e.g., exploring governmental responses and adaptations within the logistics network). Should initial analyses indicate a necessity, the spatial and temporal scope of data collection may be expanded to evaluate the impact of the bridge collapse comprehensively. This project is dedicated to improving data transparency and utility, employing elaborate documentation and a diversified strategy for data dissemination, including the development of a dedicated project website, utilization of the NSF NHERI Data Depot for data storage and dissemination, conducting workshops to engage a wide array of stakeholders, and presenting the data architecture at major transportation, infrastructure systems, and disaster conferences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2427233</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shanjiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shanjiang Zhu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[szhu3@gmu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000644454</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Mason University]]></Name>
<CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
<ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4400 UNIVERSITY DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EADLFP7Z72E5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE MASON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>H4NRWLFCDF43</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Mason University]]></Name>
<CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4400 UNIVERSITY DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>006Y00</Code>
<Text>OE Operations Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>163100</Code>
<Text>CIS-Civil Infrastructure Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>163800</Code>
<Text>HDBE-Humans, Disasters, and th</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>029E</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE SYSTEMS MGT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>078E</Code>
<Text>ENTERPRISE DESIGN &amp; LOGISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~82484</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
