<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Translation potential of image-guided proton therapy]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this I-Corps project is the development of a high-resolution, high-sensitivity technology for image-guided proton therapy (a type of radiation therapy) for treating brain cancer. Currently, there is a critical need in the rapidly growing field of proton therapy for precise targeting and minimization of radiation to surrounding healthy tissues. This technology may advance proton therapy by offering real-time, quantitative feedback, enabling more precise and effective treatments. In addition, medical facilities offering proton therapy may improve treatment outcomes and efficiency. By enhancing treatment capabilities and operational throughput, this technology may impact patient care standards and help reduce the long-term costs of cancer care.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translation potential of the technology. The solution is based on the development of a multi-modal brain positron emission tomography (PET)/single photon emission computed tomography(SPECT) scanner that integrates recently developed detector technology, leveraging advancements from particle physics to enhance medical imaging. The core of this technology consists of lutetium–yttrium oxyorthosilicate (LYSO) scintillating crystals coupled on both ends to photosensors (silicon photomultipliers) readout by ultrafast electronics, facilitating unprecedented spatial and temporal resolutions for precise image reconstruction. Experimental results have demonstrated the advanced capability of the technology to provide real-time, advanced diagnostics of proton irradiation. The scanner aims to provide superior imaging and complements existing medical imaging protocols, which may facilitate more informed clinical decision-making and enhance the effectiveness of proton therapy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2427867</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karol</FirstName>
<LastName>Lang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karol Lang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lang@physics.utexas.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000188932</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 INNER CAMPUS DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6AFQPN18437</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>AUSTIN</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121139</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 INNER CAMPUS DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
