<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Solid State Studies in Ceramics GRC: Merging Atomistic and Continuum Analysis of Defects and Interfaces Across Varying Length-Scales]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>4998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nazanin Bassiri-Gharb</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nbassiri@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922430</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-Technical Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project supports the  Gordon Research Conference (GRC), Solid State Studies in Ceramics, titled "Merging Atomistic and Continuum Analysis of Defects and Interfaces Across Varying Length Scales” and the corresponding Gordon Research Seminar (GRS), taking place from August 5 to 9, 2024. The GRC conference, and its associated  aims to discuss the latest discoveries, advancements, and future directions in the ceramics basic science, ranging from the atomic to the macro scale, spanning from point defects to surfaces and interfaces. Applications of the basic science of solid state ceramics include: energy storage technology (e.g., batteries and solar cells), sensors and actuators, and high temperature structural and protective coatings. This conference is highly committed to the participation of diverse and underrepresented groups. Qualified, US Nationals, speakers, postdoctoral researchers, young graduate student researchers, women, and minorities, all of whom are essential contributors to the conference, are sponsored (including registration and National Travel) through grant funds to foster an environment that is amicable to scientific collaboration and discovery. Broader Impacts: The discussion leaders promote the most provoking and cutting-edge science, and encourage participation of student attendees. An important outcome is that US National graduate students and early career professionals interact with senior experts in an open and shared forum with plenty of time for interaction in smaller groups in between sessions or at meal time.  The conference's "Power Hour" on Monday afternoon aims to promote the discussion of challenges that women, and minorities face in science and engineering fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project supports the Solid State Studies in Ceramics Gordon Research Conference subtitled "Merging Atomistic and Continuum Analysis of Defects and Interfaces Across Varying Length Scales,"  and the corresponding Gordon Research Seminar (GRS). The seminar and the conference is held August 5 to 9, 2024, and is designed to discuss the most recent advances in the field of ceramics basic science by bringing together experts across disciplines, including cutting edge microscopy, advanced processing science, and multi scale modeling and simulation, to discuss the latest discoveries, advancements, and future fields directions in the field of ceramics. The support of domestic travel and registration of US Nationals, including key speakers,  postdoctoral researchers, young graduate student researchers, women, and minorities, is being used to promote participation of the conference participants. The overall goal is to advance the development of new approaches to create materials with exceptional and unprecedented behaviors by developing a fundamental understanding of the atomistic and nanometer scale interactions with surfaces and interfaces. These behaviors are dictated by multi physical driving forces, which are coupled, both physically and microstructurally. A significant amount of current research in ceramics is integrally connected to its processing and manufacturing, displaying multi physical behavior, and in many cases leading to unprecedented applications. Broader Impacts: This conference is highly committed to the participation of diverse and underrepresented groups.  While speakers and discussion leaders were selected only based on their scientific excellence and leadership in the field, a third of the speakers and discussion leaders are female. The discussion leaders are expected to bring out the most provoking and cutting-edge science, and to encourage participation of student attendees. An important outcome is that graduate students and early career professionals interact with senior experts in the field in an open and shared forum with plenty of time for interaction in smaller groups in between sessions or at meal time. It should be noted that we have been able to bring a significant number of international speakers (and attendees), broadening the learning potential of the community.  The conference “Power Hour” on Monday afternoon is community event to  discuss challenges that women, and minorities face in science and engineering fields. 6891&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2427224</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edwin</FirstName>
<LastName>Garcia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edwin Garcia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[redwing@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000101910</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>177400</Code>
<Text>CERAMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~4998</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
