<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel Grant: 2024 Biogenic Hydrocarbons and the Atmosphere Gordon Research Conference and Seminar; Castelldefels, Barcelona, Spain; June 8-14, 2024]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30480.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30480</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Biogenic Hydrocarbons and the Atmosphere Conference and Seminar will bring together an international group of researchers in the biological, ecological, and atmospheric sciences from universities, government laboratories, and private research institutes to promote discussion of information and ideas on topics of contemporary interest related to biogenic hydrocarbons in the atmosphere. This will be the 11th Gordon Research Conference to address the topic of “Biogenic Hydrocarbons and the Atmosphere,” the first of which was in 2000. The conference is organized with the overall goal of reporting and discussing the latest research findings on novel sources of biogenic hydrocarbons, ecosystem-atmosphere interactions, atmospheric transport, and atmospheric chemistry/air quality modulated by hydrocarbon emissions.  This meeting brings together leaders and scholars to gain a better understanding of the biological, ecological, and atmospheric roles of biogenic hydrocarbons in a unique, cross-disciplinary environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theme of the 2024 Biogenic Hydrocarbons and the Atmosphere Conference and Seminar conference is “Biosphere-Atmosphere Interactions and Impacts in the Anthropocene.” The meeting will concentrate on the latest developments in the field, including the synthesis, release and subsequent oxidation of biogenic hydrocarbons, their molecular genetics and the biochemical mechanisms through which they are produced, stored and released, as well as their function at a cellular level, and the role they play in photosynthesis, stomatal control and plant defense mechanisms. Once released to the atmosphere, these biogenic hydrocarbons rapidly react with ozone, nitrate, and hydroxyl radicals, leading to the formation of oxidants in the atmosphere, ozone, and secondary organic aerosol. These secondary products affect air quality and regional and global climate thus creating feedbacks to the land surface.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Conference will take place in Castelldefels, Barcelona, Spain from June 9th to 14th, preceded by the Gordon Research Seminar (GRS), held for early career researchers, on June 8th-9th. NSF support will primarily be used for registration and travel for women, early career scientists, post docs, and graduate students from the US to participate in the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2427028</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karena</FirstName>
<LastName>McKinney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karena A McKinney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kamckinn@colby.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000056318</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/01/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>152400</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5247</Code>
<Text>POST DOC/TRAVEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~30480</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
