<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: International symposium on crystalline organic metals, superconductors, and magnets]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12600.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eugenia Kharlampieva</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ekharlam@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924520</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical Description: This award funds the international symposium on crystalline organic metals, superconductors, and magnets (ISCOM) to be held from September 22 - 27, 2024, in Anchorage, Alaska (USA). This workshop aims to advance the fundamental understanding of molecular and molecule-based materials, inspire new collaborations, and provide opportunities for the education and growth of a diverse group of scientists. A particular emphasis is on the role of predictive theory in developing the properties of molecular and molecule-based materials in the Materials Genome Initiative spirit.  Traditionally, the ISCOM workshop rotates between Europe, Asia, and North America, and it has not been in the United States since 2005. One of the workshop tasks is to rebuild the community after the COVID era by focusing on contemporary research topics and placing a priority on the involvement of junior scientists as speakers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description: The workshop focuses on molecular and molecule-based materials, including the interface between theory and experiment. This event intends to provide an opportunity to show off scientific accomplishments and create new partnerships and international collaborations to leverage complementary expertise in the field. A diverse group of US and international speakers is arranged for student tutorials and technical sessions. Presented topics include but not be limited to Superconductivity, Non-equilibrium phenomena, Magnetic and conducting metal-organic frameworks, Hydrogen and halogen bonding, Molecular ferroelectrics and multiferroics, Self-assembled heterostructures, Chemistry of new molecular materials, Light-induced properties, Spin liquids and frustration, glassy charge and spin states, Basic science for molecular devices, Spintronics, Quantum information, and Databases and machine learning. DMREF support is requested to partially cover costs for the conference venue to help reduce the registration fees.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2427937</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janice</FirstName>
<LastName>Musfeldt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janice L Musfeldt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[musfeldt@utk.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000388630</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Knoxville]]></Name>
<CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>379960001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 ANDY HOLT TOWER]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FN2YCS2YAUW3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>LXG4F9K8YZK5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Knoxville]]></Name>
<CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379960001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 ANDY HOLT TOWER]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>829200</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>054Z</Code>
<Text>(MGI) Materials Genome Initiative</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8400</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~12600</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
