<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Translation potential of metallic nanoparticles that can replace precious metal nanoparticles for catalytic applications]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this I-Corps project is the development of metallic nanoparticles that can replace precious metal nanoparticles for catalytic applications. Precious metal nanoparticles, such as platinum (Pt) nanoparticles, are currently used as catalysts in the energy industries even though they are expensive. This technology is designed to produce multi-metallic nanoparticles with the aim to replace or reduce noble metals used in the energy sector. The business hypothesis is that the multi-metallic nanoparticles will serve as better catalysts and electrodes than the presently used Pt nanoparticles and help energy industries such as oil and gas, fuel cells, and hydrogen production to improve cost-effectiveness, process efficiency, and reliability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translation potential of a laser-based technique that enables the ultrafast fabrication of a variety of multi-metallic nanoparticles. This nanosecond laser-processing technology enables the creation of multi-metallic nanoparticles of different sizes, shapes, and compositions covering a large dimensional and compositional space. The technology is based on the rapid shriveling of thin films into nanoparticles through the laser-induced melt-phase dewetting phenomenon, which subsequently accumulates in a droplet shape via thermally-driven mass transport and surface energy minimization. The approach has been tested to manufacture several monometallic noble metal (platinum, gold, and silver), non-noble metal (nickel and cobalt), bimetallic (silver-cobalt, gold-nickel, gold-cobalt, and copper-nickel), and multi-element alloy (nickel-cobalt-chromium and nickel-cobalt-chromium-iron-copper) nanoparticles. The technology produces nanoparticles that exhibit high-quality, contamination/oxidation-free characteristics that may be tailored for intended applications including improved functional properties such as shelf-life, stability, and catalytic activity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2427339</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ritesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Sachan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ritesh Sachan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rsachan@okstate.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000813172</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oklahoma State University]]></Name>
<CityName>STILLWATER</CityName>
<ZipCode>740781031</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4057449995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[401 WHITEHURST HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NNYDFK5FTSX9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OKLAHOMA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oklahoma State University]]></Name>
<CityName>STILLWATER</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>740781031</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[401 WHITEHURST HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
