<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[2024 Colloidal Semiconductor Nanocrystals Gordon Research Conference and Gordon Research Seminar]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Meulenberg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmeulenb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927106</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-Technical Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2024 Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) and Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Colloidal Semiconductor Nanocrystals will take place in early July 2024. These conferences aim to foster an interdisciplinary exchange among chemists, physicists, engineers, and other scientists to advance understanding and innovation in nanotechnology. By discussing emerging research and forming collaborative networks, the conferences will enhance scientific and technological developments in areas critical to national interests such as renewable energy, healthcare, and electronics. The GRC and GRS play an important role in nurturing the next generation of scientists, providing young researchers and postdocs with opportunities to present their work, engage in peer discussions, and gain exposure to the wider community of scientists working in the nanocrystal field. The GRC and GRS also aim to increase participation from underrepresented groups in nanoscience by providing an inclusive environment with opportunities for mentorship and selecting a diverse group of participants. The cutting-edge scientific developments discussed at these conferences have potential applications in a variety of areas including renewable energy, electronics, and disease detection and treatment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The field of colloidal semiconductor nanocrystals is flourishing at the frontiers of discovery in nanoscience and nanotechnology. This Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) will focus on recent advances in understanding and controlling the chemistry, physics, and engineering of colloidal semiconductor nanocrystals and related nanostructures. The conference will bring together the community of chemists, physicists, materials scientists, spectroscopists, theoreticians, and engineers to discuss major advances, pressing challenges, and new directions, build collaborations, and foster the next generation of scholars in this vibrant interdisciplinary field. The two-day GRS program includes a keynote lecture, two poster sessions, and two sessions of talks by graduate students and postdocs selected from GRS applicant abstracts. The five-day GRC program features 34 invited talks. Additionally, the GRC program will have four poster sessions, where approximately 150 posters will be presented by conference applicants on topics related to colloidal semiconductor nanocrystals and related assemblies, fostering an open and vigorous exchange of ideas. The conference participants were chosen to emphasize the focus on innovative and transformative research in the field from a diverse group of scientists. The conference is structured to foster interactions between junior researchers and senior researchers and provide a stage for junior researchers to present their work to the nanocrystal scientific community. Nanocrystals have potential applications in a variety of areas such as renewable energy, electronics, disease detection and treatment, and so on. The access to cutting-edge unpublished results presented at this conference will accelerate scientific progress toward these societal goals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/23/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2428968</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gordana</FirstName>
<LastName>Dukovic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gordana Dukovic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[gordana.dukovic@colorado.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000554527</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/23/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>176200</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8611</Code>
<Text>Energy Efficiency and End Use</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8614</Code>
<Text>Nanomaterials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~10000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
