<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Access to Science and Scholarship: A workshop on establishing a robust and sustainable research agenda for the future of open scholarly communication]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49650.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49650</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Feeney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfeeney@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The health of our national research enterprise is closely tied to the effectiveness of the scientific publishing ecosystem, which represents the primary way knowledge is broadcast, quality is assured, and reputations are established. The open science movement is driving change in this ecosystem, yet many in the research community remain unaware of the value and implications of open science. This workshop affords the academic community and its funders an opportunity to develop an evidence-driven approach to promote increased access to research outputs and meet the diverse needs of distinct research communities.  This workshop advances understanding of the urgent questions that the scientific community is facing due to shifts in academic publication praxis and dissemination publishing models.  The workshop provides a platform for critical dialogue aimed at enhancing our understanding and management of the scientific enterprise through open, data-driven research practices. Specifically, we focus on measures of research quality and assurance, cost, fairness, choice, and multiplicity.  By leveraging the collective expertise of participants, the workshop endeavors to cultivate a research agenda that is both consensus-driven and evidence-based, offering significant potential to advance knowledge of open science and public access.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop on securing a robust and sustainable future for research communication aspires to fortify the foundations of STEM communications, with a focus on educating and engaging a broad audience, including funders. The primary outputs from this meeting are a publicly available recording of the proceedings and a comprehensive report that includes a call to action intended to inform decision-making and investment at research funding organizations including the U.S. National Science Foundation, related federal agencies, and private philanthropies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is co-funded by the Science of Science: Discovery, Communication, and Impact program; the Cyberinfrastructure for Public Access and Open Science program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070, 47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2428384</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
<LastName>Brand</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amy E Brand</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[amybrand@mit.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000936797</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/14/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>125Y00</Code>
<Text>Science of Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>741400</Code>
<Text>NSF Public Access Initiative</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~49650</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
