<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Translation Potential of Extreme Textiles]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Molly Wasko</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mwasko@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924749</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this I-Corps project is based on the development of a nanomaterial assembly technology for enhancing the functionality of polymers and textiles. This innovative approach addresses a critical need for sustainable and non-toxic methods in the textile industry. By enabling advanced features such as fire retardancy, antimicrobial properties, and health monitoring capabilities without compromising the mechanical strength of textiles, this technology can significantly impact various sectors, including healthcare, environmental monitoring, and consumer goods. The potential applications range from smart textiles in wearable technology, eco-friendly industrial materials, and flexible electronics to meet the growing demand for sustainable and high-performance products. This technology could also reduce environmental pollution and health risks associated with traditional textile treatments, fostering a safer and more sustainable industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translation potential of the technology. The solution is based on the development of an eco-friendly nanomaterial assembly technology for precise and durable functionalization of polymer substrates and textiles. The technology utilizes a water-based, non-destructive process to deposit nanomaterials onto hydrophobic and chemically inert surfaces, ensuring the retention of the substrate’s or textile's inherent properties. Thus far, research has demonstrated the technology's effectiveness in adding multiple functionalities to textiles while maintaining their strength and flexibility. Technical results have shown successful applications in various textile types, paving the way for scalable and commercially viable production methods. The project aims to validate the market potential of this technology through extensive customer discovery and develop a robust business model to bring this innovative solution to market.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2429097</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bo</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bo Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[bo.li@villanova.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000757023</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Villanova University]]></Name>
<CityName>VILLANOVA</CityName>
<ZipCode>190851603</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6105194220</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 E LANCASTER AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>EYNYSU6L8ZX6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VILLANOVA UNIVERSITY IN THE STATE OF PENNSYLVANIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>HJEPRMTQMMR4</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Villanova University]]></Name>
<CityName>VILLANOVA</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>190851603</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 E LANCASTER AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1633</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
