<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 In Vivo Ultrasound Imaging Gordon Research Conference and Seminar]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4990.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>4990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephanie George</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>stgeorge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927825</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the 2024 In Vivo Ultrasound Imaging Gordon Research Conference and Seminar, which will be held August 24 -30, 2024, at Waterville Valley, a Conference Center located in Waterville Valley Resort, West Dover, VT.  The theme of the Conference is “Advances in Translational Applications of Imaging in Disease Diagnosis, Staging and Therapy.”  Ultrasound is a ubiquitous clinical imaging modality supported by a dynamic and scholarly research community. Until the inaugural Gordon Research Conference (GRC), no conference or professional meeting was explicitly dedicated to basic science ultrasound research with the goal of improving diagnostic ultrasound. The first GRC on in vivo ultrasound imaging found an exceptional reception and outstanding feedback. Discussion among the 2022 participants quickly demonstrated the strong need to propose a Gordon Research Seminar (GRS). GRC and GRS will provide an intimate forum for scientific exchange among scientists and researchers whose primary area of research is the development of novel biomedical ultrasound techniques and approaches. The proposed inaugural GRS will feature 3 sessions with dedicated discussion leaders and 11 student speakers selected from abstract submissions. A 4-member panel discussion on mentorship will conclude the GRS and create a transition to the GRC for 5 days of fostering discourse and mentoring between trainees and researchers/educators.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2024 In Vivo Ultrasound Imaging Gordon Research Conference and Seminar is divided into two sections, the first section being in the Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) format and the second in the Gordon Research Conference format.  This is the second GRC (first held in 2022) and first GRS on In Vivo Ultrasound Imaging.  The GRS, which is designed for graduate students and post docs and will be held prior to the GRC, will highlight innovations and applications of next generation functional ultrasound imaging and include a mentorship session.  The overall structures for both GRS and GRC sessions are the same.   Sessions with three of four speakers will be managed by discussion leaders. Presentations will be followed by ample discussion time.  Both sections host two poster sessions.  For the GRS sessions, 3 discussion leaders and 4 panel experts have been invited and the speakers will be selected from submitted abstracts.  For the GRC, 37 scientists with a focus in ultrasound research have been invited to attend as either invited speakers or discussion leaders.  Topics for the 3 GRS scientific sessions are:  Functional Imaging Modes, Functional Ultrasound Imaging in Therapeutic Applications, and Functional Ultrasound Neuroimaging.  Topics for the 8 GRC scientific sessions are:  Wearable Ultrasound Devices, Materials, and Application; Neuromodulation; Ultrasound Imaging and Therapy in Immunotherapy; Contrast Enhanced Ultrasound; Novel Uses of Contrast Agents; Lung Ultrasound; Applications of Machine Learning in Ultrasound; and Ultrasound Therapy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2429807</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Oliver</FirstName>
<LastName>Kripfgans</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Oliver D Kripfgans</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[greentom@umich.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000711678</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>534500</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~4990</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
