<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Santa Cruz Developmental Biology Meeting 2024]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Allen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>akallen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928011</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Santa Cruz Developmental Biology Conference 2024 (SCDB) brings together scientists, researchers, educators, and students to explore unifying principles of development and homeostasis in a broad diversity of animal and plant species. The conference fosters interdisciplinary collaborations that will lead to innovative solutions for accelerating scientific breakthroughs with immediate implications for reproductive and regenerative medicine.  The SCDB meeting plays an important role in training the next generation of developmental biologists, by providing a platform for trainees to present their research. These opportunities inspire and equip students with a set of skills to pursue diverse careers in life sciences. Additionally, the conference aims to help equip the next generation of developmental biologists to serve as professional stewards for our society and planet through one of its broader impact activities- the organization of a workshop focused on communicating science and building sustainability into research labs. Enhanced communication to the lay-public and awareness of the environmental impact of scientific research will motivate researchers to incorporate sustainably-minded practices into their work culture. Additional broader impact activities include travel support for 30 participants from historically excluded groups and early career stages. SCDB serves as a catalyst for scientific innovation, education, and societal benefit. Its impact extends beyond the scientific community, contributing to public health and education by fostering a more knowledgeable and scientifically engaged society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fundamental research in developmental biology has transformed our understanding of congenital diseases, stem cell biology, oncology, and regenerative medicine. Ongoing work at the cutting edge of this field promises to provide novel insights in the years to come, with important implications for our understanding of genetic, molecular and cellular processes of multicellular life, and with important implications for understanding how interacting developmental processes give rise to emergent properties that result in the development of complex phenotypes and structures. The 2024 meeting is focused on unifying principles of organismal development and a group of leading scientists have been invited to discuss diverse experimental and theoretical developmental models across diverse organisms. To address fundamental challenges of development of multicellular life, the 2024 meeting is organized around the following integral topics: Cell-Cell Communication, Theory and Modeling in Development, Active Matter and Mechanics, Convergent and Divergent Morphogenesis, Cellular Transitions and Plasticity, Information Processing and Gene Regulatory Networks and New Technologies and Synthetic Approaches. Broader impact activities include workshops on both scientific communication and designing environmental sustainability into research labs to prepare the next generation of developmental biologists to serve as stewards for society and our planet. This proposal will financially support members of historically excluded groups to be able to attend the meeting. In sum, the 2024 meeting will build on past successes while incorporating best practices for inclusive conferences, highlighting recent breakthroughs, and serving as a catalyst for new approaches and ideas in this rapidly evolving field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2430601</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ali</FirstName>
<LastName>Shariati</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ali Shariati</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[alish@ucsc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000850715</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Cruz]]></Name>
<CityName>SANTA CRUZ</CityName>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1156 HIGH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>VXUFPE4MCZH5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SANTA CRUZ</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Cruz]]></Name>
<CityName>SANTA CRUZ</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1156 HIGH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>111900</Code>
<Text>Animal Developmental Mechanism</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~15000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
