<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: American Chemical Society Fall 2024 Graduate Student Symposium, Denver, CO, August 18-22]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18416.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18416</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Graduate Student Symposium (GSS) is a day-long, student-organized event held during the Spring and Fall National Meetings of the American Chemical Society (ACS). This activity has been conducted since 2005 under the guidance of the Graduate Student Symposium Planning Committee of the American Chemical Society (ACS), typically with base funding from ACS supplemented by funding from other organizations. A team of students from the University of Buffalo has been selected as the Graduate Student Symposium Planning Committee (GSSPC) to organize this symposium at the ACS Fall 2024 National Meeting in Denver, Colorado. The GSSPC is responsible for all aspects of the symposium, including selecting a topic, inviting speakers, securing funds, and recruiting and mentoring the next GSSPC. The symposium's theme, "Breaking the Mold: Building Communication to Promote Green and Sustainable Practices," revolves around examining and discussing innovative approaches to implementing green and sustainable practices in both academia and industry. The primary objectives of the symposium are: (1) to raise awareness about the relevance and need for green chemistry in academic and industrial settings, (2) to establish a collaborative platform for the exchange of best practices among the attendees, and (3) to promote the notion that green and sustainable practices are achievable without compromising quality, cost, and efficiency. To maximize engagement and knowledge dissemination, the symposium will consist of two events: 1) Lectures by invited speakers (i.e., individuals from academia, scientists who work at government agencies, and active members working in industry), and 2) Green Connect: A networking event held to facilitate engagement among speakers, sponsors, and attendees. This gathering will create an environment conducive to forging meaningful connections that could transcend the symposium. Invited speakers have been thoughtfully chosen by the planning committee as distinguished lecturers to ensure a comprehensive and holistic perspective of the dynamic and evolving landscapes of green and sustainable chemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The symposium aims to address the pressing need for environmental protection and sustainability by fostering essential dialogue between the attendees and representatives from academic institutions, industries, and non-profit organizations. Moreover, the symposium intends to promote equity and diversity, inclusivity, and accessibility in STEM. The selection of speakers reflects a deliberate effort to represent a diverse scientific and cultural community to provide attendees with role models whose experiences and challenges resonate with a diverse audience. Additionally, the GSSPC presents a valuable opportunity for the professional development of both the current and future Graduate Student Symposium Planning committees.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2430639</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Luis</FirstName>
<LastName>De Jesus Baez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Luis R De Jesus Baez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ldjesus@buffalo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000877925</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>AMHERST</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282577</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[520 LEE ENTRANCE STE 211]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>LMCJKRFW5R81</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>GMZUKXFDJMA9</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142604600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[532 Natural Science Complex]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>140100</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~18416</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
