<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Granular Matter GRC and GRC Particle Systems Science and Extreme Environments]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>32000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>32000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Lawrence</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jlawrenc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922425</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports scientists and engineers, those early in their career and from under-represented groups and non-R1 institutions, to attend the eleventh Gordon Research Conference (GRC) on Granular Matter to be held on June 21-26, 2024, at Stonehill College in Easton, MA. The award will also support early career scientists and engineers attending the associated Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) held during the two days before the GRC meeting at the same place. The goal of the 2024 GRC and GRS on Granular Matter is to significantly enhance the rate of progress in understanding granular materials in complex settings relevant to many disciplines. To do so, these meetings are designed to meet the following objectives: 1. Presentation and discussion of unpublished, novel findings from researchers of a wide range of backgrounds; 2. Cultivation and promotion of emerging junior researchers, particularly, those from underrepresented groups; 3. Provide opportunities for extended discussion periods and interaction among researchers of different disciplines, backgrounds, and professions whose paths do not normally overlap. This year’s invited sessions are cross populated by researchers with backgrounds in geoscience, physics, materials science, engineering, and applied mathematics. Various activities for diversifying the impact of the meeting are included, such as a career panel with participants from different sectors and a program on inclusion, equity, and professional development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Granular matter, conglomerations of particles or of particles and fluids, is abundant in nature and industry, studied in multiple science and engineering disciplines. Much is now known about the dynamics of relatively simple particulate systems (e.g., narrow size distributions of spherical particles) at low solids concentrations, and inroads have been made into behaviors of denser systems. Yet, fundamental questions remain out of reach for more complex systems including: (1) angular/aspherical particles (2) widely dispersed in size and density, (3) interacting via complex forces (e.g., via interstitial fluids). To address these fundamental challenges requires efforts from scientists and engineers coordinated across research fields. The biannual GRC and GRS provide platforms for researchers to discuss and exchange recent developments in granular matter and unmet needs across disciplines. The meeting chairs and vice-chairs are experts in granular media at different career stages and work in complimentary disciplines. The meeting structure emphasizes presentations of new work, and discussion among researchers from disciplines that typically do not have intersecting platforms. The GRC/GRS provide time for: (1) formal discussion after every talk (guided by a discussion leader), (2) time in the afternoons for informal follow-on discussions and late afternoon poster sessions, and (3) shared meals, all of which maximize interactions between participants across backgrounds during the meeting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.049, 47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2430452</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Hill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly M Hill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[kmhill@umn.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000152590</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XL5ANMKWN557</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName>EAST GREENWICH</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028183454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5586 POST RD UNIT 2]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>141500</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>157400</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>171000</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>745800</Code>
<Text>Geomorphology &amp; Land-use Dynam</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~32000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
