<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Translation potential of tethering above-ground storage tanks to prevent flood failures]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jaime A. Camelio</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcamelio@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922061</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this I-Corps project is the development of a new methodology to prevent the failure of above ground oil storage tanks during floods. This solution is based on the development of a new methodology to tether new and existing above ground oil storage tanks to prevent failures during floods. Notably, out of approximately 5,000 tanks in the Houston Ship Channel, about a thousand tanks are located within the 100-year flood plain, making them vulnerable to storm surge-induced flood events. The failure of the tanks can lead to catastrophic oil spills. The proximity of the tanks to rivers and oceans increases the spill-induced environmental risks and chances of wildlife habitat damage in the surrounding areas. Furthermore, in many areas, such as the Houston Ship Channel and in Louisiana, tanks are located very close to residential communities. Potential spills caused by the failure of the tanks would expose these communities to hazardous substances. The improved flood safety tanks afforded by this tethering system will help improve the well-being of the surrounding communities and the environment. Furthermore, several regional economies, such as in Louisiana and Houston, TX, depend on industries that use these tanks extensively. The improved safety of tanks can make economies and communities that are dependent on these industries more resilient to floods.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translation potential of the technology. The solution uses anchor chairs, steel cables, and screw/helical piles to tether new and existing above ground oil storage tanks to prevent failures during floods. The steel cables will connect the anchor char that will be welded to the tank with the helical pile which will be embedded into the ground. The solution will allow controlled flotation of the tank during floods to avoid failure of the bottom plate, located on the underside of the tank. The existing anchor chair designs only consider vertical forces, so controlled floatation of the tanks also requires anchor chairs to sustain horizontal forces. The new design for anchor chairs can sustain a horizontal force of up to 36% of the vertical force. Computer simulations were used to develop the design for the new anchor chair. Industry feedback will be used to further develop this solution and the anchor chair design.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2430546</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sabarethinam</FirstName>
<LastName>Kameshwar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sabarethinam Kameshwar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[skameshwar1@lsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000812667</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Santosh</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghimire</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Santosh Ghimire</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sghim11@lsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>0000A05PF</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>BATON ROUGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>708030001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 HIMES HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECQEYCHRNKJ4</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>BATON ROUGE</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708030001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 HIMES HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
