<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Cosmovisions of the Pacific: Advancing Indigenous - non-Indigenous Collaboration with Integrity (Cosmovisions)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49965.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49965</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allen Pope</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>apope@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cosmovisions of the Pacific will bring together ~20 Indigenous and non-Indigenous knowledge holders, researchers, educators and other persons interested in establishing a more formal network of collaborators and in the co-creation of guiding principles necessary for collaboration with integrity across cultures. Recently, we’ve seen the cost of cross-cultural conflict as exemplified by protests against the construction of the Thirty-Meter Telescope in Hawaii, the Keystone XL (KXL) pipeline project, and elsewhere. As big science and commercial endeavors require more robust collaborations between Indigenous and non-Indigenous groups, we must find ways of understanding, working and communicating across cultures and ways of knowing. Cosmovisions will deeply explore Indigenous and non-Indigenous knowledge building using a participatory design approach.  This will include a 3-day Gathering and preparation where participants engage in deep conversations about differing approaches to research questions and scenarios, network building activities, and presentations that uncover the similarities and differences in approaches to knowledge building across Indigenous and non-Indigenous cultures. The strategic objectives for work proposed to be delivered in a post-Gathering report include: Identifying priority opportunities for Indigenous - non-Indigenous collaboration, developing recommendations that will help guide successful Indigenous and non- Indigenous collaboration, and developing and initial network of Indigenous and non-Indigenous researchers, educators, knowledge holders and others who are committed to collaboration across cultures and ways of knowing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Cosmovisions Gathering agenda will be developed based on a formalized framework which are centered around empowerment, reframing, engaging critically, allowing Indigenous people to set the agenda, and integrating ways of knowing. This project is intentionally and deeply interdisciplinary. As “cosmovisions” are worldviews by which various individuals and cultures connect with the universe around them, the workshop will have a co-created structure going into the Gathering, but allow for flexibility and generative outcomes. Cosmovisions will create a space where through authentic collaboration, Indigenous persons can more fully engage, benefit, and engage with non-Indigenous STEM practitioners. In addition, through dissemination efforts including potential future gatherings and a post-Gathering report, the broader STEM community and society more generally, will come to understand and benefit from the “two-eyed” seeing approach to knowledge building.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2430977</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>YASMIN</FirstName>
<LastName>CATRICHEO</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>YASMIN V CATRICHEO</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ycatricheo@aui.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000826252</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anica</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller-Rushing</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anica Miller-Rushing</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[amillerrushing@aui.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000994108</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Associated Universities, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>VIENNA</CityName>
<ZipCode>221807300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024621676</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2650 PARK TOWER DR STE 700]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NZBMKZMW68N3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ASSOCIATED UNIVERSITIES INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Associated Universities, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>VIENNA</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>221807300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2650 PARK TOWER DR STE 700]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>069Y00</Code>
<Text>AccelNet - Accelerating Resear</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5974</Code>
<Text>CHILE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5977</Code>
<Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5983</Code>
<Text>JAPAN AND KOREA PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7561</Code>
<Text>CANADA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~49965</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
