<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Advancing a Cultural Understanding of the Mexican Networks for inclusion into AccelNet GERI]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49610.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49610</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kara C. Hoover</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kchoover@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922235</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>We have embarked on building a global ecological Network-of-Networks (NoN), starting with six Environmental Research Infrastructures (ERIs) from around the world. This effort has come together under the Global Ecosystem Research Infrastructure (GERI) to tackle challenges in understanding the biosphere’s response to environmental changes, providing crucial information to researchers, managers, and decision-makers alike. We now seek to extend GERI to include networks and infrastructures from currently unrepresented regions and countries. As part of establishing a strong foundation in GERI, the founding networks have developed a robust cross-cultural understanding and social fabric within which they operate. GERI’s NoN roadmap, network activities, and scientific goals build upon this foundation. Since each network has its own cultural identity—including individual-to-national ways of working, perceptions, biases, strengths, science disciplines, challenges, and synergies—bringing new networks into GERI requires careful consideration of these diverse attributes and how they manifest in building a more inclusive and effective NoN. This workshop proposal is designed to assess the cultural framework and roadmap the inclusion of five Mexican networks into GERI. The workshop aims to (i) engender ownership and belonging among these networks within the GERI NoN, thereby facilitating an inclusive partnership; (ii) bring together early-career representatives from each network who will integrate GERI into their ongoing professional careers; and (iii) begin roadmapping an equitable process for the inclusion of new networks from underrepresented regions into GERI.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Global Ecosystem Research Infrastructure (GERI) aims to enhance our understanding of and response to environmental changes affecting our planet. Our goal is to expand GERI by incorporating additional networks from regions and countries that have not yet been represented. The GERI network is built on a strong foundation of diverse cultural practices and scientific approaches from its founding members. As we integrate new networks, it’s crucial to consider their unique cultural identities and ways of working to enhance the network’s overall effectiveness. This specific workshop focuses on integrating five Mexican networks into GERI. The workshop aims to make these networks feel a part of GERI, helping them recognize the benefits and contributions they can bring to this international effort. We will also start to plan how to include more networks from other underrepresented regions fairly and effectively. The workshop will gather early-career professionals from these Mexican networks, who will use GERI throughout their careers, helping them to build their skills and understanding of global ecological challenges. It’s also an opportunity to learn from each other and apply these insights more broadly in future collaborations. In short, this workshop is not just about integrating these Mexican networks into GERI; it's about preparing the next generation of scientists to work collaboratively across borders and disciplines, fostering a diverse and inclusive global scientific community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2431267</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>SanClements</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael SanClements</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[msanclements@battelleecology.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000644208</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Battelle Memorial Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432012696</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6144244873</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[505 KING AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F125YU6SWK59</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BATTELLE MEMORIAL INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Battelle Memorial Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432012696</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[505 KING AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>069Y00</Code>
<Text>AccelNet - Accelerating Resear</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5922</Code>
<Text>MEXICO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~49610</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
