<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel: NSF Student Travel Grant for 6th IEEE International Conference on Trust, Privacy, and Security in Intelligent Systems and Applications (IEEE TPS 2024)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dan Cosley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcosley@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928832</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide funding to support about 15 students at U.S.-based institutions to attend the 6th IEEE International Conference on Trust, Privacy and Security in Intelligent Systems, and Applications (IEEE TPS 2024).  TPS is an international multidisciplinary forum for presentation of state-of-the art innovations, along with discussion among academic/industry researchers, policy makers, and practitioners on issues related to trust, privacy, and security in emerging systems that are supported, attacked, and/or defended by artificial intelligence and machine learning.  Students selected for travel awards will be exposed to research problems discussed by established researchers, have the opportunity to interact and network with other researchers, and benefit from a special student mentoring session with successful researchers who can act as role models in the field.  The conference will be held in Washington D.C. on October 28-30, 2024 and is co-located with the 10th IEEE Conference on Collaboration and Internet Computing (IEEE CIC 2024), and the 6th International Conference on Cognitive Machine Intelligence (IEEE CogMI 2024).  Funding from this award will also allow students to interact with attendees from these other conferences, increasing their exposure to research and researchers from other disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Attending IEEE TPS will be very valuable to students interested in the intersection of two of the most critical areas of research around computing: trust, privacy, and security with artificial intelligence and machine learning. Students will get an opportunity to present their research, receive feedback, and network with established researchers in these areas, allowing young researchers who may otherwise not have the opportunity to attend to develop both the field and their careers.  The conference organizers also seek to broaden participation in computing through widely advertising the opportuntity of funding and considering diversity of participants in terms of research topics as well as personal and institutional backgrounds as part of the selection criteria, along with the relevance and strength of the applicant's research to the conference and the availability of other support.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2431905</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wenqi</FirstName>
<LastName>Wei</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wenqi Wei</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[wenqiwei@fordham.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000938220</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Fordham University]]></Name>
<CityName>BRONX</CityName>
<ZipCode>104585149</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7188174086</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[441 E FORDHAM RD]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>ECESTN2SSVH1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FORDHAM UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Fordham University]]></Name>
<CityName>BRONX</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>104585149</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[441 E FORDHAM RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>806000</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025Z</Code>
<Text>SaTC: Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~15000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
