<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Detection, removal, and safe destruction of PFAS from semiconductor manufacturing waste streams]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sumanta Acharya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sacharya@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924509</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Per-and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS) have been a key part of semiconductor manufacturing due to their unique physical and chemical properties. PFAS are currently essential for processes including photolithography and etching, and are used as auxiliary fluids in pumps and lubricants. While there are efforts to find alternatives for fluorochemicals, their unique physicochemical properties make replacement difficult.  As such, PFAS use in semiconductor manufacturing currently poses a challenge for balancing supply-chain security and environmental sustainability. The current workshop is proposed to provide a platform for experts to identify, discuss, and prioritize topics of urgent concern for the detection, removal, and safe destruction of PFAS from semiconductor manufacturing streams. A key goal of this workshop will be to identify the research needs for PFAS treatment that are unique to the semiconductor industry and provide a roadmap for future PFAS treatment technologies to ensure environmental sustainability. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By bringing experts from academia, industry, and national agencies, the workshop aims to cover three critical areas for PFAS abatement: (i) discuss and review analytical methods to characterize the PFAS-containing materials used in the semiconductor industry and detect the releases of PFAS in the waste streams, (ii) brainstorm and create roadmaps to guide the cost-effective and low-energy technologies for PFAS removal and separation in semiconductor waste streams, especially short-chain PFAS, and (iii) provide insights into the future opportunities and challenges for energy-efficient and cost-effective PFAS destruction methods. The proposed workshop will support education and awareness on PFAS as well as provide insights into PFAS related issues in semiconductor manufacturing. Products from the workshop will have a clear impact on environmental sustainability and water quality through addressing an urgent topic of PFAS abatement in a critical manufacturing industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2432110</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiao</FirstName>
<LastName>Su</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiao Su</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[x2su@illinois.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000799868</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/18/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>URBANA</CityName>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S WRIGHT ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Y8CWNJRCNN91</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>URBANA</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S WRIGHT ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>144000</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~99000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
