<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps:  Translation potential of a compostable, pressure-sensitive adhesive]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact of this I-Corps project is the development of a pressure sensitive adhesive to be used in labeling, packaging, and tapes that may be home composted. Currently, adhesives are nondegradable products. There are no commercially viable, home-compostable, pressure-sensitive adhesives. The developing composting infrastructure in the United States must accept compostable food packaging to divert food waste and emissions from landfills. Contamination of non-degradable plastic labels in the compost poses a risk to the growth of the composting infrastructure. This adhesive is designed to replace current nondegradable labels and is a drop-in replacement in many applications. This solution may reduce landfilling of post-consumer plastic waste, helping to address the growing plastic pollution problem. In addition, this adhesive will be the first home-compostable, pressure-sensitive adhesive meeting the current market need for sustainable adhesives to pair with other biodegradable materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translation potential of a home compostable pressure-sensitive adhesive. Pressure-sensitive adhesives are widely used to easily fasten two materials together in either a permanent or non-permanent bond. Currently, all commercially available pressure-sensitive adhesives are nondegradable, and most will be sent to a landfill at the end of their useful life. This adhesive was developed based upon a market need for sustainable adhesives to pair with other current and emerging sustainable materials. The adhesive material biodegrades via microorganisms at 21°C, allowing the material to be home composted. In addition, the organic carbon of the material is mineralized greater than 90% within four months of testing, which is eight months faster than the one year permitted for certification testing. The mechanical properties of the adhesives are tunable to meet a wide range of application demands in line with current commercial adhesives and can be either removable or permanent. The adhesive has been produced in pilot reactors, applied successfully on an industrial coating line, and successfully converted into labels using conventional die-cutting and processing equipment. With a current 72% biobased carbon content, the adhesive further reduces the reliance on petroleum feedstocks. The technoeconomic analysis completed for the material shows commercial viability as a sustainable product.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2433711</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Evan</FirstName>
<LastName>White</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Evan M White</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[emwhite@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000845870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Locklin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason Locklin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jlocklin@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000075874</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dan</FirstName>
<LastName>Geller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dan Geller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[dgeller@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000667896</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306020001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[623 BOYD GRADUATE RESEARCH CTR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Q2LKTLYJM4P8</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306020001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[623 BOYD GRADUATE RESEARCH CTR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>802300</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1238</Code>
<Text>TECH FOR SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
