<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: SACNAS GeoFutures]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99933.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99933</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>RISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div of Res, Innovation, Synergies, &amp; Edu</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>elrom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927709</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Faculty and staff at the University of Washington (UW) will organize and lead Geo-Futures, a conference-based mentoring program housed within the SACNAS (Society for Advancing Hispanics/Chicanos and Native Americans in Science) 2025 annual Conference. The Geo-Futures program will provide student attendees with mentoring before, during and after their SACNAS experience to help them maintain the intellectual momentum acquired during their time at the conference. The program will help students develop a sense of identity and community within the geosciences and assist them as they begin to define their academic and professional pathways through the discipline. Setting GeoFutures within the annual SACNAS Conference also allows for engagement with the cultural value structures of the many students participating in the program. GeoFutures will use previously developed engagement strategies for recruiting and retaining the diverse assemblage of students and perspectives that will be required to address the emerging workforce needs of 21st century geoscience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;GEO-Futures offers students pre and post-conference training that will prepare them to participate in a national scientific research conference. Pre-conference activities will provide students with an introduction on navigating a scientific conference and networking with geoscientists in attendance. Conference activities will provide students with an introduction to original research being conducted in the geosciences and examples of career pathways that can be engaged in as a professional geoscientist. Beyond providing students with guidance on how to pursue academic and professional careers in geoscience, the Geo-Futures program can help them understand how their diverse talents and perspectives can contribute to a scientific workforce that will be called upon to address the emerging needs of 21st century geoscience research. The Geo-Futures program forms an alliance among geoscience professionals to help recruit, engage and retain students in the geosciences through a conference based mentoring program. The Geo-Futures program aims to 1) recruit up to forty student participants, with an emphasis on students from underrepresented groups and those with prior experience in an NSF Geoscience Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program; 2) engage students in innovative professional development activities; 3) provide students with high-caliber mentoring; and; 4) provide rigorous support and training for students to ensure continued interest and involvement in the geosciences. The social context of the program is the demographics of the U.S, whose composition is rapidly changing, with little reflection of this change seen in the ranks of geoscience workforce in the United States. A vigorous recruitment and outreach effort leverages connections with early career research programs from across the United States and the experience of the leaders in engaging with students from underrepresented student populations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/16/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2433487</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Corey</FirstName>
<LastName>Garza</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Corey Garza</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cgarza2@uw.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000527215</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HD1WMN6945W6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981951016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 BROOKLYN AVE NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>178Y00</Code>
<Text>GOLD-GEO Opps LeadersDiversity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1733</Code>
<Text>GEOSCIENCE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~99933</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
