<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Travel: Student Travel Support for 2025 IEEE International Microwave Biomedical Conference (IMBioC)]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2025</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jenshan Lin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jenlin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927360</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The IEEE International Microwave Biomedical Conference (IMBioC) provides a global platform for sharing latest innovations and developments in radio frequency (RF) and wireless technologies, antennas, and electromagnetic theory for biomedical and biological applications. The conference is financially sponsored by the IEEE Microwave Theory and Technology Society, with technical co-sponsorships from the IEEE Antennas and Propagation Society and the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society. The 2025 IEEE IMBioC will be held in Kaohsiung, Taiwan on April 15-17, 2025. To support the training of the next-generation scientists and engineers working on RF and wireless technologies for biomedical applications, this NSF grant will provide travel support for 10 U.S. students to present their research papers at the conference and learn the state-of-the-art developments in this field. The travel grants will be awarded competitively to undergraduate and graduate students from U.S. universities who will present their accepted papers at the conference. The awardees will be selected by a review committee of the conference and the paper quality will be considered in the selection process. The proposed travel support will have long-term and broad impacts on the participating students' career developments and contribute to the U.S. STEM workforce development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first IEEE IMBioC was formed in 2018 by merging two IEEE conferences: the IEEE BioWireless Conference and the IEEE International Microwave Workshop Series on RF and Wireless Technologies for Biomedical and Healthcare Applications. Since then, the conference has become an important forum for the international research communities in microwave technologies, antennas, wireless technologies, medicine, and biology to meet and discuss cutting-edge research results in this interdisciplinary field. The IEEE IMBioC in 2025 will have a diverse range of activities, including oral sessions, poster sessions, short courses, exhibitions, student paper competition, and invited talks by leading experts. Students attending the conference will learn about the latest state-of-the-art RF and wireless technologies for emerging biomedical applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2434147</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pai-Yen</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pai-Yen Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[pychen@uic.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000682445</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[809 S MARSHFIELD AVE M/C 551]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>W8XEAJDKMXH3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>CHICAGO</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[809 S MARSHFIELD AVE M/C 551]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>756400</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>105E</Code>
<Text>RF/Microwave &amp; mm-wave tech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>108E</Code>
<Text>Bioelectronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8028</Code>
<Text>Sensor Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~25000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
