<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: INCLUDES FY24: Workshop: Faculty Development Four Corners STEM Alliance (FCSA) Workshop to Enhance Competitiveness in Proposal Preparation, August 22-24, 2024]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>98642.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>98642</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div. of Equity for Excellence in STEM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sally O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>soconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924552</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Wyoming will conduct a three-day hybrid workshop designed to empower faculty members and administrators from tribal colleges, community colleges, and predominantly undergraduate institutions across the Mountain States—Colorado, Montana, Utah, and Wyoming. This innovative workshop will host 30 participants, providing them with a unique platform to interact directly with NSF program staff and peers. The goal is to foster an environment where participants are welcomed and trusted, where they can directly engage with NSF program staff and peers to master the art of grant proposal writing. This effort is not just about securing funds; it’s about advancing scientific discovery, enhancing educational opportunities, and promoting inclusive excellence.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Participants will engage in an immersive experience that focuses on the development of effective grant proposals, targeting both federal funding and private sector grants. The workshop is structured to enhance understanding of the grant application process, offering hands-on guidance in creating compelling narratives and robust budget plans. The workshop is designed to offer comprehensive training that delves into the development of grant proposal writing, ensuring participants are well-versed in the key elements that make a successful application. It aims to guide attendees in crafting proposals that not only meet but resonate with the National Science Foundation’s funding priorities, enhancing the likelihood of securing support. Key features of the workshop include: 1) Interactive Sessions with NSF program staff to demystify the grant application process; 2) Practical tools such as budget management templates to aid in the development of NSF grant applications; 3) Collaborative opportunities for participants to form networks, fostering long-term partnerships and knowledge exchange; and 4) Focused Breakout Groups to address critical topics like responsible research conduct, mentoring, diversity, and scientific communication. By the end of the workshop, attendees will not only gain valuable insights into grant writing but also leave with a tangible product to enhance their proposal submissions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop is supported by NSF Directorate for Biological Sciences (BIO), STEM Education (EDU) and Computer and Information Science and Engineering (CISE), and the Office of Integrative Affairs (OIA).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070, 47.074, 47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2435285</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Camellia</FirstName>
<LastName>Okpodu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Camellia M Okpodu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[cokpodu@uwyo.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000251604</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName>LARAMIE</CityName>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3077665320</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 E UNIVERSITY AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>FDR5YF2K32X5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WYOMING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>FDR5YF2K32X5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wyoming]]></Name>
<CityName>LARAMIE</CityName>
<StateCode>WY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>820712000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 E UNIVERSITY AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wyoming</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WY00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y00</Code>
<Text>Eddie Bernice Johnson INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>113900</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>173Y00</Code>
<Text>CISE MSI Research Expansion</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<Fund>
<Code>04002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~98642</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
