<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 NSF CyberTraining/SCIPE Principal Investigator (PI) Meeting]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sharmistha Bagchi-Sen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>shabagch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project supports a two-day meeting for leaders and researchers from the National Science Foundation's (NSF) CyberTraining and SCIPE programs. The event will be held alongside the meeting for the NSF's Cyberinfrastructure for Sustained Scientific Innovation program. It will serve as a platform for participants to share information about their projects, goals, and outcomes with others, including NSF program directors. The meeting will also feature joint sessions for discussing common interests and exploring opportunities for collaboration between the two NSF programs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CyberTraining/SCIPE PI meeting aims to advance the community-building efforts of previous workshops by providing a platform for principal investigators (PIs) to share technical information about their projects with peers, NSF program directors, and other stakeholders. This forum facilitates the exploration of innovative topics within NSF workforce development communities, promotes discussions on best practices, and generates new ideas for training and educating CI researchers and professionals. The organizing committee will select speakers and panelists based on their research and expertise in CyberTraining for CI and SCIPE professionals. PIs will also provide valuable feedback on emerging opportunities and challenges, and participants will include projects identified by NSF as complementary to CyberTraining/SCIPE initiatives, fostering potential collaborations. This year's program will explore the impact of AI on the NSF research and training community. The workshop will convene leading experts from the CyberTraining/SCIPE and broader communities to discuss and share innovations and best practices in training CI and SCIPE professionals, aiming to lay the groundwork for the next generation of professionals who will support the development, deployment, and utilization of NSF resources and services. These collaborations will enhance productivity, accelerate research in science and engineering, and significantly increase the impact of NSF's output, particularly within OAC’s programs. The selection of speakers and panelists will ensure diversity and alignment with best practices for broadening STEM participation. Additionally, the organizing committee will extend invitations to relevant NSF program managers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2435580</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Thomas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary P Thomas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mpthomas@ucsd.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000421108</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/05/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 GILMAN DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>UYTTZT6G9DT1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 GILMAN DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>50</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA50</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>044Y00</Code>
<Text>CyberTraining - Training-based</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>122Z</Code>
<Text>CI Training and Professionals</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7361</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND WORKFORCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~99998</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
